<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Complex Event Processing</title>

  <para>Although several tries were made, there isn't up to date any broadly
  accepted definition on the term Complex Event Processing. The term Event by
  itself is frequently overloaded and used to refer to several different
  things, depending on the context it is used. Defining terms is not the goal
  of this guide and as so, lets adopt a loose definition that, although not
  formal, will allow us to proceed with a common understanding.</para>

  <para>So, in the scope of this guide:</para>

  <important>
    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Event</primary>
      </indexterm> <emphasis role="bold">Event</emphasis>, is a record of a
    significant change of state in the application domain.</para>
  </important>

  <para>For instance, on a Stock Broker application, when a sell operation is
  executed, it causes a change of state in the domain. This change of state
  can be observed on several entities in the domain, like the price of the
  securities that changed to match the value of the operation, the owner of
  the individual traded assets that change from the seller to the buyer, the
  balance of the accounts from both seller and buyer that are credited and
  debited, etc. Depending on how the domain is modelled, this change of state
  may be represented by a single event, multiple atomic events or even
  hierarchies of correlated events. In any case, in the context of this guide,
  Event is the record of the change on a particular data in the domain.</para>

  <para>Events are processed by computer systems since they were invented, and
  throughout the history, systems responsible for that were given different
  names and different methodologies were employed. It wasn't until the 90's
  though, that a more focused work started on EDA (Event Driven Architecture)
  with a more formal definition on the requirements and goals for event
  processing. Old messaging systems started to change to address such
  requirements and new systems started to be developed with the single purpose
  of event processing. Two trends were born under the names of Event Stream
  Processing and Complex Event Processing.</para>

  <para>In the very begginings, Event Stream Processing was focused on the
  capabilities of processing streams of events in (near) real time, where the
  main focus of Complex Event Processing was on the correlation and
  composition of atomic events into complex (compound) events. An important
  (maybe the most important) milestone was the publishing of the Dr. David
  Luckham's book "The Power of Events" in 2002. In the book, Dr Luckham
  introduces the concept of Complex Event Processing and how it can be used to
  enhance systems that deal with events. Over the years, both trends converged
  to a common understanding and today these systems are all refered as CEP
  systems.</para>

  <para>This is a very simplistic explanation to a really complex and fertile
  field of research, but sets a very highlevel and common understanding for
  the concepts this guide will introduce.</para>

  <para>The current understanding of what Complex Event Processing is may be
  briefly described as the following quote from Wikipedia:</para>

  <important>
    <blockquote>
      <attribution><citetitle><link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_event_processing">Wikipedia</link></citetitle></attribution>

      <para>"<indexterm><primary>Complex Event Processing</primary></indexterm><emphasis role="bold">Complex Event
      Processing</emphasis>, or CEP, is primarily an event processing concept
      that deals with the task of processing multiple events with the goal of
      identifying the meaningful events within the event cloud. CEP employs
      techniques such as detection of complex patterns of many events, event
      correlation and abstraction, event hierarchies, and relationships
      between events such as causality, membership, and timing, and
      event-driven processes."</para>
    </blockquote>
  </important>

  <para>In other words, CEP is about detecting and selecting the interesting
  events (and only them) from an event cloud, finding their relationships and
  infering new data from them and their relationships.</para>

  <note><para>For the remaining of this guide, we will use the terms 
   <emphasis role="bold">Complex Event Processing</emphasis>
  and <emphasis role="bold">CEP</emphasis> as a broad reference for any of 
  the related technologies
  and techniques, including but not limited to, CEP, Complex Event Processing,
  ESP, Event Stream Processing and Event Processing in general.</para></note>
</section>
