<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Drools Fusion</title>

  <para>Event Processing use cases, in general, share several requirements and
  goals with Business Rules use cases. These overlaps happen both on the
  business side and on the technical side.</para>

  <para>On the Business side:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Business rules are frequently defined based on the occurrence of
      scenarios triggered by events. Examples could be: </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On an algorithmic trading application: take an action if the
          security price increases X% compared to the day opening price, where
          the price increases are usually denoted by events on a Stock Trade
          application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>On a monitoring application: take an action if the temperature
          on the server room increases X degrees in Y minutes, where sensor
          readings are usually denoted by events.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Both business rules and event processing queries change frequently
      and require immediate response for the business to adapt itself to new
      market conditions, new regulations and new enterprise policies.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>From a technical perspective:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Both require seemless integration with the enterprise
      infrastructure and applications, specially on autonomous governance,
      including, but not limited to, lifecycle management, auditing, security,
      etc.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Both have functional requirements like pattern matching and
      non-functional requirements like response time and query/rule
      explanation.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Even sharing requirements and goals, historically, both fields were
  born appart and although the industry evolved and one can find good products
  on the market, they either focus on event processing or on business rules
  management. That is due not only because of historical reasons but also
  because, even overlapping in part, use cases do have some differences and
  different requirements.</para>

  <para></para>

  <para></para>
</section>
