<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="UsingUserTasksInProcesses"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Using User Tasks in our Processes</title>
       <para>jBPM supports the use of human tasks inside processes using a special User Task node defined by the BPMN2 
              Specification(as shown in the figure above). A User Task node represents an atomic task that needs to be 
              executed by a human actor.

       </para>
       <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                            fileref="images/TaskService/user-task.png"/>
              </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
       <para>
              [Although jBPM has a special user task node for including human tasks inside a process, human tasks are considered 
              the same as any other kind of external service that needs to be invoked and are therefore simply implemented as a 
              domain-specific service. See the chapter on domain-specific processes to learn more about this.]
       </para>
       <para>
              A User Task node contains the following core properties:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Actors: The actors that are responsible for executing the human task. 
                            A list of actor id's can be specified using a comma (',') as separator.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Group: The group id that is responsible for executing the human task. 
                            A list of group id's can be specified using a comma (',') as separator.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Name: The display name of the node.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>TaskName: The name of the human task. This name is used to link the task to a Form. It also represent the internal
                     name of the Task that can be used for other purposes.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>DataInputSet: all the input variables that the task will receive to work on. Usually you will be interested in copying 
                      variables from the scope of the process to the scope of the task. (Look at the data mappings section for an example)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>DataOutputSet: all the output variables that will be generated by the execution of the task. Here you specify all the 
                            name of the variables in the context of the task that you are interested to copy to the context of the process. 
                            (Look at the data mappings section for an example)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Assignments: here you specify which process variable will be linked to each Data Input and Data Output mapping.
                            (Look at the data mappings section for an example)</para>
              </listitem>
             
       </itemizedlist>
       <para>
              You can edit these variables in the properties view (see below) when selecting the User Task node.
       </para>
       <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                            fileref="images/TaskService/properties-panel.png" width="400"/>
              </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
       <para>
              A User Task node also contains the following extra properties:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Comment: A comment associated with the human task. Here you can use expressions.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Content: The data associated with this task.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                     <para>Priority: An integer indicating the priority of the human task.</para>
              </listitem>
 
              <listitem>
                     <para>Skippable: Specifies whether the human task can be skipped, i.e., whether the actor may 
                            decide not to execute the task.</para>
              </listitem>
              
             
              <listitem>
                     <para>On entry and on exit actions: Action scripts that are executed upon entry and exit of this node, respectively.</para>
              </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                            fileref="images/TaskService/properties-panel-extra.png" width="400"/>
              </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
</section>
