<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <para>This section describes how to get started with Drools Flow.  It
  will guide you to create and exectue your first Drools Flow process.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>The best way to get started is to use the Drools Eclipse IDE.  This
    is a plugin for the Eclipse developement environment that allows users to
    create, execute and debug Drools processes and rules.</para>

    <para>To get started, you need an Eclipse 3.3.x, as well as the Eclipse
    Graphical Editing Framework (GEF) plugin installed.  Eclipse can be downloaded
    from <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/">
    http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/</ulink> (choose either the Eclipse IDE for Java
    Developers or the Eclipse Classic).  Eclipse GEF can also be downloaded from
    <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/gef/downloads/">
    http://www.eclipse.org/gef/downloads/</ulink> (choose the corresponding version) or
    by using an update site.</para>

    <para>Download the Drools Eclipse IDE plugin from <ulink
    url="http://www.jboss.org/auth/drools/downloads.html">
    http://www.jboss.org/auth/drools/downloads.html</ulink>, unzip it in your eclipse
    folder and (re)start Eclipse.  If installation was successful, the Drools menu
    action should appear in the top menu bar.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating your first process</title>

    <para>You should switch to the Drools perspective within Eclipse first, as this will
    open all the relevant views for you.  You can do this by clicking on the Open Perspective
    button (top right of your screen) and selecting Other ... -> Drools.</para>

    <para>A new project wizard can be used to setup an executable project to start using
    processes immediately. This will setup a basic structure, classpath, sample
    process and execution code to get you started.  To create a new Drools Project, select
    File -> New -> Project ... and in the Drools folder, select Drools Project.  This should
    open the following dialog:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" format="BMP" role="" 
                   fileref="project-wizard1.bmp"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Give your project a name and click Next.  In the following dialog you can select
    which elements are added to your project by default.  Since we are creating a new process,
    deselect the first two checkboxes and select the last two.  This will generate a sample
    process and a class to execute this process in your project.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" format="BMP" role="" 
                   fileref="project-wizard2.bmp"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The end result should look like this and contains:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>ruleflow.rf : the process definition, which is a very simple process containing
        a start node (the entry points), and action node (that prints out 'Hello World') and an
        end node (the end of the process).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RuleFlowTest.java : a Java class that executes the process.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The necessary libraries are automatically added to the project classpath as a
        Drools library.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" format="BMP" role="" 
                   fileref="initial.bmp"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The RuleFlow editor contains a graphical representation of your process definition.  It
    consists of nodes that are connected.  The editor shows the overall control flow, while the
    details of each of the elements can be viewed (and edited) in the Properties View at the bottom.
    The editor contains a palette at the left that can be used to drag-and-drop new nodes, and an
    outline view at the right.</para>

    <para>This process is a simple sequence of three nodes.  The start node defines the start of the
    process.  It is connected to an action node (called 'Hello' that simply prints out 'Hello World'
    to the standard output.  You can see this by clicking on the Hello node and checking the action
    property in the properties view below.  This node is then connected to an end node, signalling
    the end of the process.</para>

    <para>While it is probably easier to edit processes using the graphical editor, user can also
    modify the underlying XML directly.  The XML for our sample process is shown below (note that we
    did not include the graphical information here for simplicity).  The process element contains
    parameters like the name and id of the process, and consists of three main subsections: a header
    (where information like variables, globals and imports can be defined), the nodes and the
    connections.</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;process xmlns="http://drools.org/drools-4.0/process"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xs:schemaLocation="http://drools.org/drools-4.0/process drools-processes-4.0.xsd"
         type="RuleFlow" name="ruleflow" id="com.sample.ruleflow" package-name="com.sample" &gt;

  &lt;header&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;

  &lt;nodes&gt;
    &lt;start id="1" name="Start" x="16" y="16" /&gt;
    &lt;action id="2" name="Hello" x="128" y="16" dialect="mvel" &gt;System.out.println("Hello World");&lt;/action&gt;
    &lt;end id="3" name="End" x="240" y="16" /&gt;
  &lt;/nodes&gt;

  &lt;connections&gt;
    &lt;connection from="1" to="2" /&gt;
    &lt;connection from="2" to="3" /&gt;
  &lt;/connections&gt;

&lt;/process&gt;
</programlisting>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Executing your first process</title>
    <para>To execute this process, right-click on RuleFlowTest.java and select Run As - Java
    Application.  When the process in executed, the following output should appear on the 
    console:</para>
<programlisting>
Hello World
</programlisting>

    <para>If you look at the RuleFlowTest code (see below), you will see that executing a process
    requires a few steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You should first create a knowledge base.  A knowledge base contains all the process
        definitions and rules that are relevant in your application.  This knowledge base can be
        created only once and can be reused.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Next, you should create a session to interact with the engine.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, you can start a new process instance of our process by invoking the
        startProcess("ruleflowId") method of the session.  This will start the execution of your
        process.  Since our process does not contain any wait states, the process will execute
        until it is completed in this case, passing through the start, action and end node.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

<programlisting>
package com.sample;

import java.io.InputStreamReader;
import java.io.Reader;

import org.drools.RuleBase;
import org.drools.RuleBaseFactory;
import org.drools.StatefulSession;
import org.drools.compiler.PackageBuilder;
import org.drools.rule.Package;

/**
 * This is a sample file to launch a ruleflow.
 */
public class RuleFlowTest {

  public static final void main(String[] args) {
    try {
      //load the process
      RuleBase ruleBase = createKnowledgeBase();
      // create a new session
      StatefulSession session = ruleBase.newStatefulSession();
      // start a new process instance
      session.startProcess("com.sample.ruleflow");
    } catch (Throwable t) {
      t.printStackTrace();
    }
  }

  /**
   * Creates the knowledge base by loading the process definition.
   */
  private static RuleBase createKnowledgeBase() throws Exception {
    // create a builder
    PackageBuilder builder = new PackageBuilder();
    // load the process
    Reader source = new InputStreamReader(
      RuleFlowTest.class.getResourceAsStream("/ruleflow.rf"));
    builder.addProcessFromXml(source);
    // create the knowledge base 
    Package pkg = builder.getPackage();
    RuleBase ruleBase = RuleBaseFactory.newRuleBase();
    ruleBase.addPackage(pkg);
    return ruleBase;
  }

}
</programlisting>

    <para>Congratulations, you have successfully executed your first process!  You can now
    start experimenting and designing your own process by modifying our example.  Note that
    you can validate your process by clicking on the green check box action in the upper toolbar.
    Processes will also be validated upon save and errors will be shown in the error view. Or
    you can continue reading our documentation to learn about our more advanced features.</para>

  </section>

</chapter>
