<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>JBoss Rules comes with an own implementation for the Java Rule Engine
  API (known as JSR94). The API allows you to change easier from your current
  rule engine to JBoss Rules. If your code is making use of Java Rule Engine
  API, you just need to change the implementation class, which you need to
  give to the RuleServiceProviderManager, to use JBoss Rules as your rule
  engine.</para>

  <para>Well, thus easy it is not, because there is not standarized Rule
  Language, yet. You will have to translate existing rules to the Drools Rule
  Language which is supported by JBoss Rules. W3C is planning a <ulink
  url="http://www.w3.org/TR/2006/WD-rif-ucr-20060323/">Rule Interchange
  Format (RIF)</ulink> and <ulink url="http://ruleml.org/">RuleML</ulink> is
  as well an interesting candidate for a Standard Rule Language. Till there is
  Standard Rule Language, which will be supported by JBoss Rules, you are
  invited to contribute your transformer, which is transforming rule language
  X to the Drools Rule Language. The transformer might be a script, class,
  stylesheet or everything what is doing the job.</para>

  <para>The following sections deal with the use of the Java Rule Engine API.
  There is a part which explains the specification and one how the Java Rule
  Engine API can be used in example. If you know the specification, just skip
  the specification section. There are some interesting links inside of the
  references section giving you all the information about the Java Rule Engine
  API you might need.</para>

  <para>Before you start complaining about that you need to write more code
  and that there is less functionality than if you make use of the native
  Drools API, it is mentioned now, that a standard represents everytime the
  lcd (least common denominator) of the specification drivers. That
  functionality which is common around all the rule engines.</para>

  <para>At the time of writing this documentation the JSR 94 implementation is
  not supporting rules in XML and Domain Specific Languages. This will change
  in one of the next releases. Please be appreciative of this fact and keep an
  eye on the actual release notes.</para>
</section>
