<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ReteOOSection"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" 
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>ReteOO Algorithm</title>

  <para>The <emphasis>ReteOO</emphasis> was developed throughout the 3, 4 and 5 series releases. It takes the RETE
    algorithm and applies well known enhancements, all of which are covered by existing academic literature:</para>
  <para>Node sharing<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Sharing is applied to both the alpha and beta network. The beta network sharing is always from the root
          pattern.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Alpha indexing<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Alpha Nodes with many children use a hash lookup mechanism, to avoid testing each result.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Beta indexing<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join, Not and Exist nodes indexing their memories using a hash. This reduces the join attempts for equal
          checks. Recently range indexing was added to Not and Exists.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Tree based graphs<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join matches did not contain any references to their parent or children matches. Deletions would have to
          recalculate all join matches again, which involves recreating all those join match objects, to be able to find
          the parts of the network where the tuples should be deleted. This is called symmetrical propagation. A tree
          graph provides parent and children references, so a deletion is just a matter of following those references.
          This is asymmetrical propagation. The result is faster and less impact on the GC, and more robust because
          changes in values will not cause memory leaks if they happen without the engine being notified.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Modify-in-place<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Traditional RETE implements a modify as a delete + insert. This causes all join tuples to be GC'd, many of
          which are recreated again as part of the insert. Modify-in-place instead propagates as a single pass, every
          node is inspected </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Property reactive<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Also called "new trigger condition". Allows more fine grained reactivity to updates. A Pattern can react
          to changes to specific properties and ignore others. This alleviates problems of recursion and also helps with
          performance.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Sub-networks<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Not, Exists and Accumulate can each have nested conditional elements, which forms sub networks.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Backward Chaining<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Prolog style derivation trees for backward chaining are supported. The implementation is stack based, so
          does not have method recursion issues for large graphs.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Lazy Truth Maintenance<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Truth maintenance has a runtime cost, which is incurred whether TMS is used or not. Lazy TMS only turns it
          on, on first use. Further it's only turned on for that object type, so other object types do not incur the
          runtime cost.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Heap based agenda<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The agenda uses a binary heap queue to sort rule matches by salience, rather than any linear search or
          maintenance approach.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>Dynamic Rules<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Rules can be added and removed at runtime, while the engine is still populated with data.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
</section>
