<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

    <title>The Basics</title>

    <section>
      <title>Stateless Knowledge Session</title>

      <para>So where do we get started, there are so many use cases and so
      much functionality in a rule engine such as Drools that it becomes
      beguiling. Have no fear my intrepid adventurer, the complexity is
      layered and you can ease yourself into with simple use cases.</para>

      <para>Stateless session, not utilising inference, forms the simplest
      use case. A stateless session can be called like a function passing it
      some data and then receiving some results back. Some common use cases
      for stateless sessions are, but not limited to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Validation</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Is this person eligible for a mortgage?</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Calculation</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Compute a mortgage premium.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Routing and Filtering</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Filter incoming messages, such as emails, into
              folders.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Send incoming messages to a destination.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>So let's start with a very simple example using a driving license
      application.</para>

      <programlisting>public class Applicant {
    private String name;
    private int age;
    private boolean valid;
    // getter and setter methods here
}
</programlisting>

      <para>Now that we have our data model we can write our first rule. We
      assume that the application uses rules to refute invalid applications.
      As this is a simple validation use case we will add a
      single rule to disqualify any applicant younger than 18.</para>

      <programlisting>package com.company.license

rule "Is of valid age"
when
    $a : Applicant( age &lt; 18 )
then
    $a.setValid( false );
end</programlisting>

      <para>To make the engine aware of data, so it can be processed against
      the rules, we have to <emphasis>insert</emphasis> the data, much like 
      with a database. When
      the Applicant instance is inserted into the engine it is evaluated
      against the constraints of the rules, in this case just two constraints
      for one rule. We say <emphasis>two</emphasis> because the type Applicant
      is the first object
      type constraint, and <code>age &lt; 18</code> is the second field constraint.
      An object type constraint plus its zero or more field constraints is
      referred to as a pattern. When an inserted instance satisfies both the
      object type constraint and all the field constraints, it is said to be
      matched. The <code>$a</code> is a binding variable which permits us to reference
      the matched object in the consequence. There its properties can be
      updated. The dollar character ('$') is optional, but it helps to
      differentiate variable names from field names. The process of
      matching patterns against the inserted data is, not surprisingly,
      often referred to as <emphasis>pattern matching</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Let's assume that the rules are in the same folder as the classes,
      so we can use the classpath resource loader to build our first
      <code>KnowledgeBase</code>. A Knowledge Base is what we call our collection of
      compiled rules, which are compiled using the <code>KnowledgeBuilder</code>.</para>

      <programlisting>KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();
kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "licenseApplication.drl", getClass() ),
              ResourceType.DRL );
if ( kbuilder.hasErrors() ) {
    System.err.println( builder.getErrors().toString() );
}
kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages() );</programlisting>

      <para>The above code snippet looks on the classpath for the 
      <filename>licenseApplication.drl</filename>
      file, using the method <code>newClassPathResource()</code>. The resource type
      is DRL, short for "Drools Rule Language". Once the DRL file has been added
      we can check the Knowledge Builder object for any errors. If there are no
      errors, we can add the resulting packages to our Knowledge Base.
      Now we are ready to build our session and execute against some
      data:</para>

      <programlisting>StatelessKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatelessKnowledgeSession();
Applicant applicant = new Applicant( "Mr John Smith", 16 );
assertTrue( applicant.isValid() );
ksession.execute( applicant );
assertFalse( applicant.isValid() );
</programlisting>

      <para>The preceding code executes the data against the rules. Since the applicant is
      under the age of 18, the application is marked as invalid.</para>

      <para>So far we've only used a single instance, but what if we want to use
      more than one? We can execute against any object implementing Iterable, such as
      a collection. Let's add another class called <code>Application</code>, which has the
      date of the application, and we'll also move the boolean valid field to the
      <code>Application</code> class.</para>

      <programlisting>public class Applicant {
    private String name;
    private int age;
    // getter and setter methods here
}

public class Application {
    private Date dateApplied;
    private boolean valid;
    // getter and setter methods here
}</programlisting>

      <para>We can also add another rule to validate that the application
      was made within a period of time.</para>

      <programlisting>package com.company.license

rule "Is of valid age"
when
    Applicant( age &lt; 18 )
    $a : Application()     
then
    $a.setValid( false );
end

rule "Application was made this year"
when
    $a : Application( dateApplied &gt; "01-jan-2009" )     
then
    $a.setValid( false );
end
</programlisting>

      <para>Unfortunately a Java array does not implement the
      <code>Iterable</code>
      interface, so we have to use the JDK converter method
      <code>Arrays.asList(...)</code>. The code
      shown below executes against an iterable list, where all collection
      elements are inserted before any matched rules are fired.</para>

      <programlisting>StatelessKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatelessKnowledgeSession();
Applicant applicant = new Applicant( "Mr John Smith", 16 );
Application application = new Application();
assertTrue( application() );
ksession.execute( Arrays.asList( new Object[] { application, applicant } ) );
assertFalse( application() );
</programlisting>

      <para>The two execute methods <code>execute(Object object)</code> and
      <code>execute(Iterable objects)</code> are actually convenience methods for the
      interface <code>BatchExecutor</code>'s method <code>execute(Command command)</code>.</para>

      <para>A <code>CommandFactory</code> is used to create commands, so that the following is
      equivalent to <code>execute(Iterable it)</code>:</para>

      <programlisting>ksession.execute( CommandFactory.newInsertIterable( new Object[] { application, applicant } ) );
</programlisting>

      <para>Batch Executor and Command Factory are particularly useful when working
      with multiple Commands and with output identifiers for obtaining results.</para>

      <programlisting>List&lt;Command&gt; cmds = new ArrayList&lt;Command&gt;();
cmds.add( CommandFactory.newInsert( new Person( "Mr John Smith" ), "mrSmith" );
cmds.add( CommandFactory.newInsert( new Person( "Mr John Doe" ), "mrDoe" );
BatchExecutionResults results = ksession.execute( CommandFactory.newBatchExecution( cmds ) );
assertEquals( new Person( "Mr John Smith" ), results.getValue( "mrSmith" ) );
</programlisting>

      <para><code>CommandFactory</code> supports many other Commands that can be used in
      the <code>BatchExecutor</code> like <code>StartProcess</code>, <code>Query</code>, and
      <code>SetGlobal</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stateful Knowledge Session</title>

      <para>Stateful Sessions are longer lived and allow iterative changes
      over time. Some common use cases for Stateful Sessions are, but not
      limited to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Monitoring</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Stock market monitoring and analysis for semi-automatic
              buying.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Diagnostics</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Fault finding, medical diagnostics</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Logistics</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Parcel tracking and delivery provisioning</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compliance</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Validation of legality for market trades.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In contrast to a Stateless Session, the <code>dispose()</code>
      method must be called
      afterwards to ensure there are no memory leaks, as the Knowledge Base
      contains references to Stateful Knowledge Sessions when they are created.
      <code>StatefulKnowledgeSession</code> also supports the <code>BatchExecutor</code>
      interface, like <code>StatelessKnowledgeSession</code>, the only difference
      being that the <code>FireAllRules</code> command is not automatically called at the
      end for a Stateful Session.</para>

      <para>We illustrate the monitoring use case with an example for raising a
      fire alarm. Using just four classes, we represent rooms in a house, each of which
      has one sprinkler. If a fire starts in a room, we
      represent that with a single <code>Fire</code> instance.</para>

      <programlisting>public class Room {
    private String name
    // getter and setter methods here
}
public classs Sprinkler {
    private Room room;
    private boolean on;
    // getter and setter methods here
}
public class Fire {
    private Room room;
    // getter and setter methods here
}
public class Alarm {
}
</programlisting>

      <para>In the previous section on Stateless Sessions the concepts of
      inserting and matching against data was introduced. That example assumed
      that only a single instance of each object type was ever inserted and thus
      only used literal constraints. However, a house has many rooms, so rules
      must express relationships between objects, such as a sprinkler being in
      a certain room. This is best done by using a binding variable as a constraint
      in a pattern. This "join" process results in what is called cross products, which are
      covered in the next section.</para>

      <para>When a fire occurs an instance of the <code>Fire</code> class is created, for
      that room, and inserted into the session. The rule uses a binding on the 
      <code>room</code>
      field of the <code>Fire</code> object to constrain matching to the sprinkler for that room,
      which is currently  off. When this rule fires and the consequence is executed
      the sprinkler is turned on.</para>

      <programlisting>rule "When there is a fire turn on the sprinkler"
when
    Fire($room : room)
    $sprinkler : Sprinkler( room == $room, on == false )
then
    modify( $sprinkler ) { setOn( true ) };
    System.out.println( "Turn on the sprinkler for room " + $room.getName() );
end</programlisting>

      <para>Whereas the Stateless Session uses standard Java syntax to modify
      a field, in the above rule we use the <literal>modify</literal> statement, which acts as a
      sort of "with" statement. It may contain a series of comma separated Java
      expressions, i.e., calls to setters of the object selected by the <literal>modify</literal>
      statement's control
      expression. This modifies the data, and makes the engine aware of those changes
      so it can reason over them once more. This process is called inference, and
      it's essential for the working of a Stateful Session. Stateless Sessions 
      typically do not use inference, so the engine does not need to be aware of 
      changes to data. Inference can also be turned off explicitly by using the
      <emphasis>sequential mode</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>So far we have rules that tell us when matching data exists, but
      what about when it does <emphasis>not</emphasis> exist? How do we determine
      that a fire has been extinguished, i.e., that there isn't a <code>Fire</code>
      object any more? Previously the constraints have been sentences according
      to Propositional Logic,
      where the engine is constraining against individual intances. Drools also has
      support for First Order Logic that allows you to look at sets of data.
      A pattern under the keyword <literal>not</literal> matches when something does not exist.
      The rule given below turns the sprinkler off as soon as the fire in that
      room has disappeared.</para>

      <programlisting>rule "When the fire is gone turn off the sprinkler"
when
    $room : Room( )
    $sprinkler : Sprinkler( room == $room, on == true )
    not Fire( room == $room )
then
    modify( $sprinkler ) { setOn( false ) };
    System.out.println( "Turn off the sprinkler for room " + $room.getName() );
end</programlisting>

      <para>While there is one sprinkler per room, there is just a single alarm
      for the building. An <code>Alarm</code> object is created when a fire occurs,
      but only one <code>Alarm</code> is needed for the entire building, no matter
      how many fires occur. Previously <literal>not</literal> was introduced to match the absence of
      a fact; now we use its complement <literal>exists</literal> which matches for one or more
      instances of some category.</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Raise the alarm when we have one or more fires"
when
    exists Fire()
then
    insert( new Alarm() );
    System.out.println( "Raise the alarm" );
end</programlisting>

      <para>Likewise, when there are no fires we want to remove the alarm, so
      the <literal>not</literal> keyword can be used again.</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Cancel the alarm when all the fires have gone"
when
    not Fire()
    $alarm : Alarm()
then
    retract( $alarm );
    System.out.println( "Cancel the alarm" );
end

</programlisting>

      <para>Finally there is a general health status message that is printed
      when the application first starts and after the alarm is removed and all
      sprinklers have been turned off.</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Status output when things are ok"
when
    not Alarm()
    not Sprinkler( on === true ) 
then
    System.out.println( "Everything is ok" );
end</programlisting>

      <para>The above rules should be placed in a single DRL file and saved to
      some directory on the classpath and using the file name
      <filename>fireAlarm.drl</filename>,
      as in the Stateless Session example. We can then build a Knowledge Base,
      as before, just using the new name <filename>fireAlarm.drl</filename>.
      The difference is that
      this time we create a Stateful Session from the Knowledge Base, whereas
      before we created a Stateless Session.</para>

      <programlisting>KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();
kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "fireAlarm.drl", getClass() ),
              ResourceType.DRL );
if ( kbuilder.hasErrors() ) {
    System.err.println( builder.getErrors().toString() );
}
kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages() );
StatefulKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatefulKnowledgeSession();</programlisting>

      <para>With the session created it is now possible to iteratvely work
      with it over time. Four <code>Room</code> objects are created and 
      inserted, as well as one <code>Sprinkler</code> object for
      each room. At this point the engine has done all of its
      matching, but no rules have fired yet. Calling <code>ksession.fireAllRules()</code>
      allows the matched rules to fire, but without a fire that will
      just produce the health message.</para>

      <programlisting>String[] names = new String[]{"kitchen", "bedroom", "office", "livingroom"};
Map&lt;String,Room&gt; name2room = new HashMap&lt;String,Room&gt;();
for( String name: names ){
    Room room = new Room( name );
    name2room.put( name, room );
    ksession.insert( room );
    Sprinkler sprinkler = new Sprinkler( room );
    ksession.insert( sprinkler );
}

ksession.fireAllRules()
</programlisting>

      <programlisting>&gt; Everything is ok</programlisting>

      <para>We now create two fires and insert them; this time a reference is
      kept for the returned <code>FactHandle</code>. A Fact Handle is an 
      internal engine reference to the inserted instance and allows instances to be
      retracted or modified at a later point in time. With the fires now in
      the engine, once <code>fireAllRules()</code> is called, the alarm is raised and the
      respective sprinklers are turned on.</para>

      <programlisting>Fire kitchenFire = new Fire( name2room.get( "kitchen" ) );
Fire officeFire = new Fire( name2room.get( "office" ) );

FactHandle kitchenFireHandle = ksession.insert( kitchenFire );
FactHandle officeFireHandle = ksession.insert( officeFire );

ksession.fireAllRules();</programlisting>

      <programlisting>&gt; Raise the alarm
&gt; Turn on the sprinkler for room kitchen
&gt; Turn on the sprinkler for room office</programlisting>

      <para>After a while the fires will be put out and the <code>Fire</code>
      instances are retracted. This results in the sprinklers being turned off, the alarm
      being cancelled, and eventually the health message is printed again.</para>

      <programlisting>ksession.retract( kitchenFireHandle );
ksession.retract( officeFireHandle );

ksession.fireAllRules();</programlisting>

      <programlisting>&gt; Turn on the sprinkler for room office
&gt; Turn on the sprinkler for room kitchen
&gt; Cancel the alarm
&gt; Everything is ok</programlisting>

      <para>Everyone still with me? That wasn't so hard and already I'm
      hoping you can start to see the value and power of a declarative rule
      system.</para>
    </section>

</section>
