<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base=".." xml:id="sect-designer-shapes"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <title>Getting started with Modelling</title>
  <para>The Object Repository panel provide means for users to select and drag/drop BPMN2 shapes onto the modelling canvas. Shapes are divided into sections as shown below:</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Object Repository</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/object-repository.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>Once a shape is dropped onto the canvas users have a much faster way of continuing modelling without having to go back to the Object Repository panel. This is realized through the shape morphing menu which is presented
  when a shape on the drawing canvas is clicked on. This menu allows users to either select a connecting shape (next shape) or morph the selected node into another node type. In addition this menu
  includes means to store the shape name as a dictionary item (explained later), view the specific BPMN2 code of the selected shape, asd well as create/edit the task form (in the case of user tasks only).</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Morphing Menu for shapes</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/morph-menu.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  
  <para>
    When connecting shapes Designer applies connection rules that follow the BPMN2 specification. The connection shapes presented in the morphing menu only show shapes that are allowed to be connections. Similarly same rules are applied when dropping a shape from the Object Library from the canvas and 
    trying to connect an existing shape to it. Additional connection rules for boundary events are also available (explained later) and applied when for example moving an intermediate event node onto the edge of a task node.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Users can give names to every shape on the drawing canvas. This is done by double-clicking onto the shape as shown below.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Naming a shape</title>
    
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/naming-shapes.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  
  <para>
    The name of a shape can be pulled from the Process Dictionary. If terms are set up in the dictionary, auto-complete can be used for the node names:
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Name auto-completion from dictionary</title>
    
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/name-autocomplete.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
    Designer also shows three buttons ontop of a clicked shape as shown below.
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>Extra in-line options</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/node-extra-options.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>
    These include:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>(1) Add To Dictionary - this option allows users to add the name of the task to the Process Dictionary (explained in more details later)</para></listitem> 
      <listitem><para>(2) Edit Task Form - allows users to create/edit the Task Form. This option is only available for User Tasks</para></listitem> 
      <listitem><para>(3) View shape sources - shows the BPMN2 for this particular shape only.</para></listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The section should get you started with creating simple business process models by dragging/dropping BPMN2 shapes onto the drawing canvas. Next sections will dive deeper into many other 
    aspects of Designer. 
  </para>
  
</section>
