<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base=".." xml:id="sect-designer-toolbar"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <title>Designer Toolbar</title>
  <para>The Designer toolbar contains many different functions which can be used during process modelling. </para>

  <figure>
    <title>Toolbar Buttons</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/navbar1.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
    We will now go through each of the buttons in the Designer Toolbar and give a brief overview of what it does.
  </para>
  
  <para>(1) Save - allows users to save, copy, rename and delete the business process model. In
    addition users can turn on auto-save which will uatomatically save the business process within a
    defined time inter. <figure>
      <title>Save Button</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/navbar-save.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>(2) Cut  - enabled when a portion of the model is selected. </para>
  <para>(3) Copy  - enabled when a portion of the model is selected.</para>
  <para>(4) Paste  - paste the copied portion of the model onto the drawing board. </para>
  <para>(5) Delete - enabled when there is a portion of the model is selected and removes it.</para>
  <para>(6, 7) Undo/Redo - undo the last performed operation on the drawing canvas. </para>
  <para>(8) Local History - local history allows continuous storage of your business process onto
    your browsers internal storage. Stored version of the business process can persist internet
    autages or a browser crashes so your work will not be lost. This feature is disabled by default
    and must be enabled by users. Once local history has been enabled users are able to view all
    previously stored snapshots of their business model, clear local history, configure the snapshot
    internal, or disable local history. Note that local history will only take a snapshot of your
    business process on the set storing internval if there were some changes done in the model. If
    at the end of the snapshot internval Designer detects that there were no changes since the last
    local history save, no new snapshot will be created.
  <figure>
      <title>Local History</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/localhistory1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    The Local History results screen allows users to select a stored shanpshot of the model and
      view its process image, and restory it back onto their drawing board.
    <figure>
      <title>Local History Sample Results</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/localhistory-results.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>(9) Object positioning - allows users to position one or more nodes in the business. Note
    that at last one shape must be selected first, otherwise these options are disable. Contains
    options "Bring to Front", "Bring to back", "Bring forward", and "Bring Backward"</para>
  <para>(10) Alignment: enabled when a portion of the model is selected. Includes options "Align Bottom", "Align Middle", "Align Top", "Align Left", "Align Center", "Align Right", and "Align Same Size".</para>
  <para>(11, 12) Group and Ungroup - allows grouping and ungrouping of selected shapes on the
    drawing board.</para>
  <para>(13, 14) Locking and Unlocking  - allows parts of the business model to be locked and
    unlocked. Locked parts of the model cannot be edited (visual display and properties are both
    locked). Locked nodes are displayed in a light blue color. This feature fosters collaboration of
    process modelling by allowing users to set parts of their model as "completed" and preventing
    any further changes to that portion. Other parts of the model can contunue to be edited. 
    <figure>
      <title>Locked Nodes</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/locked-nodes.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>(15, 16) Add/Remove Docker - this allows users to add or remove Dockers, or edge points, to
    sequence flows in the model. Enables when a sequence flow (connector) is selected. It allows
    users to create very customized connection poits from one shape to another. Users can add and
    remove as many dockes as they would like on a single sequence flow.
    <figure>
      <title>Adding dockers to a sequence flow</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/adding-dockers.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>(17) Color Themes - Colors are a big part or process modelling as they help with expressing intent as well as help allowing visually impaired users to better view the model. 
  Designer provides two default color themes out of the box named "jBPM" and "High Contrast". The jBPM theme is the default theme used for all new business processes created. Users can switch color themes and the changes will 
  be applied to all nodes that are currently on the model, as well as any new shapes added. Users have the ability to add new custom color themes by adding theor own definitions in the 
  Designer themes.json file. Color theme selection is persisted over browser close or possible crash/internet loss.
    <figure>
      <title>Color Themes selection</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/color-themes.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title>Switching to High Contrast Color Theme</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/color-themes2.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <para>
    (18) Process and Task forms - here users have the ability to generate/edit process and task forms. When no user task is selected the default enabled options are "Edit Process Form" and "Generate all Forms". 
    Generate all forms will apply the current model information such as process variables, data objects, and the user tasks data input/output parameters and associations to generate default executable input forms. 
    Upon editing a process and task form, users have the choice between two form editors, the jBPM Form Modeler, and the Designer in-line meta editor. The Designer meta editor is targeted more 
    to techical users as it is text based with the ability for live preview. When the user selects an user task in the model, the "Edit Task Form" and "Generate Task Form" options are enabled which allow users 
    to edit the particular task form, or choose to apply the same generation logic to create a task form for the selected task only. Users have the ability to extend the default form generation templates in designer
    to create fully customized templates. Node that in the case of the Designer meta editor for forms, generating forms will overwrite existing forms for the process and user tasks. In the case of Form Modeler 
    form generation, a merging algorithm is applied when generating.
    
    <figure>
      <title>Form generation selection</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/forms1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    When selecting a task, users have the ability to edit the selected tasks form via the form button shown above the user task node.
    <figure>
      <title>In-line task editing</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/forms2.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    When editing forms, users are asked to choose between the Form Modeler and the Designer in-line meta editor. If the user selects Form Modeler the form is shown in a new asset tab separately from Designer. Designer meta editor is in-line and part of the Designer application.
    <figure>
      <title>Form Editor Selection</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/forms3.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    The Designer in-line meta form editor is a powerful text-based editor with a live preview feature as well as auto-completion on process variables and user task data inputs/outputs.
    <figure>
      <title>Designer in-line form meta editor with live-preview</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/forms4.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
  </para>
  <para>(19) Process Information Sharing - this section includes many fucntions that help with sharing information of your model. These include:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Share process image - generates a stand-alone html image tag which contains a 64-bit encoded image source of the current model on the canvas. This link can be shared to team members or other parties amd embedded in any html content or email that allows html content embedding.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Share process PDF - generates a stand-alone html object tag which contains a 64-bit encoded pdf source of the current model on the canvas. This can similarly be shared and embedded in any html content.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Download process PNG - generates a PNG image of the current process on the drawing board which users can download and share.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Download process PDF - generates a PDF of the current process on the drawing board which can be downloaded and shared.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>View Process Sources - displays the current process sources in various formats, namely BPMN2, JSON, SVG, and ERDF. Also has the option to download the BPMN2 sources.</para></listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>
   
    
    <figure>
      <title>Process Sources View</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/processsources.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  
  <para>(20) Extra tooling - this section allows users to import their existing BPMN2 processes into designer as well as be able to migrate their old jPDL based processes to BPMN2. For BPMN2 or JSON imports users can choose
    to add the import ontop of the existing model on the drawing board or choose to replace the current one with the import.
    <figure>
      <title>Extra tooling section</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/extra1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
      <title>Import existing BPMN2 panel</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/extra2.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
      <title>Process Migration panel</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/extra3.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  
  </para>
  
  <para>(21) Visual Validation - Designer includes over 100 validation checks and this list is growing. It allows users to view validation issues in real-time as they are modelling their business process.
    Users can enable visual validation, disable it, as well as view all validation issues at once. If Visual Validation is turned on, Designer with set the shape border of shapes that do not pass validation
    to red color. Users can then click on that particular shape to view the validation issues for that particular shape only. Alternatively "View All Issues" present a cobined list of all validation errors currently found.
    Note that you do not have to periodically save your business process in order for validation to upate. It will so on its own short intervals during modelling. 
    Users can extend the list of validation issues to include their own types of validation on certain elements of their business model.
    
    <figure>
      <title>Visual Validation Toolbar </title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/validation1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
      <title>Shapes with validation errors displayed with red border</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/validation2.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
      <title>Single shape validation issues display</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/validation3.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
      <title>View all issues validation display</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/validation4.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
  </para>
  <para>(22) Process Simulation - Business Process Simulation deals with statistical analysis of
    process models over time. It's main goals include
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Pre-execution and post-execution optimization</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Reducing the rist of change in business processes</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Predict business process performance</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Foster continuous improvements of performance, quality and resource utilization of business processes</para></listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>
    Designer includes a powerful simulation engine which is based on jBPM and Drools and a graphical user interface to view and interpret simulation results. In addition users are able to view all process paths included in their current model on the drawing board.
    Designer Process Simulation is based on the BPSim 1.0 specification. Details of Process Simulation capabilities in Designer are can be found in its Simulation documentation chapter. Here we just give a brief overview of all features it contains.
    
    <figure>
      <title>Simulation tooling section</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim1.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    When selecting Process Paths, the simulation engine find all possible paths in the business model. Users can choose cetain found paths and choose to display them. The chosen path is marked with given colors as shown below. 
    <figure>
      <title>View all issues validation display</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim2.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    When selcting "Run Simulation" users have to enter in simulation runtime properties. These include the number of instances of this business process to simulate and the interval time and units. This interval is the time in-between consecutive simulation.
    <figure>
      <title>Simulation runtime properties</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim3.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    Each shape on the drawing board includes Simulation properties (properties pannel) where users can set numerous simulation properties for that particular shape. More info on each of these properties can be found in the Simulation chapter of the documentation.
    Designer pre-sets some defaults for new processes, which allows business processes to be simulated by default without any modifications of these properties. Note however that the results of the default settings
    may not be optimal or targeted for the users particular needs. 
    <figure>
      <title>Simulation properties for shapes</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim4.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    
    Once the simulation runtime has completed, users are shown the simulation results in the "Simulation Results" tab of Designer. The results default to the process results. Users can switch to results for each particular shape in their business process to see more specific detauls. In addition 
    the results contain process paths simualtion results for each path in the business process.
    <figure>
      <title>Sample simulation results</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim5.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    Designer simulation presents the users with many different chart types. These include:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Process results: Execution times, Activity instances, Total cost</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Human Task results: Execution times, Resource Utilization, Resource Cost</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>All other nodes: Execution times</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Process Paths: Path Execution</para></listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>
    The below image shows a number of possible chart types users can view after process simulation has completed.
    <figure>
      <title>Types of simulation results charts</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim6.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    In addition to the chart results, Designer simulation also offers a full timeline display that includes all details of what happened during simulation. This timeline allows users to navigate through each
    event that happened during process simulation and select a particular node to display results at that particular point in time.
    <figure>
      <title>Simulation timeline</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim7.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    The simulation timeline can be switched to the Model view. This view displays the process model with the currently selected node in the timeline highlighted. The highlighted node displays the sim results at that particular point in time of the simulation.
    <figure>
      <title>Simulation timeline model view</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim8.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    Path execution results shows a chart displaying the chosen path as well as path instance execution details.
    <figure>
      <title>Path execution detauls</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/sim9.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  
  </para>
  
  <para>(23) Service Repository - this feature allows users to connect to an existing service tasks
    repository to install service tasks into their list of available shapes. Mode default of this
    can be found in the Service Repository chapter of the documentation. Users have to enter the URL
    to the existing service repository and then can install the available service nodes by
    double-clicking on a particular results row. <figure>
      <title>Service Repository installation view</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/servicerepo.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  
  <para>(24) Full screen Modev - allows users to place the drawing board of Designer into
    full-screen mode. This can help with better visualizing larger business processes without having
    to scroll. Note that this feature is possible only if your browser has full screen mode
    capabilities. If it does not designer will show a message stating this to the user. <figure>
      <title>Full Screen Mode</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/fullscreen.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>
  
  <para>(25) Process Dictionary - Designer Dictionary Editor allows users to create their own dictionary entries or harvest from process documentation or business requirement documents. Process Dictionary entries can be used as auto-completion for shape names. This will be expaded in the 
    future versions to allow mapping of node patters to specific dictionary entries as well.
    Users can add entries to the dictionary in the Dictioanry Editor or from the selected shapes directly.

    <figure>
      <title>Process Dictionary entry screen</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/dictionary1.png" width="450"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>Addint to process dictionary from selected shape</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Designer/dictionary2.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>  
  
  <para>(26, 27, 28, 29) Zooming - zomming allows users to zoom in/out of the model, zoom in/out back to the original setting as well as zoom the process model on the drawing board to fit the currently dimentions of the drawing board.</para> 
  
</section>
