<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="ProcessManagement"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  

         <title>Process Management</title>
         
         <para>This chapter describes the screens related with the creation and management of 
                process definitions and process instances. 
         </para>
         <para>
                Once you have modelled, configured all the technical details and build and deployed your projects containing your business processes you 
             should be able to see all the available process definitions in the Process Definition List. For all the process definitions listed in the 
             Process Definitions List you will be able to inspect the Process Definition details and start as many Process Instances as needed.
                The following sections describes the features provided by all the screens in charge of the manupulation of process definitions and 
             process instances.
                You can find these screens under the <emphasis role="bold">Process Management</emphasis> Menu, in the jBPM Console NG or in Kie Workbench.
         </para>
         
         <para>
                You can find the source code related with the process definition and instances manupilation inside this module:
                <link xlink:href="http://github.com/droolsjbpm/jbpm-console-ng/tree/master/jbpm-console-ng-process-runtime">
                    http://github.com/droolsjbpm/jbpm-console-ng/tree/master/jbpm-console-ng-process-runtime
                </link>
                Feel free to report issues, send Pull Requests and get in contact with the team via comments in github.
         </para>
         
         
         <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                       <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                              fileref="images/Console/process-management.png"/>
                </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
         
         <section>
                <title>Process Definitions</title>
                
                <para>The process definition section is composed by two main screens: the Process Definition Lists and the
                       Process Definition Details.</para>
                
                <section>
                       <title>The Process Definition List</title>
                       <para> The process definition list shows all the available process definitions that were deployed into the platform. 
                              Look at the Deployments section for more information about how to check all the deploymed units available in the platform runtime. </para>
                       
                       <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                   <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                          fileref="images/Console/process-definitions-list.png"
                                          width="700"/>
                            </imageobject>
                     </mediaobject>
                       
                       <para>You can click in the list rows to access to the details of the process definition. </para>
                       
                </section>
                
                <section>
                       <title>The Process Definition Details</title>
                       <para> The process definition details shows all the available information about the process definition. You can consider this
                              screen as a brief about the process model. You can quickly see if there is a Sub Process associated with it, or how many users and groups
                              are participating in the selected definition. 
                       </para>
                       
                       <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                   <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                          fileref="images/Console/process-definitions-details.png"
                                          width="700"/>
                            </imageobject>
                     </mediaobject>
                       <para>Notice that you can View the Process Model (Read Only mode) using the Options Menu in the top bar. You can also
                              look at all the process instances for the selected process definition by going to Options -> View Process Instances.
                       </para>
                       
                       
                       <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                   <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                          fileref="images/Console/process-model.png"
                                          width="700"/>
                            </imageobject>
                     </mediaobject>
                </section>
                
                <section>
                     <title>Creating Process Instances</title>
                       <para> You can create new Process Instances from the Process Definition List (Action Column) or from the Process Definition Detail view. </para>
                       
                       <mediaobject>
                              <imageobject>
                                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                            fileref="images/Console/process-definitions-new-instance.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                              </imageobject>
                       </mediaobject>
                       <para>When you create a Process Instance usually a Form will be presented to introduce the information required
                              by the process to be started. Once you complete the required information and click on the Submit button, the instance will be created and
                              the details of the Process Instance will be displayed on top of the Process Definition Details. 
                       
                       </para>
                </section>
         </section>
         <section>
             <title>Process Instances</title>
                
             <para>The process instances section is composed by two main screens: the Process Instance Lists and the
                 Process Instance Details. In this case the Process Instance Details provides several tabs with the 
                 runtime information related with the process. </para>
             <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                                fileref="images/Console/process-instances-list.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                 </imageobject>
             </mediaobject>
             <para>
                 Each row inside the process instance list represent a running process instance from a particular Process Definition. 
                 Each execution is differentiated from all the others by the internal state of the information that the process is manipulating. 
                 In order to inspect this information you can click in each row to see the process instance details.
             </para>   
             <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                                fileref="images/Console/process-instances-details.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                 </imageobject>
             </mediaobject>   
             <para>
                 As you can see the Process Instance Detail first tab gives you a quick overview about what is going on inside the process. This is by showing 
                 the current state of the instance and also the current activity that is being executed.
                 The process variables tab display all the process variables  that are being manipulated by the instance with the exception of the variables that contains
                 documents. 
             </para> 
             <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                                fileref="images/Console/process-instances-variables.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                 </imageobject>
             </mediaobject>
             <para>
                 If the process contains a variable of the type: org.jbpm.Document it will be listed in the Documents tab, for easy access, download and manipulation
                 of the attached documents. Notice that at this point you cannot attach new documents to currently running instances, but this feature will be added in future versions.
             </para> 
             <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                                fileref="images/Console/process-instances-documents.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                 </imageobject>
             </mediaobject>  
             <para>
                 Finally, the Logs tab shows two types of logs for different end users. There are two types of Logs available inside the tab: Business and Technical.
                 
             </para>
               
             <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                                fileref="images/Console/process-instances-logs.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                 </imageobject>
             </mediaobject>        
             <para>
                 To complement the process logs you can open the Process Model that shows the completed activies in grey and the current activities
                 highlighted in red.
             </para> 
             
            <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                                                fileref="images/Console/process-instances-running-model.png"  width="400" />
                                     
                 </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>         
         </section>
</section>
