<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<section>
  <title>Administration guide</title>

  <para>This chapter covers installation and administration issues of the
  BRMS.</para>

  <para>The BRMS is a web application that can run in multiple environments,
  and be configured to suit most situations. There is also some initial setup
  of data, and export/import functions covered.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>Installation for most people is very simple. The BRMS application is
    deployed as a .war file, which can be deployed in application servers or
    servlet containers with little or no configuration if you are happy with
    the defaults.</para>

    <para>When you have downloaded the BRMS distribution (which you can get
    from http://labs.jboss.com/jbossrules/downloads), you will find the
    drools-jbrms.war file in the zip file. Copy the WAR file into the
    deployment directory of you app server, and then start your app server. If
    you need to customise some settings, you can first "explode" (unzip) the
    war file, and change any configuration settings, and then either zip it
    up, or deploy it "exploded".</para>

    <para>Once the drools-jbrms.war has been placed in the deployment
    directory, and the application server started, you should navigate to
    http://localhost/drools-jbrms and check that the BRMS appears. (Obviously
    substitute the URL for what your application server is configured
    to).</para>

    <para>Once that shows up, you are deployed and ready to go !</para>

    <section>
      <title>Supported and recommended platforms</title>

      <para>The BRMS is capable of running in any application server that
      sypports Java SE5 (JEE 5 is not required) - this includes servlet
      containers like tomcat.</para>

      <para>It is actively tested on JBoss platforms, and these are
      recommended if you are able to use them, or don't have any existing
      infrastructure. However, it is possible to use any container/app server,
      in some cases with minor configuration tweaks (consult the wiki for
      specific tips).</para>

      <para>The following are a list of recommended platforms (all freely
      available), in all cases, you can substitute newer versions of the same
      and it should work (as time may have passed since this was
      written):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>JBoss Application Server 4.0.5</para>

          <para>This is recommended as a general application server solution,
          if you need to run other applications alongside the BRMS.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JBoss Web 1.0.1</para>

          <para>This is an ideal solution if you need a "lighter" server to
          run just the BRMS (perhaps stand alone).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You can of course download these from www.jboss.com for every
      operating system.</para>

      <para>Deployment into JBoss platforms: If you are installing a new JBoss
      platform, the WAR can be copied to [app server
      directory]/server/default/deploy. You then start up the server by
      running run.sh or run.bat in the [app server directory/bin]
      directory.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Database configuration</title>

    <para>The BRMS uses the JCR standard for storing assets (such as rules).
    The default implementation is Apache Jackrabbit
    (http://jackrabbit.apache.org/). This includes an out of the box storage
    engine/database, which you can use as is, or configure to use an existing
    RDBMS if needed.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Changing the location of the data store</title>

      <para>When you run the BRMS for the first time (starting up the app
      server), it will create a database in the [app server directory]/bin/
      directory (assuming you used on of the JBoss platforms). There is a
      repository.xml file, and a repository directory that are automatically
      created.</para>

      <para>The location of the data store should be a secure location, that
      is backed up. The default location may not be suitable for this, so the
      easiest way is to set a more suitable location. If you want to change
      this, please make sure you have stopped the BRMS (ie stopped the app
      server or undeployed the application).</para>

      <para>To change the location, unzip the WAR file, and locate the
      components.xml file in the WEB-INF directory. This is a JBoss Seam
      configuration file (Seam is the framework used) which allows various
      parts of the system to be customised. When you have located the
      components.xml file, you should see something like the following:
      <programlisting>&lt;component name="repositoryConfiguration"&gt;
 &lt;!--
  *** This is for configuring the "home" directory for the repo storage. the directory must exist. ***
     &lt;property name="homeDirectory"&gt;/home/michael/RulesRepository_001&lt;/property&gt;
   --&gt;  

   ...
&lt;/component&gt;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>Find the component with a name of "repositoryConfiguration" and
      the property with the name of "homeDirectory".</para>

      <para>If you un comment this (as in the example above it is commented
      out), you can set whatever path you need for the repository data to be
      stored in. You can also use this to move the repository around. In that
      case, when you have set the location in the components.xml you can
      simply move the repository.xml AND the repository directory to the new
      location that you set in the components.xml.</para>

      <para>If there is no repository at the location specified (or in the
      default location) then the BRMS will create a new empty one.</para>

      <para>There are many more options which can be configured in the
      repository.xml, but for the most part, it is not recommended to change
      the defaults.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the BRMS to use an external RDBMS</title>

      <para>In some cases it may be a requirement that you use an external
      RDBMS, such as Oracle, MySQL, or Microsoft SQL Server as the data store
      - this is permitted. In this case, the easiest thing to do is to start
      up the RDBMS with defaults (or with a suitable home directory as
      specified above) to let it generate the default repository.xml
      scaffolding.</para>

      <para>Locate the repository.xml file that was generated, and open it -
      it will be annotated with comments describing many of the different
      options. From here on, you will need to know a little about Jackrabbit
      Persistence managers:
      http://jackrabbit.apache.org/doc/config.html</para>

      <para>There are a few persistence managers, some are database specific
      (eg Oracle). There is a SimpleDBPersistenceManager which works with any
      database that supports JDBC - you also specify the database type, so it
      uses the specific DDL to create the table structure (all major databases
      are supported).</para>

      <para>The BRMS will create the tables the first time it is started up if
      it is running against a fresh (empty) RDBMS - so its important to note
      that the user credentials supplied have permissions to create tables (at
      least initially, on first run, after that they could be locked
      down).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Searching and indexing, Version storage</title>

      <para>Jackrabbit has a seperate storage area for version storage (as
      over time, the number of old versions will increase, yet it should not
      slow down the performance of the main data store). The version storage
      also has its own persistence manage configuration in the repository.xml,
      but for most purposes you can use the same database as the main storage
      (just with a different schema object prefix - ie in your database, all
      the version data will be prefixed with "version_" but otherwise in the
      same tablespace). See the repository.xml for more details of
      this.</para>

      <para>Lucene is used to provide indexing across the semi structured
      data, and across versions. This indexing is generally best stored on a
      filesystem, local to the BRMS (as per the default in the repository.xml)
      - in most cases the default is fine.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>Security is configured by using the components.xml file in the war
    file. To customise this, you will need to unzip the war file, and locate
    the components.xml file which is in the WEB-INF directory.</para>

    <para>The JAAS standard is used as the underlying authentication and
    authorization mechanism, the upshot of which means its very flexable and
    able to integrate into most existing environments.</para>

    <para>Out of the box, the BRMS shows a login screen, but no security
    credentials are enforced - the user name is used, but no password check is
    performed. To enforce authentication, you need to configure it to use an
    appropriate user directory (you may have Active Directory or similar
    already).</para>

    <para>In the components.xml file, you should located a security
    configuration section like the following:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;!-- SECURITY CONFIGURATION --&gt;
    
&lt;!-- default (will take any username, useful if you want to keep track of users but not authenticate --&gt;
&lt;security:identity authenticate-method="#{defaultAuthenticator.authenticate}"/&gt;

&lt;!-- NO authentication. This will bypass the login screen when you hit the app. Everyone is "guest" --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;security:identity authenticate-method="#{nilAuthenticator.authenticate}"/&gt; --&gt;   </programlisting>

    <para>As you can see from above, the 2 "out of the box" options are pass
    through - which means any user is allowed in, or bypassed, in which case
    there is no login screen (eg you may be securing access to the app via a
    web server anyway).</para>

    <section>
      <title>Using your containers security and LDAP</title>

      <para>Every application server supports advanced configurations which
      can work with your existing security infrastructure. The case of JBoss
      AS will be shown here as an example.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;security:identity authenticate-method="#{authenticator.authenticate}" 
                      jaas-config-name="other"/&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>This will use the "other" jaas config in JBoss AS. If you look in
      [jboss install dir]/server/default/conf you will see a login-config.xml
      file. This file contains various configs. If you use "other" like the
      one above, then it will look for users.properties and roles.properties
      in the conf directory for usernames and passwords to authenticate
      against (this is fine for a fixed small number of users).</para>

      <para>LDAP is perhaps the most popular choice for larger enterprises, so
      following is an example that works with Active Directory. You can get
      much more information on how to configure JBoss AS for all scenarios
      with LDAP from http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=LdapLoginModule
      and http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=LdapExtLoginModule.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;application-policy name="brms"&gt;
    &lt;authentication&gt;
        &lt;login-module code="org.jboss.security.auth.spi.LdapExtLoginModule" flag="required" &gt;
            &lt;!--
                Some AD configurations may require searching against
                the Global Catalog on port 3268 instead of the usual
                port 389.  This is most likely when the AD forest
                includes multiple domains.
            --&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="java.naming.provider.url"&gt;ldap://ldap.jboss.org:389&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="bindDN"&gt;JBOSS\someadmin&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="bindCredential"&gt;password&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="baseCtxDN"&gt;cn=Users,dc=jboss,dc=org&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="baseFilter"&gt;(sAMAccountName={0})&lt;/module-option&gt;

            &lt;module-option name="rolesCtxDN"&gt;cn=Users,dc=jboss,dc=org&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="roleFilter"&gt;(sAMAccountName={0})&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="roleAttributeID"&gt;memberOf&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="roleAttributeIsDN"&gt;true&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="roleNameAttributeID"&gt;cn&lt;/module-option&gt;

            &lt;module-option name="roleRecursion"&gt;-1&lt;/module-option&gt;
            &lt;module-option name="searchScope"&gt;ONELEVEL_SCOPE&lt;/module-option&gt;
        &lt;/login-module&gt;
    &lt;/authentication&gt;
&lt;/application-policy&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>To use the above, you would put jaas-config-name="brms" in the
      security:identity tag in the components.xml for the BRMS.</para>

      <para>Similar configuration examples can be found for other directory
      services.</para>

      <para>LDAP isn't the final word, you can use JDBC against a database of
      user name, or you can write your own login module to use any sort of
      wierd and wonderful authentication and authorisation systems that you
      may have to deal with (that would be an extreme case, but its possible).
      Refer to JBoss AS documentation (or documentation for your existing
      application server).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Data management</title>

    <section>
      <title>Backups</title>

      <para>How backups are performed is dependent on what persistence manager
      scheme you are using. Using the default one - then its a matter of
      backing up the repository directory (wherever you have it configured to
      be). Restoring it is simply a matter of copying across the repository
      directory.</para>

      <para>Ideally you will either stop the BRMS application while a file
      backup is being done, or ensure that no one is using it.</para>

      <para>In the case of using an external database (eg Oracle, MySQL), then
      the normal scheme can apply that you would use to backup those database
      (you do back them up, right?). In this case, when restoring, it is also
      a good idea to clear the indexes (delete the directory where the indexes
      are) so they are created fresh from the data (and thus guaranteed to be
      in sync).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Asset list customisation</title>

      <para>In a few places in the BRMS there is an asset list: this list can
      be customised by looking for the AssetListTable.properties file. You can
      then set the header names and the "getter" methods that are used to
      populate the columns. eg you could add in getCreator, or
      getExternalSource as extra fields if you were using them.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding your own logos or styles to the BRMS web GUI</title>

      <para>Everyone loves having their own logo on screen - this is to ensure
      that the people using the application don't forget who they work for or
      what product they are using for more then a nanosecond (the consequences
      of them forgetting are too terrible con contemplate).</para>

      <para>To achieve, this, you can "explode" the deployment war file, and
      locate the JBRMS.html file. <programlisting>
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;meta name='gwt:module' content='org.drools.brms.JBRMS'&gt;
  &lt;link rel='stylesheet' href='JBRMS.css'&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;JBoss Business Rules Management System&lt;/title&gt;
     &lt;link rel="shortcut icon" href="images/drools.gif" type="image/gif"&gt;
     &lt;link rel="icon" href="images/drools.gif" type="image/gif"&gt;
 &lt;/head&gt;
 &lt;body&gt;
     &lt;div class="headerBarblue"&gt;&lt;img src="images/jbossrules_hdrlogo.png" width="279" height="70" /&gt;&lt;/d
 &lt;!-- This script is the bootstrap stuff that simply must be there; it is sent down uncompressed --&gt; 
  &lt;script language='javascript' src='gwt.js'&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;iframe id='__gwt_historyFrame' style='width:0;height:0;border:0'&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting> The above is the contents of the JBRMS.html
      file - it is faily empty (as most of the work is done by the GWT - the
      GUI is built dynamically in the browser). The parts you can customise
      are the style sheet - you can either edit the JBRMS.css (or better yet,
      take a copy, and change the style to be what you need), the "shortcut
      icon" (its what shows in the address bar in the browser etc - also
      change the "icon" link to be the same so it works in IE), and the header
      logo. The rest should be left as is, to allow the GWT components to be
      loaded and attached to the page. This html page is loaded only once by
      the browser when the user accesses the BRMS web GUI.</para>

      <para>The best way to customise is to take a copy of the JBRMS.html -
      and then edit. You can also change the URL by editing the web.xml via
      the normal means. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Import and Export</title>

      <para>A JCR standard export/import feature is available from the Admin
      part of the web interface.</para>

      <para>This will export the entire repository to an XML format as defined
      by the JCR standard.</para>

      <para>In the case of import, it will clear any existing content in the
      database.</para>

      <para>This is not a substitute for backup but can be useful when
      migrating. It is important to note that version history is not exported
      this way, only the current state. Hence it is still recommended that a
      formal backup regime be used at all times on the repository database
      itself.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>