<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Activities</title>
   <section>
      <title>Script task</title>
      
      <figure>
        <title>Script task</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/ScriptTask.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>Represents a script that
        should be executed in this process.  A Script Task should have one incoming
        connection and one outgoing connection.  The associated action specifies what
        should be executed, the dialect used for coding the action (i.e., Java or MVEL),
        and the actual action code.  This code can access any variables and globals.
        There is also a predefined variable <code>kcontext</code> that references the
        <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/jbpm/v6.0.1/javadocs/org/kie/api/runtime/process/ProcessContext.html"><code>ProcessContext</code></ulink> object (which can,
        for example, be used to access the current <code>ProcessInstance</code> or
        <code>NodeInstance</code>, and to get and set variables, or get access to the
        ksession using <code>kcontext.getKieRuntime()</code>). When a Script Task
        is reached in the process, it will execute the action and then continue with the
        next node.  It contains the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which is unique within
            one node container).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Action</emphasis>: The action script associated with this 
            action node.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>Note that you can write any valid Java code inside a script node.  This
        basically allows you to do anything inside such a script node.  There are some
        caveats however:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>When trying to create a higher-level business process, that should
            also be understood by business users, it is probably wise to avoid low-level
            implementation details inside the process, including inside these script tasks.
            A Script Task could still be used to quickly manipulate variables etc. but
            other concepts like a Service Task could be used to model more complex
            behaviour in a higher-level manner.</listitem>
            <listitem>Scripts should be immediate.  They are using the engine thread
            to execute the script.  Scripts that could take some time to execute should
            probably be modeled as an asynchronous Service Task.</listitem>
            <listitem>You should try to avoid contacting external services through a
            script node.  Not only does this usually violate the first two caveats, it
            is also interacting with external services without the knowledge of the engine,
            which can be problematic, especially when using persistence and transactions.
            In general, it is probably wiser to model communication with an external
            service using a service task.</listitem>
            <listitem>Scripts should not throw exceptions.  Runtime exceptions should
            be caught and for example managed inside the script or transformed into
            signals or errors that can then be handled inside the process.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Service task</title>
      
      <figure>
        <title>Service task</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/ServiceTask.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>Represents an (abstract)
        unit of work that should be executed in this process.  All work that is
        executed outside the process engine should be represented (in a declarative
        way) using a Service Task.  Different types of services are predefined, e.g.,
        sending an email, logging a message, etc.  Users can define domain-specific
        services or work items, using a unique name and by defining
        the parameters (input) and results (output) that are associated with this
        type of work.  Check the chapter on domain-specific processes for a
        detailed explanation and illustrative examples of how to define and use
        work items in your processes.  When a Service Task is reached in the
        process, the associated work is executed.  A Service Task should
        have one incoming connection and one outgoing connection.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which is unique
            within one node container).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Parameter mapping</emphasis>: Allows copying the
            value of process variables to parameters of the work item.  Upon
            creation of the work item, the values will be copied.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Result mapping</emphasis>: Allows copying the value
            of result parameters of the work item to a process variable.  Each
            type of work can define result parameters that will (potentially)
            be returned after the work item has been completed.  A result
            mapping can be used to copy the value of the given result parameter
            to the given variable in this process.  For example, the "FileFinder"
            work item returns a list of files that match the given search
            criteria within the result parameter <code>Files</code>.  This list
            of files can then be bound to a process variable for use within the
            process.  Upon completion of the work item, the values will be copied.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>On-entry and on-exit actions</emphasis>: Actions that are
            executed upon entry or exit of this node, respectively.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Additional parameters</emphasis>: Each type of work
            item can define additional parameters that are relevant for that
            type of work.  For example, the "Email" work item defines additional
            parameters such as <code>From</code>, <code>To</code>, <code>Subject</code>
            and <code>Body</code>.  The user can either provide values for these
            parameters directly, or define a
            parameter mapping that will copy the value of the given variable
            in this process to the given parameter; if both are specified, the
            mapping will have precedence.  Parameters of type <code>String</code> can use
            <emphasis><code>#{expression}</code></emphasis> to embed a value in the
            string.  The value will be retrieved when creating the work item, and the
            substitution expression will be replaced by the result of calling
            <code>toString()</code> on the variable.  The expression could
            simply be the name of a variable (in which case it resolves
            to the value of the variable), but more advanced MVEL expressions
            are possible as well, e.g., <code>#{person.name.firstname}</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>User task</title>
      
      <figure>
        <title>User task</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/UserTask.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>Processes can also
        involve tasks that need to be executed by human actors.  A User Task
        represents an atomic task to be executed by a human actor.  It
        should have one incoming connection and one outgoing connection.
        User Tasks can be used in combination with Swimlanes to assign multiple
        human tasks to similar actors. Refer to the chapter on human tasks
        for more details.  A User Task is actually nothing more than a specific
        type of service node (of type "Human Task").  A User Task contains
        the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which is unique
            within one node container).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>TaskName</emphasis>: The name of the human task.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Priority</emphasis>: An integer indicating the priority
            of the human task.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Comment</emphasis>: A comment associated with the human
            task.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>ActorId</emphasis>: The actor id that is responsible for
             executing the human task.  A list of actor id's can be specified using
             a comma (',') as separator.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>GroupId</emphasis>: The group id that is responsible for
             executing the human task.  A list of group id's can be specified using
             a comma (',') as separator.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
             <para><emphasis>Skippable</emphasis>: Specifies whether the human task
             can be skipped, i.e., whether the actor may decide not to execute the
             task.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Content</emphasis>: The data associated with this task.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Swimlane</emphasis>: The swimlane this human task node
            is part of.  Swimlanes make it easy to assign multiple human tasks to
            the same actor.  See the human tasks chapter for more detail on how to
            use swimlanes.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>On entry and on exit actions</emphasis>: Action scripts
            that are executed upon entry and exit of this node, respectively.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Parameter mapping</emphasis>: Allows copying the value
            of process variables to parameters of the human task.  Upon creation of
            the human tasks, the values will be copied.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Result mapping</emphasis>: Allows copying the value 
            of result parameters of the human task to a process variable.  Upon
            completion of the human task, the values will be copied.  A human task
            has a result variable "Result" that contains
            the data returned by the human actor.  The variable "ActorId" contains
            the id of the actor that actually executed the task.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>A user task should define the type of task that needs to be executed
        (using properties like TaskName, Comment, etc.) and who needs to perform it
        (using either actorId or groupId).  Note that if there is data related to
        this specific process instance that the end user needs when performing the
        task, this data should be passed as the content of the task.  The task for
        example does not have access to process variables.  Check out the chapter on
        human tasks to get more detail on how to pass data between human tasks and
        the process instance.</para>
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>Reusable sub-process</title>
    
      <figure>
        <title>Reusable sub-process - Call activity</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/ReusableSubProcess.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>Represents the invocation
        of another process from within this process.  A sub-process node should
        have one incoming connection and one outgoing connection.  When a Reusable Sub-Process
        node is reached in the process, the engine will start the process with the
        given id.  It contains the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which is unique within
            one node container).</para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>ProcessId</emphasis>: The id of the process that should
            be executed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Wait for completion</emphasis> (by default true): If this property is true,
            this sub-process node will only continue if the child process that was started
            has terminated its execution (completed or aborted); otherwise it will 
            continue immediately after starting the subprocess (so it will not wait for
            its completion).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Independent</emphasis> (by default true): If this property is true, the
            child process is started as an independent process, which means that the
            child process will not be terminated if this parent process is completed (or
            this sub-process node is canceled for some other reason);
            otherwise the active sub-process will be canceled on termination of the parent
            process (or cancellation of the sub-process node).  Note that you can only set
            independent to "false" only when "Wait for completion" is set to true.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>On-entry and on-exit actions</emphasis>: Actions that are 
            executed upon entry or exit of this node, respectively.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Parameter in/out mapping</emphasis>: A sub-process node can
            also define in- and out-mappings for variables.  The variables
            given in the "in" mapping will be used as parameters (with the associated 
            parameter name) when starting the process. The variables of the child process
            that are defined for the "out" mappings will be copied to the variables of this
            process when the child process has been completed.  Note that you can use
             "out" mappings only when "Wait for completion" is set to true.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>Business rule task</title>
      
      <figure>
        <title>Business rule task</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/BusinessRuleTask.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>A Business Rule Task Represents a set of rules that need to be 
        evaluated.  The rules are evaluated when the node is reached.  A Rule 
        Task should have one incoming connection and one outgoing connection.  
        Rules are defined in separate files using the Drools rule format.  Rules 
        can become part of a specific ruleflow group using the <literal>ruleflow-group</literal> 
        attribute in the header of the rule.</para>

        <para>When a Rule Task is reached in the process, the engine will start 
        executing rules that are part of the corresponding ruleflow-group (if any).  
        Execution will automatically continue to the next node if there are 
        no more active rules in this ruleflow group. As a result, during the 
        execution of a ruleflow group, new activations belonging to the currently active
        ruleflow group can be added to the Agenda due to changes made to the facts by
        the other rules. Note that the process will immediately continue with the
        next node if it encounters a ruleflow group where there are no active rules
        at that time.</para>
        
        <para>If the ruleflow group was already active, the ruleflow group
        will remain active and execution will only continue if all active rules of the
        ruleflow group has been completed. It contains the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which is unique within
            one node container).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>RuleFlowGroup</emphasis>: The name of the ruleflow group
            that represents the set of rules of this RuleFlowGroup node.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Embedded sub-process</title>
      
      <figure>
        <title>Embedded sub-process</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/EmbeddedSubProcess.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>A Sub-Process is 
        a node that can contain other nodes so that it acts as a node container.
        This allows not only the embedding of a part of the process within such
        a sub-process node, but also the definition of additional variables that
        are accessible for all nodes inside this container. A sub-process should
        have one incoming connection and one
        outgoing connection. It should also contain one start node that defines
        where to start (inside the Sub-Process) when you reach the sub-process.
        It should also contain one or more end events.  Note that, if you use a
        terminating event node inside a sub-process, you are terminating just that
        sub-process. A sub-process ends when there are no more active nodes inside
        the sub-process.
        It contains the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which is unique
            within one node container).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Variables</emphasis>: Additional variables can be
            defined to store data during the execution of this node. See section
            <quote><link linkend='sec.data' endterm="sec.data.title"/></quote>
            for details.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Multi-instance sub-process</title>
      
      <figure>
        <title>Multi-instance sub-process</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-5-CoreEngine/MultipleInstances.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

        <para>A Multiple Instance sub-process is a
        special kind of sub-process that allows you to execute the contained
        process segment multiple times, once for each element in a collection.  A 
        multiple instance sub-process should have one incoming connection and one
        outgoing connection. It waits until the embedded process fragment is completed
        for each of the elements in the given collection before continuing.  It contains
        the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Id</emphasis>: The id of the node (which
            is unique within one node container).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Name</emphasis>: The display name of the node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>CollectionExpression</emphasis>: The name of a
            variable that represents the collection of elements that should
            be iterated over.  The collection variable should be an array or
            of type <code>java.util.Collection</code>.  If the collection
            expression evaluates to null or an empty collection, the multiple
            instances sub-process will be completed immediately and follow its
            outgoing connection.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>VariableName</emphasis>: The name of the variable to contain the current
          element from the collection. This gives nodes within the composite node access to the
          selected element.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">CollectionOutput</emphasis>: The name of a variable that
          represents collection of elements that will gather all output of the multi instance sub
          process</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">OutputVariableName</emphasis>: The name of the variable to
          contain the currentl output from the multi instance activitiy</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">CompletionCondition</emphasis>: MVEL expression that will be
          evaluated on each instance completion to check if given multi instance activity can
          already be completed. In case it evaluates to true all other remaining instances within
          multi instance activity will be canceled.</para>
      </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    
    </section>
        
</section>
