<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Others</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Variables</title>
<para>While the flow chart focuses on specifying the control flow of the
    process, it is usually also necessary to look at the process from a data
    perspective.  Throughout the execution of a process, data can be retrieved,
    stored, passed on and used.</para>

    <para>For storing runtime data, during the execution of the process,
    process variables can be used.  A variable is defined by a name and a data type.
    This could be a basic data type, such as boolean, int, or String, or any kind of
    Object subclass (it must implement Serializable interface).  Variables can be
    defined inside a variable <emphasis>scope</emphasis>.  The top-level
    scope is the variable scope of the process itself.  Subscopes can be
    defined using a Sub-Process.  Variables that are defined in a subscope
    are only accessible for nodes within that scope.</para>

    <para>Whenever a variable is accessed, the process will search for the
    appropriate variable scope that defines the variable.  Nesting of variable
    scopes is allowed. A node will always search for a variable in its parent
    container.  If the variable cannot be found, it will look in that one's
    parent container, and so on, until the process instance itself is reached.
    If the variable cannot be found, a read access yields null, and a write
    access produces an error message, with the process continuing its
    execution.</para>

    <para>Variables can be used in various ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Process-level variables can be set when starting a process
        by providing a map of parameters to the invocation of the
        <code>startProcess</code> method.  These parameters will be set as
        variables on the process scope.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Script actions can access variables directly, simply by using the
        name of the variable as a local parameter in their script.  For example, if the process
        defines a variable of type "org.jbpm.Person" in the process, a script in the process
        could access this directly:</para>
        <programlisting language="java">
// call method on the process variable "person"
person.setAge(10);
        </programlisting>
        <para>Changing the value of a variable in a script can be done through the knowledge context:</para>
          <programlisting language="java">kcontext.setVariable(variableName, value);</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Service tasks (and reusable sub-processes) can pass the value of process
        variables to the outside world (or another process instance) by mapping the variable
        to an outgoing parameter.  For example, the parameter mapping of a service task could define
        that the value of the process variable x should be mapped to a task parameter y right
        before the service is being invoked.  You can also inject the value of process variable
        into a hard-coded parameter String using
        <emphasis><code>#{expression}</code></emphasis>.  For example, the description of a human
        task could be defined as <code>You need to contact person #{person.getName()}</code> (where
        person is a process variable), which will replace this expression by the actual name of the
        person when the service needs to be invoked.  Similarly results of a service (or reusable
        sub-process) can also be copied back to a variable using a result mapping.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Various other nodes can also access data. Event nodes for
        example can store the data associated to the event in a variable, etc. 
        Check the properties of the different node types for more information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Process variables can be accessed also from the Java code of your application. It is
        done by casting of <code>ProcessInstance</code> to <code>WorkflowProcessInstance</code>.
        See the following example:</para>
        <programlisting language="java">
variable = ((WorkflowProcessInstance) processInstance).getVariable("variableName");
        </programlisting>
        <para>To list all the process variables see the following code snippet:</para>
        <programlisting language="java">
org.jbpm.process.instance.ProcessInstance processInstance = ...;
VariableScopeInstance variableScope = (VariableScopeInstance) processInstance.getContextInstance(VariableScope.VARIABLE_SCOPE);
Map&lt;String, Object&gt; variables = variableScope.getVariables();
        </programlisting>
        <para>Note that when you use persistence then you have to use a command based
        approach to get all process variables:</para>
        <programlisting language="java">
Map&lt;String, Object&gt; variables = ksession.execute(new GenericCommand&lt;Map&lt;String, Object&gt;&gt;() {
    public Map&lt;String, Object&gt; execute(Context context) {
        KieSession ksession = ((KnowledgeCommandContext) context).getStatefulKnowledgesession();
        org.jbpm.process.instance.ProcessInstance processInstance = (org.jbpm.process.instance.ProcessInstance) ksession.getProcessInstance(piId);
        VariableScopeInstance variableScope = (VariableScopeInstance) processInstance.getContextInstance(VariableScope.VARIABLE_SCOPE);
        Map&lt;String, Object&gt; variables = variableScope.getVariables();
        return variables;
    }
});</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    <para>Finally, processes (and rules) all have access to globals, i.e.
    globally defined variables and data in the Knowledge Session.  Globals are directly
    accessible in actions just like variables.  Globals need to be defined as part of the
    process before they can be used.  You can for example define globals by clicking the
    globals button when specifying an action script in the Eclipse action property
    editor.  You can also set the value of a global from the outside using 
    <code>ksession.setGlobal(name, value)</code> or from inside process scripts using 
    <code>kcontext.getKnowledgeRuntime().setGlobal(name,value);</code>.</para>
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Scripts</title>
<para>Action scripts can be used in different ways:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Within a Script Task,</listitem>
        <listitem>As entry or exit actions, with a number of nodes.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>Actions have access to globals and the variables that are defined
    for the process and the predefined variable <code>kcontext</code>.  This
    variable is of type
    <code>org.kie.api.runtime.process.ProcessContext</code> and can be used for
    several tasks:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Getting the current node instance (if applicable).  The node
        instance could be queried for data, such as its name and type.  You can
        also cancel the current node instance.</para>
        <programlisting language="java">NodeInstance node = kcontext.getNodeInstance();
String name = node.getNodeName();</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Getting the current process instance.  A process instance
        can be queried for data (name, id, processId, etc.), aborted or
        signaled an internal event.</para>
        <programlisting language="java">ProcessInstance proc = kcontext.getProcessInstance();
proc.signalEvent( type, eventObject );</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Getting or setting the value of variables.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Accessing the Knowledge Runtime allows you do things
        like starting a process, signaling (external) events, inserting data,
        etc.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    <para>jBPM currently supports two dialects, Java and MVEL.
    Java actions should be valid Java code.  MVEL actions can use the business
    scripting language MVEL to express the action.  MVEL accepts any valid Java
    code but additionally provides support for nested accesses of parameters
    (e.g., <code>person.name</code> instead of <code>person.getName()</code>),
    and many other scripting improvements.  Thus, MVEL expressions are more
    convenient for the business user. For example, an action that prints out
    the name of the person in the "requester" variable of the process would
    look like this:</para>

    <programlisting>// Java dialect
System.out.println( person.getName() );

//  MVEL dialect
System.out.println( person.name );
    </programlisting>
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Constraints</title>
<para>Constraints can be used in various locations in your processes,
    for example in a diverging gateway.  jBPM supports two types of constraints:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Code constraints</emphasis> are boolean expressions,
        evaluated directly whenever they are reached. We currently support two
        dialects for expressing these code constraints: Java and MVEL.
        Both Java and MVEL code constraints have direct access
        to the globals and variables defined in the process.  Here is an example
        of a valid Java code constraint, <code>person</code> being a variable
        in the process:</para>
          <programlisting language="java">return person.getAge() > 20;</programlisting>
        <para>A similar example of a valid MVEL code constraint is:</para>
          <programlisting>
return person.age > 20;</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Rule constraints</emphasis> are equals to normal
        Drools rule conditions.  They use the Drools Rule Language syntax to
        express possibly complex constraints.  These rules can, like any other
        rule, refer to data in the Working Memory.  They can also refer to
        globals directly.  Here is an example of a valid rule constraint:</para>
          <programlisting
>Person( age > 20 )</programlisting>
        <para>This tests for a person older than 20 being in the Working
        Memory.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    <para>Rule constraints do not have direct access to variables defined
    inside the process.  It is however possible to refer to the current process
    instance inside a rule constraint, by adding the process instance to the
    Working Memory and matching for the process instance in your rule
    constraint.  We have added special logic to make sure that a variable
    <code>processInstance</code> of type <code>WorkflowProcessInstance</code>
    will only match to the current process instance and not to other process
    instances in the Working Memory.  Note that you are however responsible
    yourself to insert the process instance into the session and, possibly,
    to update it, for example, using Java code or an on-entry or on-exit or
    explicit action in your process. The following example of a rule
    constraint will search for a person with the same name as the value
    stored in the variable "name" of the process:</para>

    <programlisting>processInstance : WorkflowProcessInstance()
Person( name == ( processInstance.getVariable("name") ) )
# add more constraints here ...</programlisting>	
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Timers</title>
<para>Timers wait for a predefined amount of time, before triggering, once
    or repeatedly.  They can be used to trigger
    certain logic after a certain period, or to repeat some action at regular
    intervals.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Configure timer with delay and period</title>
      <para>A Timer node is set up with a delay and a period.  The delay specifies
      the amount of time to wait after node activation before
      triggering the timer the first time.  The period defines the time between
      subsequent trigger activations. A period of 0 results in a one-shot timer.</para>

      <para>The (period and delay) expression should be of the form
      [#d][#h][#m][#s][#[ms]].  You can specify the amount of days,
      hours, minutes, seconds and milliseconds (which is the default if you don't
      specify anything).  For example, the expression "1h" will wait one hour
      before triggering the timer (again).</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configure timer ISO-8601 date format</title>
      <para>since version 6 timers can be configured with valid <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO_8601">
      ISO8601</ulink> date format that supports both one shot timers and repeatable timers. Timers can be defined
      as data dn time representation, time duration or repeating intervals</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Date - 2013-12-24T20:00:00.000+02:00 - fires exactly at Christmas Eve at 8PM</listitem>
        <listitem>Duration - PT1S - fires once after 1 second</listitem>
        <listitem>Repeatable intervals - R/PT1S - fires every second, no limit, alternatively R5/PT1S will fire 5 times every second</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configure timer with process variables</title>
      In addition to two configuration otpions above timers can be specified using process variable that can consists
      of string representation of ether delay and period or ISO8601 date format. By specifying #{variable} engine will
      dynamically extract process variable and use it as timer expression.
    </section>

    <para>The timer service is responsible for making sure that timers get
    triggered at the appropriate times.  Timers can also be cancelled, meaning
    that the timer will no longer be triggered.</para>

    <para>Timers can be used in two ways inside a process:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>A Timer Event may be added to the process flow. Its activation
        starts the timer, and when it triggers, once or repeatedly, it activates the
        Timer node's successor. Subsequently, the outgoing connection of a
        timer with a positive period is triggered multiple times. Cancelling a
        Timer node also cancels the associated timer, after which no more triggers
        will occur.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Timers can be associated with a Sub-Process or tasks as a boundary event.
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  </section>
    
</section>
