<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="../../">
      <title>Number Guess</title>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Number Guess 
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.NumberGuessExample
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> NumberGuess.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Demonstrate use of Rule Flow to organise Rules
</programlisting>

      <para>The "Number Guess" example shows the use of RuleFlow, a way of
      controlling the order in which rules are fired. It uses widely
      understood workflow diagrams to make clear the order that groups of
      rules will be executed.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating the Number Guess RuleBase - extract 1 from
        NumberGuessExample.java main() method</title>

        <programlisting>final KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();
        kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "NumberGuess.drl",
                                                                    ShoppingExample.class ),
                              ResourceType.DRL );
        kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "NumberGuess.rf",
                                                                    ShoppingExample.class ),
                              ResourceType.DRF );

        final KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
        kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages() );

</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The creation of the package, and the loading of the rules (using
      the add() method ) is the same as the previous examples.
      There is a additional line to add the RuleFlow (NumberGuess.rf) as you
      have the option of specifying different ruleflows for the same KnowledgeBase.
      Otherwise the KnowledgeBase is created in the same manner as before.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Starting the RuleFlow - extract 2 from NumberGuessExample.java
        main() method</title>

        <programlisting>final StatefulKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatefulKnowledgeSession();

        KnowledgeRuntimeLogger logger = KnowledgeRuntimeLoggerFactory.newFileLogger(ksession, "log/numberguess");

        ksession.insert( new GameRules( 100,
                                        5 ) );
        ksession.insert( new RandomNumber() );
        ksession.insert( new Game() );

        ksession.startProcess( "Number Guess" );
        ksession.fireAllRules();

        logger.close();

        ksession.dispose();

</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Once we have a KnowledgeBase we can use it to obtain a stateful
      session. Into our session we insert our facts (standard Java Objects).
      For simplicity in this sample, these classes are all contained within
      our NumberGuessExample.java file. The GameRules class provides the
      maximum range and the number of guesses allowed. The RandomNumber class
      automatically generates a number between 0 and 100 and makes it
      available to our rules after insertion (via the getValue() method). The
      Game class keeps track of the guesses we have made before, and the
      number of guesses we have made.</para>

      <para>Note that before we call the standard fireAllRules() method, we
      also start the process that we loaded earlier (via the startProcess()
      method). We explain where to obtain the parameter we pass ("Number
      Guess" - the id of the ruleflow) when we talk about the RuleFlow file
      and the graphical RuleFlow editor below.</para>

      <para>Before we finish we our Java code , we note that In 'real life' we
      would examine the final state of the objects (e.g. how many guesses it
      took, so that we could add it to a high score table). For this example
      we are content to ensure the working memory session is cleared by
      calling the dispose() method.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>RuleFlow for the NumberGuess Example</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-ruleflow.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If you open the NumberGuess.rf file open in the Drools IDE (and
      have the JBoss Rules extensions installed correctly in Eclipse) you
      should see the above diagram, similar to a standard flowchart. Its icons
      are similar (but not exactly the same) as the JBoss jBPM workflow
      product. Should you wish to edit the diagram, a menu of available
      components should be available to the left of the diagram in the IDE,
      which is call the pallete. This diagram is saved in a (almost human)
      readable xml format, using xstream.</para>

      <para>If it is not already open, ensure the properties view is visible
      in the IDE. It can opened by selecting Window -&gt; Show View -&gt;
      Other and then select the Properties view. If you do this <emphasis
      role="bold">before</emphasis> you select any item on the RuleFlow (or
      click on blank space in the RuleFlow) you should be presented with the
      following set of properties.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Properties for the Number Guess RuleFlow</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-ruleflow-properties.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Keep an eye on the properties view as we progress through the
      example RuleFlow as it gives valuable information. In this case it
      provides us with the ID of the RuleFlow process that we used in our
      earlier code example when we called session.startprocess().</para>

      <para>To give an overview of each of the node types (boxes) in the
      NumberGuess RuleFlow.</para>

      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Start and End nodes (green arrow and red box) are where
            the RuleFlow starts and ends.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RuleFlowGroup (simple yellow box). These map to the
            RuleFlowGroups in our rules (DRL) file that we will look at later.
            For example when the flow reaches the 'Too High' RuleFlowGroup,
            only those rules marked with an attribute of <emphasis
            role="bold">ruleflow-group "Too High" </emphasis> can potentially
            fire.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Action Nodes (yellow box with cog like icon). These can
            perform standard Java method calls. Most action nodes in this
            example call System.out.println to give an indication to the user
            of what is going on.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Split and Join Nodes (Blue Ovals) such as "Guess Correct"
            and "More Guesses Join" where the flow of control can split
            (according to various conditions) and / or rejoin.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Arrows that indicate the flow between the various
            nodes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>These various nodes work together with the Rules to make the
      Number Guess game work. For example, the "Guess" RuleFlowGroup allows
      only the rule "Get user Guess" to fire (details below) as only that Rule
      has a matching attribute of <emphasis role="bold">ruleflow-group
      "Guess"</emphasis></para>

      <example>
        <title>A Rule that will fire only a specific point in the RuleFlow -
        extract from NumberGuess.drl</title>

        <programlisting>rule "Get user Guess"
 ruleflow-group "Guess"
 no-loop
 when    
     $r : RandomNumber()
     rules : GameRules( allowed : allowedGuesses )
     game : Game( guessCount &lt; allowed )
     not ( Guess() )
 then
     System.out.println( "You have " + ( rules.allowedGuesses - game.guessCount ) 
     + " out of " + rules.allowedGuesses + " guesses left.\nPlease enter your guess 
     from 0 to " + rules.maxRange );
        br = new BufferedReader( new InputStreamReader( System.in ) );
        modify ( game ) { guessCount = game.guessCount + 1 }
        i = br.readLine();        
    insert( new Guess( i ) );
end</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The rest of this rule is fairly standard : The <emphasis
      role="bold">LHS (when)</emphasis> section of the rule states that it
      will be activated for each <emphasis>RandomNumber</emphasis> object
      inserted into the working memory where <emphasis>guessCount</emphasis>
      is less than the <emphasis>allowedGuesses</emphasis> ( read from the
      GameRules Class) and where the user has not guessed the correct
      number.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">RHS (consequence, then)</emphasis>
      prints a message to the user, then awaits user input from
      <emphasis>System.in. </emphasis> After getting this input (as System.in
      blocks until the &lt;return&gt; key is pressed) it updates/modifes the
      guess count, the actual guess and makes both available in the working
      memory.</para>

      <para>The rest of the Rules file is fairly standard ; the package
      declares the dialect is set to MVEL, various Java classes are imported.
      In total, there are five rules in this file:</para>

      <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Get User Guess, the Rule we examined above.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A Rule to record the highest guess.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A Rule to record the lowest guess.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A Rule to inspect the guess and retract it from memory if
            incorrect.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A Rule that notifies the user that all guesses have been
            used up.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
	
	<para>One point of integration between the standard Rules and
      the RuleFlow is via the 'ruleflow-group' attribute on the rules (as
      dicussed above). A <emphasis role="bold">second point of integration
      between the Rules File (drl) and the Rules Flow .rf files </emphasis>is
      that the Split Nodes (the blue ovals) can use values in working memory
      (as updated by the Rules) to decide which flow of action to take. To see
      how this works click on the "Guess Correct Node" ; then within the
      properties view, open the constraints editor (the button at the right
      that appears once you click on the 'Constraints' property line). You
      should see something similar to the Diagram below.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Edit Constraints for the GuessCorrect Node</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-editconstraints.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Click on 'Edit' beside 'To node Too High' and you see a dialog
      like the one below. The values in the 'Textual Editor' follow the
      standard Rule Format (LHS) and can refer to objects in working memory.
      The consequence (RHS) is that the flow of control follows this node
      (i.e. To node Too high') if the LHS expression evaluates to true.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Constraints Editor for the GuessCorrect Node / value too
        high</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-constraint-toohigh.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Since the NumberGuess.java example contains a main() method, it
      can be run as a standard Java application (either from the command line
      or via the IDE). A typical game might result in the interaction below
      (the numbers in bold are typed in by the user).</para>

      <example>
        <title>Example Console output where the Number Guess Example beat the
        human!</title>

        <programlisting>You have 5 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">50</emphasis>
Your guess was too high
You have 4 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">25</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have 3 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">37</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have 2 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">44</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have 1 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">47</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have no more guesses
The correct guess was 48 

</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>A summary of what is happening in this sample is:</para>


        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Main() method of NumberGuessExample.java loads RuleBase,
            gets a StatefulSession and inserts Game, GameRules and
            RandomNumber (containing the target number) objects into it. This
            method sets the process flow we are going to use, and fires all
            rules. Control passes to the RuleFlow.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The NumberGuess.rf RuleFlow begins at the Start node.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Control passes (via the "more guesses" join node) to the
            Guess Node..</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>At the Guess node, the appropriate RuleFlowGroup ("Get user
            Guess") is enabled. In this case the Rule "Guess" (in the
            NumberGuess.drl file) is triggered. This rule displays a message
            to the user, takes the response, and puts it into memory. Flow
            passes to the next Rule Flow Node.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>At the next node , "Guess Correct", constraints inspect the
            current session and decide which path we take next.</para>

            <para>If the guess in step 4 was too high / too low flow procees
            along a path which has (i) An action node with normal Java code
            prints a too high / too low statement and (ii) a RuleFlowGroup
            causes a highest guess / lowest guess Rule to be triggered in the
            Rules file. Flow passes from these nodes to step 6.</para>

            <para>If the guess in step 4 just right we proceed along the path
            towards the end of the Rule Flow. Before we get there, an action
            node with normal Java code prints a statement "you guessed
            correctly". There is a join node here (just before the Rule Flow
            End) so that our no-more-guesses path (step 7) can also terminate
            the RuleFlow.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Control passes as per the RuleFlow via a join node, a guess
            incorrect RuleFlowGroup (triggers a rule to retract a guess from
            working memory) onto the "more guesses" decision node.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The "more guesses" decision node (right hand side of
            ruleflow) uses constraints (again looking at values that the Rules
            have put into the working memory) to decide if we have more
            guesses and if so, goto step 3. If not we proceed to the end of
            the workflow, via a RuleFlowGroup that triggers a rule stating
            "you have no more guesses".</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Loop 3-7 continues until the number is guessed
            correctly, or we run out of guesses.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

    </section>
