<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="../../">
		<title>Honest Politician Example</title>

		<para>The honest politician example demonstrates truth maintenance with logical assertions, the basic premise is that an object can only exist while a statement is true. A rule's consequence can logical insert an object with the insertLogical method, this means the object will only remain in the working memory as long as the rule that logically inserted it remains true, when the rule is no longer true the object is automatically retracted.</para>

    <para>In this example there is Politician class with a name and a boolean
    value for honest state, four politicians with honest state set to true are
    inserted.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Politician Class</title>

        <programlisting>public class Politician {
    private String name;
    private boolean honest;
    ...
}</programlisting>
      </example><example>
        <title>Honest Politician Example Execution</title>

        <programlisting>Politician blair  = new Politician("blair", true);
Politician bush  = new Politician("bush", true);
Politician chirac  = new Politician("chirac", true);
Politician schroder   = new Politician("schroder", true);
        
ksession.insert( blair );
ksession.insert( bush );
ksession.insert( chirac );
ksession.insert( schroder );

ksession.fireAllRules();</programlisting>
      </example>The console out shows that while there is atleast one honest
    polician democracy lives, however as each politician is in turn corrupted
    by an evil corporation, when all politicians are dishonest democracy is
    dead.<example>
        <title>Honest Politician Example Console Output</title>

        <programlisting>Hurrah!!! Democracy Lives
I'm an evil corporation and I have corrupted schroder
I'm an evil corporation and I have corrupted chirac
I'm an evil corporation and I have corrupted bush
I'm an evil corporation and I have corrupted blair
We are all Doomed!!! Democracy is Dead
</programlisting>
      </example>As soon as there is one more more honest politcians in the
    working memory a new Hope object is logically asserted, this object will
    only exist while there is at least one or more honest politicians, the
    moment all politicians are dishonest then the Hope object will be
    automatically retracted. This rule is given a salience of 10 to make sure
    it fires before any other rules, as at this stage the "Hope is Dead" rule
    is actually true.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Honest Politician Example : Rule "We have an honest
      politician"</title>

      <programlisting>rule "We have an honest Politician"
    salience 10
    when
        exists( Politician( honest == true ) )
    then
        insertLogical( new Hope() );
end</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>As soon as a Hope object exists the "Hope Lives" rule matches, and
    fires, it has a salience of 10 so that it takes priority over "Corrupt the
    Honest".</para>

    <example>
      <title>Honest Politician Example : Rule "Hope Lives"</title>

      <programlisting>rule "Hope Lives"
    salience 10
    when
        exists( Hope() )
    then
        System.out.println("Hurrah!!! Democracy Lives");
end</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Now that hope exists and we have, at the start, four honest
    politicians we have 4 activations for this rule all in conflict. This rule
    iterates over those rules firing each one in turn, corrupting each
    politician so that they are no longer honest. When all four politicians
    have been corrupted we have no politicians with the property "honest ==
    true" thus the rule "We have an honest Politician" is no longer true and
    the object it logical inserts "new Hope()" is automatically
    retracted.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Honest Politician Example : Rule "Corrupt the Honest"</title>

      <programlisting>rule "Corrupt the Honest"
    when
        politician : Politician( honest == true )   
        exists( Hope() )
    then
        System.out.println( "I'm an evil corporation and I have corrupted " + politician.getName() );
        modify ( politician ) { honest = false };
end</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>With Hope being automatically retracted, via the truth maintenance
    system, then Hope no longer exists in the system and this rule will match
    and fire.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Honest Politician Example : Rule "Hope is Dead"</title>

      <programlisting>rule "Hope is Dead"
    when
        not( Hope() )
    then
        System.out.println( "We are all Doomed!!! Democracy is Dead" );
end</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>lets take a look the audit trail for this application:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Honest Politician Example Audit View</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/HonestPoliticianExample/honest_politician_audit.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The moment we insert the first politician we have two activations,
    the "We have an honest Politician" is activated only once for the first
    inserted politician because it uses an existential 'exists' conditional
    element which only matches. the rule "Hope is Dead" is also activated at
    this stage, because as of yet we have not inserted the Hope object. "We
    have an honest Politician" fires first, as it has a higher salience over
    "Hope is Dead" which inserts the Hope object, that action is highlighted
    green above. The insertion of the Hope object activates "Hope Lives" and
    de-activates "Hope is Dead", it also actives "Corrupt the Honest" for each
    inserted honested politician. "Rule Hope Lives" executes printing
    "Hurrah!!! Democracy Lives". Then for each politician the rule "Corrupt
    the Honest" fires printing "I'm an evil corporation and I have corrupted
    X", where X is the name of the politician, and modifies the politicians
    honest value to false. When the last honest polician is corrupted Hope is
    automatically retracted, by the truth maintenance system, as shown by the
    blue highlighted area. The green highlighted area shows the origin of the
    currently selected blue highlighted area. Once Hope is retracted "Hope is
    dead" activates and fires printing "We are all Doomed!!! Democracy is
    Dead".</para>

  </section>
