<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Performance considerations</title>

  <para>In any reasonably complex application, there are many things that may
  effect performance. The usual advice applies of course (ie don't speculate,
  measure, profile and plan). In terms of the rule engine, it does its best to
  be as efficient as possibly, without too much thought needed, most people
  should not need to read this chapter in detail.</para>

  <para>Note that for someone who is using a rule engine of the first time,
  the most noticeable "cost" will be the startup of the rule engine (which is
  actually compiling the rules) - this problem is easily solved - simply cache
  the RuleBase instances (or the rule packages) and only update rules as
  needed (there are many ways to achieve this in your application which will
  not be covered here).</para>

  <para>The remainder of this chapter is considerations on tuning the runtime
  performance of rules (not compiling), which is where performance often
  really counts.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Beta Node Memory Indexing</title>

    <para>As explained in the chapter on the Rete Algorithm, BetaNodes are
    nodes that have two inputs: the left input (for tuples) and the right
    input (for single objects). Each beta node has two memories, one for each
    input: the left memory and the right memory.</para>

    <para>So, when a single object arrives at the right input of the node, it
    tries to match every tuple in the left memory according to the constraints
    defined for the given BetaNode. Those elements that match are propagated
    down through the network. The symmetrical behavior happens for when a
    tuple arrives at the left input of the node. See diagram bellow: </para>

    <figure>
      <title>Beta Node</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="300" fileref="beta_node.svg"
                     format="SVG" scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="beta_node.png" format="PNG"
                     scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When the number of elements in each of the Beta Node Memories starts
    to grow, the matching process starts to slow down, as each new element
    that arrives needs to try to match all the elements in the opposite memory
    for the given constraints. This process becomes a serious limitation for
    real systems where thousands of facts are asserted into working memory and
    where the Rete Network has several Beta Nodes.</para>

    <para>One way of minimizing the problem is to index each of the BetaNode
    memories in a way that when a new element arrives, it does not need to
    iterate over all elements of the opposite memory in order to find its
    matches.</para>

    <para>So, for example, if we have a Rule like the following:</para>
    <programlisting>rule "find brothers"
    when
        p1: Person( $mother : mother )
        p2: Person( mother == $mother )
    then
        // do something
end
</programlisting>
    <para>If no indexing is used, each new Person object asserted into
    working memory will try to match each other previously asserted Person
    object to find those that have the same mother. So, if we have 1000 Person
    objects already asserted into working memory, and we assert a new one, the
    new one will try to match each of the 1000 previously asserted
    objects.</para>

    <para>If we index BetaNode memories by the “mother” attribute, though,
    when a new Person is asserted into memory, it will try to match only the
    previously asserted objects that have the same mother attribute, in a very
    efficient way using the previously built index. So, if the new object has
    only one brother previously asserted into memory, it will match only one
    object, avoiding the 999 tries that would fail.</para>

    <para>Drools implements BetaNode indexing exactly as described above in
    order to boost performance. The BetaNode indexing is enabled by default
    and users usually don’t need to worry about it. Although, for specific
    situations where a user has a limited amount of memory or for some reason
    does not want to incur in the indexing overhead, indexing can be disabled
    for each of the memories, by setting the following system properties to
    <literal>false</literal>:</para>
    <programlisting>org.drools.reteoo.beta.index-left
org.drools.reteoo.beta.index-right

For example:
..when you launch the application (or in the container as appropriate).
-Dorg.drools.reteoo.beta.index-right=false
-Dorg.drools.reteoo.beta.index-left=false
</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Indexing Performance Tuning</title>

    <para>A good way to understand what happens when indexing is used is to
    make an analogy to databases systems. As we all know, indexing is a great
    mechanism for performance improvements on database queries, but also adds
    an overhead to other operations like insert, updates and deletes. Also,
    there is a memory consumption cost involved. A well planned set of indexes
    is essential for most enterprise applications and the responsible for
    defining them is usually the DBA. Once indexes are defined, when a query
    is executed against that database, a query planner component is used by
    database systems to estimate the best plan to run the query with the best
    performance, sometimes using the index, sometimes not.</para>

    <para>Working memory has the same issues and same thoughts are valid here.
    Drools implements an automatic indexing strategy to index beta node
    memories. Just to have some data to understand the consequences of it,
    lets use Manners 64 benchmark test results on a Pentium IV 3 Ghz HT
    machine with 1.0 Gb memory. This is not really a detailed benchmark test,
    but simply some rough numbers in order to make the scenario easier to
    understand:</para>
    <programlisting>Manners 64 without indexes: 135000 millisec to run 
Manners 64 with BetaNode indexes: 10078 millisec to run on average</programlisting>

    <para>It is obvious by the previous run times that indexes overall
    benefits pays off the overhead to keep them, at least in terms of
    performance. We are not analyzing limited memory environments here.</para>

    <para>Although, every system has its own peculiarities and sometimes it is
    possible to do some fine tuning on performance. For example, in our
    Manners 64 example, if we disable the right memory indexing we would have
    the following result:</para>
    <programlisting>Manners 64 with BetaNode indexing only for left memory: 142000 millisec to run on average
</programlisting>
    <para>The above is even worse than no using any indexing. This
    happens clearly because for Manners 64, the left indexing overhead is
    bigger than its benefit. So, if we do the contrary, leaving right indexing
    enabled and disabling the left indexing, we get the following result:</para>
    <programlisting>Manners 64 with BetaNode indexing only for right memory: 8765 millisec to run on average
</programlisting>
    <para>So, we have the best scenario now. For Manners 64, the best
    would be to disable left indexing, leaving only right indexing
    enabled.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Re-arranging constraints</title>

      <para>Another tip to tune performance when using indexing is always to
      write your rules in a way that the most restrictive constraints are
      declared before the less restrictive ones in your rule. For example, if
      you have a rule with a column like this: <programlisting>Employee (department == $aDepartment, name == $aName)
</programlisting> Rewriting it as shown bellow will probably give you a better
      performance, as “name” is probably a more restrictive constraint than
      “department”: <programlisting>Employee (name == $aName, department == $aDepartment)
</programlisting> (Unless you work in an organization where there are more
      departments then employees, which could well be the case in a Government
      organization ;)</para>
    </section>

    <para>Some other improvements are being developed for Drools in this area
    and will be documented as they become available in future versions.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Large Ruleset</title>
    <para>For this section, large rulesets are define as the following</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>1-500 - small ruleset</listitem>
    <listitem>500-2000 - medium ruleset</listitem>
    <listitem>2000+ - large ruleset</listitem>
    <listitem>10,000 - extremely large ruleset</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>There are some cases where a rule engine has to handle 500,000 or 1 million rules.
    Those are primarily machine learning and AI systems, where a rule engine produces new
    rules, terms and facts at execution time. Those topics are beyond the scope of the
    documentation and aren't covered. The techniques described are focused on business rules.</para>
    <para>The first thing to do is identify why there are so many rules and whether or not
    rewriting the rules can solve the problem. There's a couple of things to look for.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>Do the rules have a lot of constant values hard coded in the conditions?</listitem>
    <listitem>Is the domain model a huge flat spreadsheet with 100+ columns?</listitem>
    <listitem>Do most of the rules share the same conditions?</listitem>
    <listitem>Can the logic be divided into stages?</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>If you answer yes to any of the 4 questions, chances are you can solve the issue with
    changing the rules. Managing 100,000 rules or even 1,000,000 rules is a huge headache, so
    try to avoid it. Examine the rules and see if it matches any of the following scenarios.</para>
    <programlisting>
If
  customer.account == "abcd"
  customer.type == "basic"
  .....
Then
  // do something
    </programlisting>
    <para>The basic problem with rules sample above, is the rules have most of the values hard
    coded. If the average customer has 50 rules and there's 40 million customers, the system has
    200 million rules. Let's use a more concrete example to flesh this out.</para>
    <programlisting>
If
  customer.accountId == "peter"
  customer.type == "level2"
  customer.favoriateActor == "jackie chan"
Then
  recommend movies with jackie chan

If
  customer.accountId == "peter"
  customer.type == "level2"
  customer.favoriateActor == "jet li"
Then
  recommend movies with jet li
    </programlisting>
    <para>Looking at the example, the first to question ask is "do these kinds of rules apply
    to all customers?" If it does, the first condition in the rule "customer.accountId" is
    pointless. It's pointless because all rules of this type will have that condition.
    Although the accountId changes, the rule can effectively ignore it. If we rewrite the rule
    this way, the rule can apply to any customer that likes jackie chan and jet li.</para>
    <programlisting>
If
  customer.type == "level2"
  customer.favoriateActor == "jackie chan"
Then
  recommend movies with jackie chan

If
  customer.type == "level2"
  customer.favoriateActor == "jet li"
Then
  recommend movies with jet li
    </programlisting>
    <para>The reason we do this is straight forward. The rules reason over data. Having a
    ton of rules with the customer's accountId hard coded doesn't do any good, because we
    want the rule engine to only evaluate the active sessions. We don't want to load all
    the customers into the rule engine. We can take it a step further and make the rule more
    general.</para>
    <programlisting>
If
  customer.type == "level2"
  customer.accountId ?id // bind the account id to a variable
  favorites.accountId ?id // find the list of favorites by the account id
Then
  recommend all items in the favorites
    </programlisting>
    <para>With this change, it can reduce the number of rules significantly. This is one
    reason the RETE approach is often called "data driven approach". Let's take this example
    a bit further and define 10 types of customers from level1 to level10. Say we run a mega
    online store and customers can define their favorites in each of the categories (books,
    videos, music, toys, electronics, clothing). What happens if a customer has different
    levels for each category. Using the hard coded approach, one might have to add more rules.
    If we change the rule and make it more generalized, the same rule can handle multiple
    categories.</para>
    <programlisting>
If
  recommendation.level ?lvl // bind the recommendation level to a variable
  recommendation.category ?rcat // bind the recommendation category
  customer.accountId ?id // bind the account id to a variable
  favorites.accountId ?id // find the list of favorites by the account id
  favorites.category ?rcat // match favorite to recommendation category
  favorites.level ?lvl // match the favorite level to recommendation level
Then
  recommend all items in the favorites    
    </programlisting>
    <para>So what is the cost of making the rule dynamic and data driven? Obviously, hard
    coding a rule is going to be faster than making it generalized, but the performance delta
    should be small. In the case where a ruleset is small, the hard coded approach may have a
    slight performance lead. Why is that? Lets look at 2 different types of rule engines:
    procedural and RETE.</para>
    <para>In a procedural engine, one can build a decision tree and end the evaluation once
    the data fails to satisfy the conditions at a given level. As the rule count increases,
    there are more rules the engine has to evaluate. In a procedural approach, the rules have
    to be sequenced in the optimal order to get the best results. The limitation of sorting
    the rules in optimal sequence is that many cases it's not possible to pre-sort. If we use
    a RETE rule engine, the hard coded rules result in fewer joins for a small number of rules.
    As the rule count grows, the single rule will perform better. The equation to estimate the
    threshold where the generalized form is faster than hard coding the constants.</para>
    <para>bn = join nodes, lf = left facts, rf = right facts, ae = average number of
    evaluation descending from the object type node for a random sample, f = facts,
    hd = hard coded constants in the rules, general = generalized form using joins</para>
    <para>general( sum( bn(lf * rf) ) + sum(ae * f) ) &lt; hd( sum( bn(lf * rf) ) + sum(ae * f) )</para>
    <para>The best way to quantify the threshold is to write rules in both formats and run a
    series of tests. Given that most projects are under tight schedules, developers don't
    always have time to do this. The other common problem is using really large flat objects.
    In a nutshell, using large flat objects leads to the same problem as hard coding the
    constants in the rules. The solution to the problem is to change the domain objects,
    such that it models the business concepts in a concise manner. That isn't always an
    option.</para>
    <para>When most of the rules share the same conditions, there's two solutions. The best
    solution is to rewrite the rules to use chaining. Identify the common conditions and extract
    it into a generalized rule. The generalized rule then trigger subsequent rules by asserting
    a new fact. Often this can reduce the rules by an order of magnitude or more. The second
    option is to put common conditions at the beginning of the rule. What this does is it
    allows RETE rule engines to share those nodes. When the nodes are shared, it reduces the
    cost from a memory and performance perspective.</para>
    <para>If the ruleset can be divided into smaller chunks, it's a good idea to divide it into
    discrete stages and load each ruleset on a different JVM or server. Depending on the
    situation, this may not be an option. So what can you do when the ruleset is large and
    rewriting the rules isn't an option?</para>
    <para>The only viable option is to scale the hardware and use a different JVM. This means
    using 64bit JVM from SUN, IBM or BEA JRockit on a machine with at least 8Gb RAM. Depending
    on the ruleset, the system may need more RAM.</para>
    
  </section>
</section>
