<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Deployment options</title>

  <para>Once you have rules integrated in your application (or ideally before)
  you will need to plan how to deploy rules along with your application.
  Typically rules are used to allow changes to application business logic
  without re-deploying the whole application. This means that the rules must
  be provided to the application as data, not as part of the application (eg
  embedded in the classpath).</para>

  <para>The recommended way of deploying depends on how you are managing your
  rules. If you are using the BRMS, you should use the RuleAgent (the detailed
  documentation for this is in the chapter on the BRMS/Guvnor). You can still
  use the RuleAgent even without the BRMS, in which case you will need to use
  ant (the drools-ant task or something custom) to create serialized "Package"
  objects of your rules.</para>

  <para>As every organization is subtly different, and different deployment
  patterns will be needed. Many organizations have (or should have)
  configuration management processes for changes to production systems. It is
  best to think of rules as "data" rather then software in that regard.
  However, as rules can contain a considerable amount of powerful logic,
  proper procedures should be used in testing and verifying rule changes, and
  approving changes before exposing them to the world. If you need to "roll
  your own" deployment, or have specific deployment needs, the information is
  provided in this chapter for your reference, but for the most part, people
  should be able to deploy either as the agent, or in the classpath.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Deployment using the KnowledgeAgent</title>

    <para>The easiest and most automated way to deploy rules is to use the
    Knowlegde Agent as described in the quick start guide. This can access rules from the file system, classpath, web server, the Guvnor server (which is really a web server) and more. Rules can be in DRL, XLS, compiled binary form and more.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployment using drl source</title>

    <para>In some cases people may wish to deploy drl source. In that case all
    the drools-compiler dependencies will need to be on the classpath for your
    application. You can then load drl from file, classpath, or a database
    (for example) and compile as needed. The trick, as always, is knowing when
    rules change (this is also called "in process" deployment as described
    below).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deploying rules in your classpath</title>

    <para>If you have rules which do not change separate to your application,
    you can put packaged into your classpath. This can be done either as
    source (in which case the drl can be compiled, and the rulebase cached the
    first time it is needed) or else you can pre-compile packages, and just
    include the binary packages in the classpath.</para>

    <para>Keep in mind with this approach to make a rule change, you will both
    need to deploy your app (and if its a server - restart the
    application).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployable objects, RuleBase, Package etc.</title>

    <para>In the simplest possible scenario, you would compile and construct a
    rulebase inside your application (from drl source), and then cache that
    rulebase. That rulebase can be shared across threads, spawning new working
    memories to process transactions (working memories are then discarded).
    This is essentially the stateless mode. To update the rulebase, a new
    rulebase is loaded, and then swapped out with the cached rulebase (any
    existing threads that happen to be using the old rulebase will continue to
    use it until they are finished, in which case it will eventually be
    garbage collected).</para>

    <para>There are many more sophisticated approaches to the above - Drools
    rule engine is very dynamic, meaning pretty much all the components can be
    swapped out on the fly (rules, packages) even when there are *existing*
    working memories in use. For instance rules can be retracted from a
    rulebase which has many in-use working memories - the RETE network will
    then be adjusted to remove that rule without having to assert all the
    facts again. Long running working memories are useful for complex
    applications where the rule engine builds up knowledge over time to assist
    with decision making for instance - it is in these cases that the
    dynamic-ness of the engine can really shine.</para>

    <section>
      <title>DRL and PackageDescr</title>

      <para>One option is to deploy the rules in source form. This leaves the
      runtime engine (which must include the compiler components) to compile
      the rules, and build the rule base. A similar approach is to deploy the
      "PackageDescr" object, which means that the rules are pre-parsed (for
      syntactic errors) but not compiled into the binary form. Use the
      PackageBuilder class to achieve this. You can of course use the XML form
      for the rules if needed.</para>

      <programlisting>PackageDescr, PackageBuilder, RuleBaseLoader</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Package</title>

      <para>This option is the most flexible. In this case, Packages are built
      from DRL source using PackageBuilder - but it is the binary Package
      objects that are actually deployed. Packages can be merged together.
      That means a package containing perhaps a single new rule, or a change
      to an existing rule, can be built on its own, and then merged in with an
      existing package in an existing RuleBase. The rulebase can then notify
      existing working memories that a new rule exists (as the RuleBase keeps
      "weak" links back to the Working Memory instances that it spawned). The
      rulebase keeps a list of Packages, and to merge into a package, you will
      need to know which package you need to merge into (as obviously, only
      rules from the same package name can be merged together).</para>

      <para>Package objects themselves are serializable, hence they can be
      sent over a network, or bound to JNDI, Session etc.</para>

      <programlisting>PackageBuilder, RuleBase, org.drools.rule.Package</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>RuleBase</title>

      <para>Compiled Packages are added to rulebases. RuleBases are
      serializable, so they can be a binary deployment unit themselves. This
      can be a useful option for when rulebases are updated as a whole - for
      short lived working memories. If existing working memories need to have
      rules changed on the fly, then it is best to deploy Package objects.
      Also beware that rulebases take more processing effort to serialize (may
      be an issue for some large rulebases).</para>

      <programlisting>RuleBase, RuleBaseLoader</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Serializing</title>

      <para>Practically all of the rulebase related objects in Drools are
      serializable. For a working memory to be serializable, all of your
      objects must of course be serializable. So it is always possible to
      deploy remotely, and "bind" rule assets to JNDI as a means of using them
      in a container environment.</para>
    </section>

    <para>Please note that when using package builder, you may want to check
    the hasError() flag before continuing deploying your rules (if there are
    errors, you can get them from the package builder - rather then letting it
    fail later on when you try to deploy).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployment patterns</title>

    <section>
      <title>In process rule building</title>

      <para>In this case, rules are provided to the runtime system in source
      form. The runtime system contains the drools-compiler component to build
      the rules. This is the simplest approach.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Out of process rule building</title>

      <para>In this case, rules are built into their binary process outside of
      the runtime system (for example in a deployment server). The chief
      advantage of deploying from an outside process is that the runtime
      system can have minimal dependencies (just one jar). It also means that
      any errors to do with compiling are well contained and and known before
      deployment to the running system is attempted.</para>

      <para>Use the PackageBuilder class out of process, and then use
      getPackage() to get the Package object. You can then (for example)
      serialize the Package object to a file (using standard Java
      serialization). The runtime system, which only needs drools-core, can
      then load the file using
      RuleBaseFactory.newRuleBase().addPackage(deserialized package
      object).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Some deployment scenarios</title>

      <para>This section contains some suggested deployment scenarios, of
      course you can use a variety of technologies as alternatives to the ones
      in the diagram.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Pull style</title>

        <para>This pattern is what is used by the RuleAgent, by
        default.</para>

        <para>In this scenario, rules are pulled from the rule repository into
        the runtime system. The repository can be as simple as a file system,
        or a database. The trigger to pull the rules could be a timed task (to
        check for changes) or a request to the runtime system (perhaps via a
        JMX interface). This is possibly the more common scenario.</para>
      </section>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Deployment/DeploymentPatterns1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <section>
        <title>Push style</title>

        <para>In this scenario, the rule deployment process/repository
        "pushes" rules into the runtime system (either in source or binary
        form, as described above). This gives more control as to when the new
        rules take effect.</para>
      </section>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Deployment/DeploymentPatterns2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Web Services</title>

    <para>A possible deployment pattern for rules are to expose the rules as a
    web service. There a many ways to achieve this, but possibly the simplest
    way at present do achieve it is to use an interface-first process: Define
    the "facts" classes/templates that the rules will use in terms of XML
    Schema - and then use binding technologies to generate binding objects for
    the rules to actually operate against. A reverse possibility is to use a
    XSD/WSDL generator to generate XML bindings for classes that are hand
    built (which the rules work against). It is expected in a future version
    there will be an automated tool to expose rules as web services (and
    possibly use XSDs as facts for the rules to operate on).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Future considerations</title>

    <para>A future release of Drools will contain a rule repository (server)
    component that will directly support the above patterns, and more.</para>
  </section>
</section>
