<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
  xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Guided decision tables (web based)</title>

  <para>The guided decision table feature allows decision tables to be edited in place on the web. This works similar to
  the guided editor by introspecting what facts and fields are available to guide the creation of a decision table. Rule
  attributes, meta-data, conditions and actions can be defined in a tabular format thus facilitating rapid entry of
  large sets of related rules. Web-based decision table rules are compiled into DRL like all other rule assets.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Types of decision table</title>

    <para>There are broadly two different types of decision table, both of which are supported in Drools Workbench:-</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Extended Entry</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limited Entry</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Extended Entry</title>

      <para>An Extended Entry decision table is one for which the column definitions, or stubs, specify Pattern, Field
      and operator but not value. The values, or states, are themselves held in the body of the decision table. It is
      normal, but not essential, for the range of possible values to be restricted by limiting entry to values from a
      list. Drools Workbench supports use of Java enumerations, Drools Workbench enumerations or decision table "optional value lists" to
      restrict value entry.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Extended Entry Decision table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-complete1.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Limited Entry</title>

      <para>A Limited Entry decision table is one for which the column definitions specify value in addition to Pattern,
      Field and operator. The decision table states, held in the body of the table, are boolean where a positive value
      (a checked tick-box) has the effect of meaning the column should apply, or be matched. A negative value (a cleared
      tick-box) means the column does not apply.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Limited Entry Decision table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-complete2.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Main components\concepts</title>

    <para>The guided decision table is split into two main sections:-</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The upper section allows table columns to be defined representing rule attributes, meta-data, conditions
        and actions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The lower section contains the actual table itself; where individual rows define separate rules.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Main components</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-sections.png"
            format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section>
      <title>Navigation</title>

      <para>Cells can be selected in a variety of ways:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Firstly individual cells can be double-clicked and a pop-up editor corresponding to the underlying
          data-type will appear. Groups of cells in the same column can be selected by either clicking in the first and
          dragging the mouse pointer or clicking in the first and clicking the extent of the required range with the
          shift key pressed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Secondly the keyboard cursor keys can be used to navigate around the table. Pressing the enter key will
          pop-up the corresponding editor. Ranges can be selected by pressing the shift key whilst extending the range
          with the cursor keys.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Columns can be resized by hovering over the corresponding divider in the table header. The mouse cursor will
      change and then the column width dragged either narrower or wider.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cell merging</title>

      <para>The icon in the top left of the decision table toggles cell merging on and off. When cells are merged those
      in the same column with identical values are merged into a single cell. This simplifies changing the value of
      multiple cells that shared the same original value. When cells are merged they also gain an icon in the top-left
      of the cell that allows rows spanning the merged cell to be grouped.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Cell merging</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-merged.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cell grouping</title>

      <para>Cells that have been merged can be further collapsed into a single row. Clicking the [+\-] icon in the top
      left of a merged cell collapses the corresponding rows into a single entry. Cells in other columns spanning the
      collapsed rows that have identical values are shown unchanged. Cells in other columns spanning the collapsed rows
      that have different values are highlighted and the first value displayed.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Cell grouping</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-grouped.png"
              format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When the value of a grouped cell is altered all cells that have been collapsed also have their values
      updated.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operation of "otherwise"</title>

      <para>Condition columns defined with literal values that use either the equality (==) or inequality (!=) operators
      can take advantage of a special decision table cell value of "otherwise". This special value allows a rule to be
      defined that matches on all values not explicitly defined in all other rules defined in the table. This is best
      illustrated with an example:-</para>

      <programlisting>when
  Cheese( name not in ("Cheddar", "Edam", "Brie") )
  ...
then
  ...
end</programlisting>

      <programlisting>when
  Cheese( name in ("Cheddar", "Edam", "Brie") )
  ...
then
  ...
end</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Re-arranging columns</title>

      <para>Whole patterns and individual conditions can be re-arranged by dragging and dropping them in the
      configuration section of the screen. This allows constraints to be re-ordered to maximise performance of the
      resulting rules, by placing generalised constraints before more specific. Action columns can also be re-arranged
      by dragging and dropping them.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Re-arranging Condition patterns</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-rearranging-patterns.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Re-arranging columns</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-rearranging-columns.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Defining a web based decision table</title>

    <section>
      <title>Manual creation</title>

      <para>When a new empty decision table has been created you need to define columns for Facts, their constraints and
      corresponding actions.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Column configuration</title>

        <para>Expand the "Decision table" element and you will see three further sections for "Conditions", "Actions"
        and "Options". Expanding either the "Conditions" or "Actions" sections reveals the "New column" icon. This can
        be used to add new column definitions to the corresponding section. Existing columns can be removed by clicking
        the "-" icon beside each column name, or edited by clicking the "pencil" icon also beside each column name. The
        "Options" section functions slightly differently however the principle is the same: clicking the "Add
        Attribute/Metadata" icon allows columns for table attributes to be defined (such as "salience", "no-loop" etc)
        or metadata added.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Column configuration</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-config.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <section>
          <title>Utility columns</title>

          <para>All decision table contain two utility columns containing rule number and rule description.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Adding columns</title>

          <para>To add a column click on the "New column" icon.</para>

          <para>You are presented with the following column type selection popup.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Column type popup</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                  fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-type-popup.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>By default the column type popup only shows the following simple types:-</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Add a new Metadata\Attribute column</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Add a simple Condition</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set the value of a field</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set the value of a field on a new fact</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete an existing fact</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Clicking on "Include advanced options" adds the following additional "advanced" column types for more
          advanced use cases:-</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Add a Condition BRL fragment</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Execute a Work Item</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set the value of a field with a Work Item parameter</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set the value of a field on a new Fact with a Work Item parameter</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Add an Action BRL fragment</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Simple column types</title>

          <section>
            <title>Metadata</title>

            <para>Zero or more meta-data columns can be defined, each represents the normal meta-data annotation on DRL
            rules.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Attributes</title>

            <para>Zero or more attribute columns representing any of the DRL rule attributes (e.g. salience, timer,
            enabled etc) can be added. An additional pseudo attribute is provide in the guided decision table editor to
            "negate" a rule. Use of this attribute allows complete rules to be negated. For example the following simple
            rule can be negated as also shown.</para>

            <programlisting>when
  $c : Cheese( name == "Cheddar" )
then
  ...
end</programlisting>

            <programlisting>when
  not Cheese( name == "Cheddar" )
then
  ...
end</programlisting>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Simple Condition</title>

            <para>Conditions represent constraints on Fact Patterns defined in the left-hand side, or "when" portion, of
            a rule. To define a condition column you must first select or define a Fact Pattern bound to a model class.
            You can choose to negate the pattern. Once this has been completed you can define field constraints. If two
            or more columns are defined using the same fact pattern binding the field constraints become composite field
            constraints on the same pattern. If you define multiple bindings for a single model class each binding
            becomes a separate model class in the left-hand side of the rule.</para>

            <para>When you edit or create a new column, you will be given a choice of the type of constraint:-</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Literal : The value in the cell will be compared with the field using the operator.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Formula: The expression in the cell will be evaluated and then compared with the field.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Predicate : No field is needed, the expression will be evaluated to true or false.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure>
              <title>Simple Condition popup</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-condition-popup.png" format="PNG"
                  />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Set the value of a field</title>

            <para>An Action to set the value of a field on previously bound fact. You have the option to notify the Rule
            Engine of the modified values which could lead to other rules being re-activated.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Set the value of a field popup</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-setField-popup.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Set the value of a field on a new fact</title>

            <para>An Action to insert a new Fact into the Rule Engine Working Memory and set the a value of one of the
            new Facts' fields. You can choose to have the new Fact "logically inserted" meaning it will be automatically
            deleted should the conditions leading to the action being invoked cease to be true. Please refer to the
            Drools Expert documentation for details on Truth Maintenance and Logical insertions.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Set the value of a field on a new fact popup</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-insertField-popup.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Delete an existing fact</title>

            <para>An Action to delete a bound Fact.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Delete an existing fact popup</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-deleteFact-popup.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Advanced column types</title>

          <section>
            <title>Condition BRL fragments</title>

            <para>A construct that allows a BRL fragment to be used in the left-hand side of a rule. A BRL fragment is
            authored using the Guided Rule Editor and hence all features available in that editor can be used to define
            a decision table column; such as "from", "collect" and "accumulate" etc. When using the embedded Guided Rule
            Editor field values defined as "Template Keys" will form columns in the decision table. Facts and Fact's
            fields bound in the BRL fragment can be referenced by the simpler column types and vice-versa.</para>

            <para>In the following example two Template Keys have been defined and hence two columns appear in the
            decision table.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Defining a Condition with BRL</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-condition-brl1-popup.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <figure>
              <title>The resulting decision table</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-condition-brl2-popup.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Execute a Work Item</title>

            <para>An Action invoking a jBPM Work Item Handler setting it's input parameters to bound Facts\Facts fields
            values.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Set the value of a field with a Work Item parameter</title>

            <para>An Action setting the value of a Fact's field to that of a jBPM Work Item Handlers result
            parameter.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Set the value of a field on a new Fact with a Work Item parameter</title>

            <para>An Action setting the value of a new Fact's field to that of a jBOM Work Item Handlers result
            parameter.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Action BRL fragment</title>

            <para>A construct that allows a BRL fragment to be used in the right-hand side of a rule. A BRL fragment is
            authored using the Guided Rule Editor and hence all features available in that editor can be used to define
            a decision table column. When using the embedded Guided Rule Editor field values defined as "Template Keys"
            will form columns in the decision table. Facts bound in the BRL fragment can be referenced by the simpler
            column types and vice-versa.</para>

            <para>In the following example two Template Keys have been defined and hence two columns appear in the
            decision table.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Defining an Action with BRL</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-action-brl1-popup.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <figure>
              <title>The resulting decision table</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                    fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-column-action-brl2-popup.png"
                    format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using a Wizard</title>

      <para>A Wizard can also be used to assist with defining the decision table columns.</para>

      <para>The wizard can be chosen when first electing to create a new rule. The wizard provides a number of pages to
      define the table:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Summary</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add Fact Patterns</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add Constraints</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add Actions to update facts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Add Actions to insert facts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Columns to expand</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>Selecting the wizard</title>

        <para>The "New Wizard" dialog shows a "Use wizard" checkbox when the asset type is set to "Decision Table (Web -
        guided editor)".</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Selecting the wizard</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard1.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Summary page</title>

        <para>the summary page shows a few basic details about the decision table and allows the asset name to be
        changed.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Summary page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard2.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Add Fact Patterns page</title>

        <para>This page allows Fact types to be defined that will form the "When" columns of the rules. Fact types that
        are available in your model will be shown in the left-hand listbox. Select a Fact type and use the "&gt;&gt;"
        button to add it to your list of chosen facts on the right-hand listbox. Removal is a similar process: the Fact
        that is no longer required can be selected in the right-hand listbox and the "&lt;&lt;" button used to remove
        it. All Fact types need to be bound to a variable. Incomplete Fact types will be highlighted and a warning
        message displayed. You will be unable to finish your definition until all warnings have been resolved.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Add Fact Patterns page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard3a.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <title>Example of an incomplete Fact definition</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard3b.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Add Constraints page</title>

        <para>This page allows field constraints on the Fact types you have chosen to use in the decision table to be
        defined. Fact types chosen on the previous Wizard page are listed in the right-hand listbox. Selecting a Fact
        type by clicking on it will result in a list of available fields being shown in the middle listbox together with
        an option to create a predicate that do not require a specific field. Fields can be added to the pattern's
        constraints by clicking on the field and then the "&gt;&gt;" button. Fields can be removed from the pattern
        definition by clicking on the Condition in the right-hand listbox and then the "&lt;&lt;" button. All fields
        need to have a column header and operator. Incomplete fields will be highlighted and a warning message
        displayed. You will be unable to finish your definition until all warnings have been resolved.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Add Constraints page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard4.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Add Actions to update facts page</title>

        <para>Fact types that have been defined can be updated in the consequence, or action, part of a rule. This page
        allows such actions to be defined. Fact types added to the decision table definition are listed in the left-hand
        listbox. Selecting a Fact type by clicking on it will result in a list of available fields being shown in the
        middle listbox. Fields that need to be updated by the rule can be added by selecting an available field and
        pressing the "&gt;&gt;" button. Fields can be removed similarly by clicking on a chosen field and then the
        "&lt;&lt;" button. All actions require a column header. Any incomplete actions will be highlighted and a warning
        message displayed. You will be unable to finish your definition until all warnings have been resolved.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Add Actions to update facts page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard5.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Add Actions to insert facts page</title>

        <para>Actions can also be defined to insert new Facts into the Rule Engine. A list of Fact types available in
        your model are listed in the left-hand listbox. Select those you wish to include in your decision table
        definition by clicking on them and pressing the "&gt;&gt;" button between the left most listbox and that titled
        "Chosen patterns". Removal is a similar process whereby a chosen pattern can be selected and removed by pressing
        the "&lt;&lt;" button. Selection of a chosen pattern presents the user with a list of available fields. Fields
        that need to have values set by the action can be added by selecting them and pressing the "&gt;&gt;" button
        between the "Available fields" and "Chosen fields" listbox. Removal is a similar process as already described.
        New Facts need to be bound to a variable and have a column heading specified. Incomplete Facts and\or fields
        will be highlighted and a warning message displayed. You will be unable to finish your definition until all
        warnings have been resolved.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Add Actions to insert facts page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard6.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Columns to expand page</title>

        <para>This page controls how the decision table, based upon Conditions defined on the prior pages, will be
        created. Condition columns defined with an optional list of permitted values can be used to create rows in the
        decision table. Where a number of Condition columns have been defined with lists of permitted values the
        resulting table will contain a row for every combination of values; i.e. the decision table will be in expanded
        form. By default all Condition columns defined with value lists will be included in the expansion however you
        are able to select a sub-set of columns if so required. This can be accomplished by unticking the "Fully expand"
        checkbox and adding columns to the right-hand listbox. If no expansion is required untick the "Fully expand"
        checkbox and ensure zero columns are added to the right-hand listbox.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Columns to expand page</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard7a.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <title>Example of a Condition column with optional values defined</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard7b.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <title>Example of a decision table generated with expanded columns</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-wizard7c.png"
                format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rule definition</title>

    <para>This section allows individual rules to be defined using the columns defined earlier.</para>

    <para>Rows can be appended to the end of the table by selecting the "Add Row" button. Rows can also be inserted by
    clicking the "+" icon beside an existing row. The "-" icon can be used to delete rows.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Rule definition</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/dtable-body.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Audit Log</title>

    <para>An audit log has been added to the web-guided Decision Table editor to track additions, deletions and
    modifications.</para>

    <para>By default the audit log is not configured to record any events, however, users can easily select the events
    in which they are interested.</para>

    <para>The audit log is persisted whenever the asset is checked in.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>An empty audit log</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/audit-log1.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Once the capture of events has been enabled all susbsequent operations are recorded. Users are able to perform
    the following:-</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Record an explanatory note beside each event.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Delete an event from the log. Event details remain in the underlying repository.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Example of audit events</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/AuthoringAssets/audit-log2.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</section>
