<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="ch.Drools_Eclipse_IDE_Features"
         version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="./">

  <title id="ch.Drools_Eclipse_IDE_Features,title">Drools Eclipse IDE Features</title>

  <para>The Drools plugin for the Eclipse IDE provides a few additional features that
  might be interesting for developers.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Drools Runtimes</title>
 
    <para>A Drools runtime is a collection of jar files that represent
    one specific release of the Drools project jars. To create a runtime, you must 
    point the IDE to the release of your choice.  If you want to create a new runtime
    based on the latest Drools project jars included in the plugin itself, you can also
    easily do that.  You are required to specify a default Drools runtime for your
    Eclipse workspace, but each individual project can override the default and select
    the appropriate runtime for that project specifically.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Defining a Drools Runtime</title>

      <para>To define one or more Drools runtimes using the Eclipse preferences
      view you open up your Preferences, by selecting the "Preferences" menu item
      in the menu "Window".  A "Preferences" dialog should show all your settings. On the
      left side of this dialog, under the Drools category, select "Installed Drools
      runtimes".  The panel on the right should then show the currently defined Drools
      runtimes.  If you have not yet defined any runtimes, it should look like
      the figure below.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>To define a new Drools runtime, click on the add button.  A dialog such
      as the one shown below should pop up, asking for the name of your runtime and
      the location on your file system where it can be found.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes-add.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>In general, you have two options:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>If you simply want to use the default jar files as included
        in the Drools Eclipse plugin, you can create a new Drools runtime automatically
        by clicking the "Create a new Drools 5 runtime ..." button.  A file browser
        will show up, asking you to select the folder on your file system where you
        want this runtime to be created.  The plugin will then automatically copy
        all required dependencies to
        the specified folder.  After selecting this folder, the dialog should look like
        the figure shown below.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>If you want to use one specific release of the Drools project, you should
        create a folder on your file system that contains all the necessary Drools libraries
        and dependencies.  Instead of creating a new Drools runtime as explained above, give
        your runtime a name and select the location of this folder containing all the required
        jars.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes-add2.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>After clicking the OK button, the runtime should show up in your table of installed
      Drools runtimes, as shown below.  Click on checkbox in front of the newly created runtime 
      to make it the default Drools runtime.  The default Drools runtime will be used as the
      runtime of all your Drools project that have not selected a project-specific runtime.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes2.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can add as many Drools runtimes as you need.  For example, the screenshot below
      shows a configuration where three runtimes have been defined: a Drools 4.0.7 runtime, a
      Drools 5.0.0 runtime and a Drools 5.0.0.SNAPSHOT runtime.  The Drools 5.0.0 runtime is
      selected as the default one.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes3.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Note that you will need to restart Eclipse if you changed the default runtime and
      you want to make sure that all the projects that are using the default runtime update
      their classpath accordingly.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting a runtime for your Drools project</title>

      <para>Whenever you create a Drools project (using the New Drools Project wizard or by
      converting an existing Java project to a Drools project using the action 
      "Convert to Drools Project" that is shown when you are in the Drools perspective
      and you right-click an existing Java project), the plugin will automatically add all
      the required jars to the classpath of your project.</para>

      <para>When creating a new Drools project, the plugin will automatically use the default
      Drools runtime for that project, unless you specify a project-specific one.  You can do
      this in the final step of the New Drools Project wizard, as shown below, by deselecting
      the "Use default Drools runtime" checkbox and selecting the appropriate runtime in the
      drop-down box.  If you click the "Configure workspace settings ..." link, the workspace
      preferences showing the currently installed Drools runtimes will be opened, so you can
      add new runtimes there.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes-newproject.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can change the runtime of a Drools project at any time by opening the project
      properties and selecting the Drools category, as shown below.  Mark the
      "Enable project specific settings" checkbox and select
      the appropriate runtime from the drop-down box.  If you click the "Configure workspace
      settings ..." link, the workspace preferences showing the currently installed Drools
      runtimes will be opened, so you can add new runtimes there.  If you deselect the "Enable
      project specific settings" checkbox, it will use the default runtime as defined in your
      global preferences.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/drools-runtimes-project.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Process Skins</title>

    <para>The concept of <emphasis>process skins</emphasis> provides a way of
    control the visualization of the different nodes of a processd. You may
    change the visualization of the various node types to the way you prefer
    by implementing your own <code>SkinProvider</code>.</para>

    <para>BPMN is a popular language used by business users for modeling business
    processes. BPMN defines terminology, different types of nodes, how these should
    be visualized, etc. People who are familiar with BPMN might find it easier to
    implement an executable process (possibly based on a BPMN process diagram) using
    a similar visualization. We have therefore created a BPMN skin that maps the Drools
    Flow concepts to the equivalent BPMN visualization.</para>

    <para>As an example, the following figure shows a process using some of
    the different types of nodes in the RuleFlow language using the default
    skin.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/RuleFlow.png" format="PNG" role="" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>You may now change the preferred process skin in the Drools Preferences dialog:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/preferences.png" format="PNG" role="" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>After reopening the editor, the same process is displayed using the BPMN skin.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata align="center" width="100%"
                   fileref="images/Chapter-Eclipse/BPMN.png" format="PNG" role="" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

  </section>

</chapter>
