<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <title>Drools Flow API</title>

  <section>
    <title>Knowledge Base</title>

    <para>Our knowledge-based API allows you to first create a Knowledge Base
    that contains all the necessary knowledge.  This includes all the
    relevant process definitions and other knowledge types like rules.  The
    following code snippet shows how to create a Knowledge Base consisting of only
    one process definition, using a Knowledge Builder to add a resource, checking
    for errors and, finally, creating the Knowledge Base.</para>

<programlisting>
KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();
kbuilder.add(ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource("ruleflow.rf"), ResourceType.DRF);
KnowledgeBuilderErrors errors = kbuilder.getErrors();
if (errors.size() > 0) {
  for (KnowledgeBuilderError error: errors) {
    System.err.println(error);
  }
  throw new IllegalArgumentException("Could not parse knowledge.");
}
KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
kbase.addKnowledgePackages(kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages());
</programlisting>

    <para>Note that the knowledge-based API allows users to add different types of
    resources, such as rules and processes, in almost identical ways into the same
    Knowledge Base.  This enables a user who knows how to use Drools Flow to start
    using Drools Fusion almost instantaneously, and even to integrate these
    different types of Knowledge.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Session</title>

    <para>Next, you should create a session to interact with the engine.  Again, the
    API is knowledge-based, supporting different types of Knowledge, with a specific
    extension for each Knowledge Type.  The following code snippet shows how easy it
    is to create a session based on the earlier created Knowledge Base, and to start a
    process.</para>

<programlisting>
StatefulKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatefulKnowledgeSession();
ProcessInstance processInstance = ksession.startProcess("com.sample.ruleflow");
</programlisting>

    <para>The <code>ProcessRuntime</code> interface defines all the session methods
    for interacting with processes, as shown below.  Consult the Javadocs to get
    a detailed explanation for each of the methods.</para>

<programlisting>
ProcessInstance startProcess(String processId);
ProcessInstance startProcess(String processId, Map&lt;String, Object&gt; parameters);
void signalEvent(String type, Object event);
Collection&lt;ProcessInstance&gt; getProcessInstances();
ProcessInstance getProcessInstance(long id);
WorkItemManager getWorkItemManager();
</programlisting>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Events</title>

    <para>Both the Stateful and Stateless Knowledge Session provide methods for
    registering and removing listeners. <code>ProcessEventListener</code> objects
    can be used to listen to process-related events, like starting or completing
    a process, and entering and leaving a node.  Below, the different methods of a
    <code>ProcessEventListener</code> are shown.  An event object provides access
    to related information, like the process instance and node instance linked to
    the event.</para>

<programlisting>
public interface ProcessEventListener {

  void beforeProcessStarted( ProcessStartedEvent event );
  void afterProcessStarted( ProcessStartedEvent event );
  void beforeProcessCompleted( ProcessCompletedEvent event );
  void afterProcessCompleted( ProcessCompletedEvent event );
  void beforeNodeTriggered( ProcessNodeTriggeredEvent event );
  void afterNodeTriggered( ProcessNodeTriggeredEvent event );
  void beforeNodeLeft( ProcessNodeLeftEvent event );
  void afterNodeLeft( ProcessNodeLeftEvent event );

}</programlisting>

    <para>An audit log can be created based on the information provided by these process
    listeners.  We provide various default logger implementations:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>Console logger: This logger writes out all the events to the console.</listitem>

      <listitem>File logger: This logger writes out all the events to a file using an
      XML representation.  This log file might then be used in the IDE to generate
      a tree-based visualization of the events that occurred during execution.</listitem>

      <listitem>Threaded file logger: Because a file logger writes the events to disk only
      when closing the logger or when the number of events in the logger reaches a predefined
      level, it cannot be used when debugging processes at runtime.  A threaded file logger
      writes the events to a file after a specified time interval, making it possible to use
      the logger to visualize the progress in realtime, while debugging processes.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>The <code>KnowledgeRuntimeLoggerFactory</code> let you add a logger to
    your session, as shown below.  When creating a console logger, the Knowledge Session
    for which the logger needs to be created must be passed as an argument. The file
    logger also requires the name of the log file to be created, and the threaded file
    logger requires the interval (in milliseconds) after which the events should be saved.</para>

<programlisting>
KnowledgeRuntimeLogger logger =
    KnowledgeRuntimeLoggerFactory.newFileLogger( ksession, "test" );
// add invocations to the process engine here,
// e.g. ksession.startProcess(processId);
...
logger.close();</programlisting>

    <para>The log file can be opened in Eclipse, using the Audit View in the Drools
    Eclipse plugin, where the events are visualized as a tree. Events that occur
    between the before and after event are shown as children of that event.  The
    following screenshot shows a simple example, where a process is started,
    resulting in the activation of the Start node, an Action node and an End node,
    after which the process was completed. </para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                   fileref="images/Chapter-API/AuditView.png"/>
       </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

  </section>

</chapter>
