<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="./" xml:id="chap-dashbuilder-import-export"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <title>Import &amp; Export</title>


  <para>Dashbuilder provides import and export functionality in order to move application assets between environments.</para>
  <para>These assets can be:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Workspaces</emphasis>: By exporting and importing workspaces you can move your set of pages with a given look and feel between installations.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Key performance indicators and data providers:</emphasis>: By exporting and importing KPIs you can move your indicators and its data providers between installations.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Data sources</emphasis>: By exporting and importing data sources you can move your external connection configurations between installations.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In general, asset <emphasis role="bold">exportation</emphasis> must be done using the <emphasis>Web User Interface</emphasis>. There exist a panel for exporting each type of asset.</para>
  
  <para>On the other hand, asset <emphasis role="bold">importation</emphasis> can be done in two ways:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Using the <emphasis>Web User Interface</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>There exist panels for importing each type of asset.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Using the <emphasis>Deployment Scanner</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>It allows to place your exported assets in a given folder inside the web application. Once application is starting, it scans the deployment folder and import the assets found.</para>
      <para>Using the <emphasis>Deployment Scanner</emphasis> allows for the automatic deployment of assets on application start up time and does not requires the user intervention either.</para>
      <para>It's important to note that assets are imported only at deploy time, not during application runtime.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>The following sections describe how to perform import and export for each kind of asset.</para>
  
  <xi:include href="ImportExport/Workspaces.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="ImportExport/KPI.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="ImportExport/DataSources.xml"/>

</chapter>
