<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="jBPMExamplesHR"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
       xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
       xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
       <title>Human Resources Example</title>

       <para>Let’s imagine for a second that you work for a Software company that works with several
              projects and from time to time the company wants to hire new developers. So, which
              employees, Departments and Systems are required to Hire a new Developer in your
              company? Trying to answering these questions will help you to define your business
              process. The following figure, represents how does this process works for Acme Inc. We
              can clearly see that three Departments are involved: Human Resources, IT and
              Accounting teams are involved. Inside our company we have Katy from the Human
              Resources Team, Jack on the IT team and John from the Accounting team involved. Notice
              that there are other people inside each team, but we will be using Katy, Jack and John
              to demonstrate how to execute the business process. </para>
       <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                            fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-high-level.png" width="700"/>
              </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
       <para> Notice that there are 6 activities defined inside this business process, 4 of them are
              User Tasks, which means that will be handled by people. The other two are Service
              Tasks, which means an interaction with another system will be required. </para>
       <para> The process diagram is self explanatory, but just in case and to avoid confusions this
              is what is supposed to happen for each instance of the process that is started a
              particular candidate: </para>

       <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>
                     The Human Resources Team perform the initial interview to the candidate to
                     see if he/she fits the profile that the company is looking for.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                     The IT Department perform a technical interview to evaluate the candidate
                     skills and experience.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                     Based on output of the Human Resources and IT teams, the accounting team
                     create a Job Proposal which includes the yearly salary for the candidate. The
                     proposal is created based on the output of both of the interviews (Human
                     Resources and Technical).</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                     As soon as the proposal has being created it is automatically sent to the
                     candidate via email.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                     If the candidate accept the proposal, a new meeting is created with someone
                     from the Human Resource team to sign the contract.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem><para>
                     If everything goes well, as soon as the process is notified that the
                     candidate was hired, the system will automatically post a tweet about the new
                     Hire using the twitter service connector.</para>
              </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>

       <para> As you can see Jack, John and Katy will be performing the tasks for this example
              instance of the business process, but any person inside the company that have those
              Roles will be able to claim and interact with those tasks. </para>

       <section>
              <title>The KIE Project: human-resources</title>
              <para> Let's take a look at the Project content in the Authoring Perspective: </para>
              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-project-editor.png"
                                   width="700"/>
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <para>As you can see it contains the <emphasis role="bold">hiring.bpmn2</emphasis>
                     process and a set of forms for each human task. You can explore these knowledge
                     assets by clicking on them. You will notice that different editors will open
                     for different types of assets. If you click on the Business Process file you
                     will be able to edit the process definition using the Process Designer:</para>
              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-hiring-bpmn.png"
                                   width="700"/>
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <para>Feel free to inspect the forms as well. Notice that the Form Modeller will be
                     opened and there you can edit the forms to fit your requirements.</para>

              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-hr-interview-form.png"
                                   width="700" />
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
       </section>
       <section>
              <title>Building the Human Resources Example</title>
              <para>In order to build the Project so it gets available in the Process Definitions
                     List you need to go to the Authoring Perspective and open the Project Editor
                     panel: </para>
              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-go-to-project-editor.png"
                                   width="400" />
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>

              <para>Once you open the Project Editor, you will see on the top right corner of the
                     panel the button called Build &amp; Deploy. This button will allow you to
                     create a new JAR artifact that will be deployed to the Runtime environment as a
                     new Deployment Unit. </para>
              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-build-and-deploy.png"
                                   width="700" />
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <para>Once you get the visual notification that the project was built and deployed
                     successfully you can go to the Deployments screen to verify that your artifact
                     is there. In order to do that go to the top level menu called Deploy ->
                     Deployments</para>
              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-go-to-deployments.png"
                                   width="200" />
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <para>In the Deployments screen you will find all the deployed units. By default when
                     you Build &amp; Deploy a project from the Project Editor, it will be
                     automatically deployed using the default configurations. That is Singleton
                     Strategy, the default KIE Base and the default KIE Session will be used. </para>
              <para>If you want a more advanced deployment, that is selecting a different strategy
                     or using non defaults KIE Base or KIE Session you will be able to undeploy and
                     re-deploy your artifacts using their GAV and selecting non default
                     options.</para>

              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-deployment-screen.png"
                                   width="700"/>
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>

              <para> Once your artifact that contains the process definition is deployed, the
                     Process Definition will be available under Process Management -> Process
                     Definitions. </para>

       </section>
       <section>
              <title>Create a new Process Instance</title>
              <para>In order to create new Process Instances you need to go to Process Management ->
                     Process Definitions.</para>

              <para>Here you will find all the available process definitions in the runtime
                     environment. If you want to add new process definitions look at the previous
                     sections where it is explained how to build and deploy KIE Projects.</para>

              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-process-definitions.png"
                                   width="700"/>
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <para>You can start process instances using any of the two options highlated in the
                     previous screen.</para>
              <para>In order to create a new process instance most of the processes will require you
                     to fill in some information and for that a form will be displayed. For this
                     specific use case the name of the candidate that we are interviewing is
                     required:</para>

              <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role=""
                                   fileref="images/Examples/human-resources-new-instance-form.png"
                                   width="400" />
                     </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
              <para> If we hit the big Start button, the new process instance will be created and
                     the first task of the process will be create for the Human Resources Team.
                     Depending on the assigned roles of the user that you are using to create the
                     process instance you will be able to see the created task or not. In order to
                     see the first task of the process we will need to logout tot he application and
                     log in as someone from the Human Resources team. </para>
              <para>After starting the process you can go to the Task -> Tasks section to interact
                     with the created human tasks. Notice that in order to see the tasks in the task
                     lists you will need to belong to some specific user Groups. For example the HR
                     Interview task will be visitable for any member of the HR group, the Tech
                     Interview will be visible by any member of the IT Group. </para>
       </section>

</section>
