<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Why use a Rule Engine?</title>

  <para>Some frequently asked questions:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>When should you use a rule engine?</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>What advantage does a rule engine have over hand coded
      "if...then" approaches?</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Why should you use a rule engine instead of a scripting framework,
      like <indexterm>
          <primary>BeanShell</primary>
        </indexterm> BeanShell?</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>We will attempt to address these questions below.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Advantages of a Rule Engine</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Declarative Programming</para>

        <para>Rule engines allow you to say "What to do", not "How to do
        it".</para>

        <para>The key advantage of this point is that using rules can make it
        easy to express solutions to difficult problems and consequently have
        those solutions verified. Rules are much easier to read than
        code.</para>

        <para>Rule systems are capable of solving very, very hard problems,
        providing an explanation of how the solution was arrived at and why
        each "decision" along the way was made (not so easy with other of AI
        systems like neural networks or the human brain - I have no idea why I
        scratched the side of the car).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Logic and Data Separation</para>

        <para>Your data is in your domain objects, the logic is in the rules.
        This is fundamentally breaking the OO coupling of data and logic,
        which can be an advantage or a disadvantage depending on your point of
        view. The upshot is that the logic can be much easier to maintain as
        there are changes in the future, as the logic is all laid out in
        rules. This can be especially true if the logic is cross-domain or
        multi-domain logic. Instead of the logic being spread across many
        domain objects or controllers, it can all be organized in one or more
        very distinct rules files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Speed and Scalability</para>

        <para>The Rete algorithm,the Leaps algorithm, and their descendants such as
        Drools' ReteOO, provide very efficient ways of matching
        rule patterns to your domain object data. These are especially
        efficient when you have datasets that change in small portions as the
        rule engine can remember past matches. These algorithms are battle
        proven.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Centralization of Knowledge</para>

        <para>By using rules, you create a repository of knowledge (a
        knowledge base) which is executable. This means it's a single point of
        truth, for business policy, for instance. Ideally rules are so
        readable that they can also serve as documentation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tool Integration</para>

        <para>Tools such as Eclipse (and in future, Web based user interfaces)
        provide
        ways to edit and manage rules and get immediate feedback, validation
        and content assistance. Auditing and debugging tools are also
        available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explanation Facility</para>

        <para>Rule systems effectively provide an "explanation facility" by
        being able to log the decisions made by the rule engine along with why
        the decisions were made.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Understandable Rules</para>

        <para>By creating object models and, optionally, Domain Specific
        Languages that model your problem domain you can set yourself up to
        write rules that are very close to natural language. They lend
        themselves to logic that is understandable to, possibly nontechnical,
        domain experts as they are expressed in their language, with all the
        program plumbing, the technical know-how being hidden
        away in the usual code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>When should you use a Rule Engine?</title>

    <para>The shortest answer to this is "when there is no satisfactory
    traditional programming approach to solve the problem.". Given that short
    answer, some more explanation is required. The reason why there is no
    "traditional" approach is possibly one of the following: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The problem is just too fiddle for traditional code.</para>

          <para>The problem may not be complex, but you can't see a
          non-fragile way of building a solution for it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The problem is beyond any obvious algorithmic
          solution.</para>

          <para>It is a complex problem to solve, there are no obvious
          traditional solutions, or basically the problem isn't fully
          understood.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The logic changes often</para>

          <para>The logic itself may even be simple but
          the rules change quite often. In many organizations software
          releases are few and far between and pluggable rules can help provide the
          "agility" that is needed and expected in a reasonably safe
          way.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Domain experts (or business analysts) are readily available,
          but are nontechnical.</para>

          <para>Domain experts often possess a wealth of knowledge about business
          rules and processes. They typically are nontechnical, but can be
          very logical. Rules can allow them to express the logic in their own
          terms. Of course, they still have to think critically and be capable
          of logical thinking. Many people in nontechnical positions do
          not have training in formal logic, so be careful and work with them,
          as by codifying business knowledge in rules, you will often expose
          holes in the way the business rules and processes are currently
          understood.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>If rules are a new technology for your project teams, the overhead
    in getting going must be factored in. It is not a trivial technology, but
    this document tries to make it easier to understand.</para>

    <para>Typically in a modern OO application you would use a rule engine to
    contain key parts of your business logic, 
    <emphasis>especially the really messy parts</emphasis>. This is
    an inversion of the OO concept of encapsulating all the logic inside your
    objects. This is not to say that you throw out OO practices, on the
    contrary in any real world application, business logic is just one part of
    the application. If you ever notice lots of conditional statements
    such as "if" and "switch", an
    overabundance of strategy patterns and other messy logic in your code
    that just doesn't feel right: that would be a place for rules.
    If there is some such logic and you keep coming back to fix it, either
    because you got it wrong, or the logic or your understanding changes: think
    about using rules. If you are faced with tough problems for which there are
    no algorithms or patterns: consider using rules.</para>

    <para>Rules could be used embedded in your application or perhaps as a
    service. Often a rule engine works best as "stateful" component, being
    an integral part of an application. However, there have been
    successful cases of creating reusable rule services which are
    stateless.</para>

    <para>For your organization it is important to decide about the process you
    will use for updating rules in systems that are in production. The options
    are many, but different organizations have different requirements.
    Frequently, rules maintenance is out of the control of the application
    vendors or project developers.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>When not to use a Rule Engine</title>

    <para>To quote a Drools mailing list regular: <blockquote><attribution>Dave Hamu</attribution>
<para>It seems to me
    that in the excitement of working with rules engines, that people forget
    that a rules engine is only one piece of a complex application or
    solution. Rules engines are not really intended to handle workflow or
    process executions nor are workflow engines or process management tools
    designed to do rules. Use the right tool for the job. Sure, a pair of
    pliers can be used as a hammering tool in a pinch, but that's not what
    it's designed for.</para>
</blockquote></para>

    <para>As rule engines are dynamic (dynamic in the sense that the rules can
    be stored and managed and updated as data), they are often looked at as a
    solution to the problem of deploying software. (Most IT departments seem to
    exist for the purpose of preventing software being rolled out.) If this is
    the reason you wish to use a rule engine, be aware that rule engines work
    best when you are able to write declarative rules. As an alternative, you
    can consider data-driven designs (lookup tables), or script processing
    engines where the scripts are managed in a database and are able to be
    updated on the fly.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Scripting or Process Engines</title>

    <para>Hopefully the preceding sections have explained when you may want to
    use a rule engine.</para>

    <para>Alternatives are script-based engines that provide the drive
    for "changes on the fly", and there are many such solutions.</para>

    <para>Alternatively Process Engines (also capable of workflow) such as
    jBPM allow you to graphically (or programmatically) describe steps in a
    process. Those steps can also involve decision points which are in
    themselves a simple rule. Process engines and rules often can work nicely
    together, so they are not mutually exclusive.</para>

    <para>One key point to note with rule engines is that some rule engines
    are really scripting engines. The downside of scripting engines is that
    you are tightly coupling your application to the scripts. If they are
    rules, you are effectively calling rules directly and this may cause more
    difficulty in future maintenance, as they tend to grow in complexity over
    time. The upside of scripting engines is that they can be easier to
    implement initially, producing results quickly, and are conceptually
    simpler for imperative programmers.</para>

    <para>Many people have also implemented data-driven systems successfully
    in the past (where there are control tables that store meta-data that
    changes your applications behavior) - these can work well when the
    control can remain very limited. However, they can quickly grow out of
    control if extended too much (such that only the original creators can
    change the applications behavior) or they cause the application to
    stagnate as they are too inflexible.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Strong and Loose Coupling</title>

    <para>No doubt you have heard terms like "tight coupling" and "loose
    coupling" in systems design. Generally people assert that "loose" or
    "weak" coupling is preferable in design terms, due to the added
    flexibility it affords. Similarly, you can have "strongly coupled" and
    "weakly coupled" rules. Strongly coupled in this sense means that one rule
    "firing" will clearly result in another rule firing, and so on; in other
    words,
    there is a clear (probably obvious) chain of logic. If your rules are all
    strongly coupled, the chances are that the will turn out to be inflexible,
    and, more significantly, that a rule engine is an overkill. A clear chain
    can be hard coded, or implemented using a Decision Tree. This is not to
    say that strong
    coupling is inherently bad, but it is a point to keep in mind when
    considering a rule engine and the way you capture the rules. "Loosely"
    coupled rules should result in a system that allows rules to be changed,
    removed and added without requiring changes to other, unrelated
    rules.</para>
  </section>
</section>
