<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Artificial Intelligence</title>

  <section>
    <title>A Little History</title>

    <para>Over the last few decades <firstterm>artificial
    intelligence</firstterm> (AI) became an unpopular term, with the well know
    <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI_winter">"AI
    Winter"</link>. There were large boasts from scientists and engineers
    looking for funding, that never lived up to expectations along with many
    failed projects. <link
    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking_Machines_Corporation">Thinking
    Machines Corporation</link> and the <link
    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fifth-generation_computer">5th
    Generation Computer</link> (5GP) project probably exemplify best the
    problems at the time.</para>

    <para>Thinking Machines Corporation was one of the leading AI firms in
    1990, it had sales of nearly $65 million. Here is quote from it's
    brochure:</para>

    <para><quote>Some day we will build a thinking machine. It will be a truly
    intelligent machine. One that can see and hear and speak. A machine that
    will be proud of us.</quote></para>

    <para>Yet 5 years later it filed for Chapter 11. inc.com has a fascinating
    article titled <link
    xlink:href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/19950915/2622.html">"The Rise and
    Fall of Thinking Machines"</link>. The article covers the growth of the
    industry and how a cosy relationship with Thinking Machines and <link
    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DARPA">DARPA</link> over heated
    the market, to the point of collapse. It explains how and why commerce
    moved away from AI and towards more practical number crunching super
    computers.</para>

    <para>The 5th Generation Computer project was a 400mill USD project in
    Japan to build a next generation computer. Valves was first, transistors
    was second, integrated circuits was third and finally microprocessors was
    fourth. This project spurred an "arms" race with the UK and USA, that
    caused much of the AI bubble. The 5GP would provide massive multi-cpu
    parallel processing hardware along with powerful knowledge representation
    and reasoning software via <firstterm>Prolog</firstterm>; a type of
    <firstterm> expert system</firstterm>. By 1992 the project was considered
    a failure and cancelled. It was the largest and most visible commercial
    venture for Prolog, and many of the failures are pinned on the problems
    trying to run a logic based programming language concurrently on multi cpu
    hardware with effective results. Some believe that the failure of the 5GP
    project tainted Prolog and resigned it academia, see <link
    xlink:href="http://www.dvorak.org/blog/whatever-happened-to-prolog/">"Whatever
    Happened to Prolog"</link> by John C. Dvorak.</para>

    <para>However while research funding dried up and the term AI became less
    used, many green shoots where planted and continued more quietly under
    discipline specific names: <firstterm>cognitive systems</firstterm>,
    <firstterm>machine learning</firstterm>, <firstterm>intelligent
    systems</firstterm>,<firstterm> knowledge representation and
    reasoning</firstterm>. Offshoots of these then made their way into
    commercial systems, such as expert systems in the <firstterm>Business
    Rules Management System</firstterm> (BRMS) market.</para>

    <para><firstterm>Imperative</firstterm>, system based languages, languages
    such as C, C++, Java and .Net have dominated the last 20 years. Enabled by
    the practicality of the languages and ability to run with good performance
    on commodity hardware. However many believe there is renaissance
    undergoing in the field of AI, spurred by advances in hardware
    capabilities and AI research. In 2005 Heather Havenstein authored <link
    xlink:href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/99691/Spring_comes_to_AI_winter">"Spring
    comes to AI winter"</link> which outlines a case for this resurgence,
    which she refers to as a <firstterm>spring</firstterm>. Norvig and Russel
    dedicate several pages to what factors allowed the industry to over come
    it's problems and the research that came about as a result:</para>

    <para><quote>Recent years have seen a revolution in both the content and
    the methodology of work in artificial intelligence. It is now more common
    to build on existing theories than to propose brand-new ones, to base
    claims on rigorous theorems or hard experimental evidence rather than on
    intuition, and to show relevance to real-world applications rather than
    toy examples.</quote> (Artificial Intelligence : A Modern
    Approach.)</para>

    <para><firstterm>Computer vision</firstterm>, <firstterm>neural
    networks</firstterm>, <firstterm>machine learning</firstterm> and
    <firstterm>knowledge representation and reasoning</firstterm> (KRR) have
    made great strides in become practical in commercial environments. For
    example vision based systems can now fully map out and navigate their
    environments with strong recognition skills, as a result we now have self
    driving cars about to enter the commercial market.
    <firstterm>Ontological</firstterm> research, based around description
    logic, has provided very rich semantics to represent our world. Algorithms
    such as the tableaux algorithm have made it possible to effectively use
    those rich semantics in large complex ontologies. Early KRR systems, like
    Prolog in 5GP, were dogged by the limited semantic capabilities and memory
    restrictions on the size of those ontologies.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Knowledge Representation and Reasoning</title>

    <para>In A Little History talks about AI as a broader subject and touches
    on Knowledge Representation and Reasoning (KRR) and also Expert Systems,
    I'll come back to Expert Systems later.</para>

    <para>KRR is about how we represent our knowledge in symbolic form, i.e.
    how we describe something. Reasoning is about how we go about the act of
    thinking using this knowledge. System based languages, like Java or C+,
    have classification systems, called Classes, to be able to describe
    things, in Java we calls these things beans or instances. However those
    classification systems are limited to ensure computational efficiency.
    Over the years researchers have developed increasingly sophisticated ways
    to represent our world, many of you may already have heard of OWL (Web
    Ontology Language). Although there is always a gap between what we can be
    theoretically represented and what can be used computationally in
    practically timely manner, which is why OWL has different sub languages
    from Lite to Full. It is not believed that any reasoning system can
    support OWL Full. Although Each year algorithmic advances try and narrow
    that gap and improve expressiveness available to reasoning engines.</para>

    <para>There are also many approaches to how these systems go about
    thinking. You may have heard of discussions comparing the merits of
    forward chaining, which is reactive and data driven, or backward chaining,
    which is passive and query driven. Many other types of reasoning
    techniques exists, each of which enlarges the scope of the problems we can
    tackle declaratively. To list just a few: imperfect reasoning (fuzzy
    logic, certainty factors), defeasible logic, belief systems, temporal
    reasoning and correlation. Don't worry if some of those words look alien
    to you, they aren't needed to understand Drools and are just there to give
    an idea of the range of scope of research topics; which is actually far
    more extensive than this small list and continues to grow as researches
    push new boundaries.</para>

    <para>KRR is often refereed as the core of Artificial Intelligence Even
    when using biological approaches like neural networks, which model the
    brain and are more about pattern recognition than thinking, they still
    build on KRR theory. My first endeavours with Drools were engineering
    oriented, as I had no formal training or understanding of KRR. Learning
    KRR has allowed me to get a much wider theoretical background. Allowing me
    to better understand both what I've done and where I'm going, as it
    underpins nearly all of the theoretical side to our Drools R&amp;D. It
    really is a vast and fascinating subject that will pay dividends for those
    that take the time learn, I know it did and still does for me. Bracham and
    Levesque have written a seminal piece of work, called "Knowledge
    Representation and Reasoning" that for anyone wanting to build strong
    foundations is a must read. I would also recommend the Russel and Norvig
    book "Artificial Intelligence, a modern approach" which also covers
    KRR.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rule Engines and Production Rule Systems (PRS)</title>

    <para>We've now covered a brief history of AI and learnt that the core of
    AI is formed around KRR. We've shown than KRR is vast and fascinating
    subject which forms the bulk of the theory driving Drools R&amp;D.</para>

    <para>The rule engine is the computer program that delivers KRR
    functionality to the developer. At a high level it has three
    components:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ontology</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Rules</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Data</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>As previous mentioned the ontology is the representation model we
    use for our "things". It could be a simple records or Java classes or full
    blown OWL based ontologies. The Rules do the reasoning and facilitate
    thinking. The distinction between rules and ontologies blurs a little with
    OWL based ontologies, who's richness is rule based.</para>

    <para>The term rule engine is quite ambiguous in that it can be any system
    that uses rules, in any form, that can be applied to data to produce
    outcomes. This includes simple systems like form validation and dynamic
    expression engines. The book "How to Build a Business Rules Engine (2004)"
    by Malcolm Chisholm exemplifies this ambiguity. The book is actually about
    how to build and alter a database schema to hold validation rules. The
    book then shows how to generate VB code from those validation rules to
    validate data entry. Which while very valid, it is very different to what
    we talking about so far.</para>

    <para>Drools started life as a specific type of rule engine called a
    production rule system (PRS) and was based around the Rete algorithm. The
    Rete algorithm, developed by Charles Forgey in 1979, forms the brain of a
    Production Rules System and is able to scale to a large number of rules
    and facts. A Production Rule is a two-part structure: the engine matches
    facts and data against Production Rules - also called Productions or just
    Rules - to infer conclusions which result in actions.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">when
    &lt;conditions&gt;
then
    &lt;actions&gt;;</programlisting>

    <para>The process of matching the new or existing facts against Production
    Rules is called <firstterm>pattern matching</firstterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Pattern Matching</primary>
      </indexterm>, which is performed by the <firstterm>inference
    engine</firstterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Inference Engine</primary>
      </indexterm>. Actions execute in response to changes in data, like a
    database trigger; we say this is a <firstterm>data
    driven</firstterm><indexterm>
        <primary>data driven</primary>
      </indexterm> approach to reasoning. The actions themselves can change
    data, which in turn could match against other rules causing them to fire;
    this is referred to as<indexterm>
        <primary>forward chaining</primary>
      </indexterm>forward chaining</para>

    <para>Drools implements and extends the <indexterm>
        <primary>Rete</primary>
      </indexterm> Rete algorithm;<indexterm>
        <primary>Leaps</primary>
      </indexterm>. The Drools <indexterm>
        <primary>Rete</primary>
      </indexterm> Rete implementation is called ReteOO, signifying that
    Drools has an enhanced and optimized implementation of the Rete algorithm
    for object oriented systems. Our more recent work goes well beyond Rete.
    Other Rete based engines also have marketing terms for their proprietary
    enhancements to Rete, like RetePlus and Rete III. Th e most common
    enhancements are covered in "Production Matching for Large Learning
    Systems (Rete/UL)" (1995) by Robert B. Doorenbos. Leaps used to be
    provided but was retired as it became unmaintained, the good news is our
    research is close to producing an algorithm that merges the benefits of
    Leaps with Rete.</para>

    <para>The Rules are stored in the <indexterm>
        <primary>Production Memory</primary>
      </indexterm> Production Memory and the facts that the Inference Engine
    matches against are kept in the <indexterm>
        <primary>WorkingMemory</primary>
      </indexterm> Working Memory. Facts are asserted into the Working Memory
    where they may then be modified or retracted. A system with a large number
    of rules and facts may result in many rules being true for the same fact
    assertion; these rules are said to be in conflict. The Agenda manages the
    execution order of these conflicting rules using a Conflict Resolution
    strategy.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>High-level View of a Production Rule System</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="300px" contentwidth="540px"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/rule-engine-inkscape.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Hybrid Reasoning Systems (HRS)</title>

    <para>You may have read discussions comparing the merits of forward
    chaining (reactive and data driven) or backward chaining(passive query).
    Here is a quick explanation of these two main types of reasoning.</para>

    <para>Forward chaining is "data-driven" and thus reactionary, with facts
    being asserted into working memory, which results in one or more rules
    being concurrently true and scheduled for execution by the Agenda. In
    short, we start with a fact, it propagates and we end in a
    conclusion.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Forward Chaining</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Forward_Chaining.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Backward chaining is "goal-driven", meaning that we start with a
    conclusion which the engine tries to satisfy. If it can't it then searches
    for conclusions that it can satisfy; these are known as subgoals, that
    will help satisfy some unknown part of the current goal. It continues this
    process until either the initial conclusion is proven or there are no more
    subgoals. Prolog is an example of a Backward Chaining engine. Drools can
    also do backward chaining, which we refer to as derivation queries.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Backward Chaining</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Backward_Chaining.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Historically you would have to make a choice between systems like
    OPS5 (forward) or Prolog (backward). Now many modern systems provide both
    types of reasoning capabilities. There are also many other types of
    reasoning techniques, each of which enlarges the scope of the problems we
    can tackle declaratively. To list just a few: imperfect reasoning (fuzzy
    logic, certainty factors), defeasible logic, belief systems, temporal
    reasoning and correlation. Modern systems are merging these capabilities,
    and others not listed, to create <firstterm>hybrid reasoning
    systems</firstterm> (HRS).</para>

    <para>While Drools started out as a PRS, 5.x introduced Prolog style
    backward chaining reasoning as well as some functional programming styles.
    For this reason HRS is now the preferred term when referring to Drools,
    and what it is.</para>

    <para>Drools current provides crisp reasoning, but imperfect reasoning is
    almost ready. Initially this will be imperfect reasoning with fuzzy logic,
    later we'll add support for other types of uncertainty. Work is also under
    way to bring OWL based ontological reasoning, which will integrate with
    our <firstterm>traits</firstterm> system. We also continue to improve our
    functional programming capabilities.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Expert Systems</title>

    <para>You will often hear the terms <firstterm>expert systems</firstterm>
    used to refer to <firstterm>production rule systems</firstterm> or
    <firstterm>Prolog</firstterm> like systems. While this is normally
    acceptable, it's technically wrong as these are frameworks to build expert
    systems with, and not actually expert systems themselves. It becomes an
    expert system once there is an ontological model to represent the domain
    and there are facilities for knowledge acquisition and explanation.
    </para>

    <para><firstterm>Mycin</firstterm> is the most famous expert system, built
    during the 70s. It is still heavily covered in academic literature, such
    as the recommended book "Expert Systems" by Peter Jackson.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Early History of Expert Systems</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Introduction/expertsytem_history.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Recommended Reading</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">General AI, KRR and Expert System
    Books</emphasis></para>

    <para>For those wanting to get a strong theoretical background in KRR and
    expert systems, I'd strongly recommend the following books. "Artificial
    Intelligence: A Modern Approach" is must have, for anyone's
    bookshelf.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Introduction to Expert Systems</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Peter Jackson</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Expert Systems: Principles and Programming</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Joseph C. Giarratano, Gary D. Riley</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Knowledge Representation and Reasoning</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Ronald J. Brachman, Hector J. Levesque</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Artificial Intelligence : A Modern Approach.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Stuart Russell and Peter Norvig</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Recommended Reading</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Introduction/book_recommendations.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Papers</emphasis></para>

    <para>Here are some recommended papers that cover some interesting areas
    in rule engine research.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Production Matching for Large Learning Systems : Rete/UL
        (1993)</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Robert B. Doorenbos</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Advances In Rete Pattern Matching</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Marshall Schor, Timothy P. Daly, Ho Soo Lee, Beth R.
            Tibbitts (AAAI 1986)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Collection-Oriented Match</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Anurag Acharya and Milind Tambe (1993)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Leaps Algorithm (1990)</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Don Battery</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Gator: An Optimized Discrimination Network for Active Database
        Rule Condition Testing (1993)</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Eric Hanson , Mohammed S. Hasan</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Drools Books</emphasis></para>

    <para>There are currently three Drools books, all from Packt
    Publishing.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>JBoss Drools Business Rules</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Paul Brown</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Drools JBoss Rules 5.0 Developers Guide</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Michali Bali</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Drools Developer's Cookbook</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Lucas Amador</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Recommended Reading</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Introduction/drools_book_recommendations.png"
                     format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</section>
