<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Decision Tables in Spreadsheets</title>

  <para>Decision tables are a "precise yet compact" (ref. Wikipedia) way of representing conditional logic, and are well
  suited to <emphasis>business</emphasis> level rules.</para>

  <para>Drools supports managing rules in a spreadsheet format. Supported formats are Excel (XLS), and CSV, which means
  that a variety of spreadsheet programs (such as Microsoft Excel, OpenOffice.org Calc amongst others) can be utilized.
  It is expected that web based decision table editors will be included in a near future release.</para>

  <para>Decision tables are an old concept (in software terms) but have proven useful over the years. Very briefly
  speaking, in Drools decision tables are a way to generate rules driven from the data entered into a spreadsheet. All
  the usual features of a spreadsheet for data capture and manipulation can be taken advantage of.</para>

  <section>
    <title>When to Use Decision Tables</title>

    <para>Consider decision tables as a course of action if rules exist that can be expressed as rule templates and
    data: each row of a decision table provides data that is combined with a template to generate a rule.</para>

    <para>Many businesses already use spreadsheets for managing data, calculations, etc. If you are happy to continue
    this way, you can also manage your business rules this way. This also assumes you are happy to manage packages of
    rules in <filename>.xls</filename> or <filename>.csv</filename> files. Decision tables are not recommended for rules
    that do not follow a set of templates, or where there are a small number of rules (or if there is a dislike towards
    software like Excel or OpenOffice.org). They are ideal in the sense that there can be control over what
    <emphasis>parameters</emphasis> of rules can be edited, without exposing the rules directly.</para>

    <para>Decision tables also provide a degree of insulation from the underlying object model.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Here are some examples of real world decision tables (slightly edited to protect the innocent).</para>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         Using Excel to edit a decision table 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/excel.png" format="PNG" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         Multiple actions for a rule row 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/actions.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         Using OpenOffice.org 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/open_office.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>In the above examples, the technical aspects of the decision table have been collapsed away (using a standard
    spreadsheet feature).</para>

    <para>The rules start from row 17, with each row resulting in a rule. The conditions are in columns C, D, E, etc.,
    the actions being off-screen. The values in the cells are quite simple, and their meaning is indicated by the
    headers in Row 16. Column B is just a description. It is customary to use color to make it obvious what the
    different areas of the table mean.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Note that although the decision tables look like they process top down, this is not necessarily the case.
      Ideally, rules are authored without regard for the order of rows, simply because this makes maintenance easier, as
      rows will not need to be shifted around all the time.</para>
    </note>

    <para>As each row is a rule, the same principles apply. As the rule engine processes the facts, any rules that match
    may fire. (Some people are confused by this. It is possible to clear the agenda when a rule fires and simulate a
    very simple decision table where only the first match effects an action.) Also note that you can have multiple
    tables on one spreadsheet. This way, rules can be grouped where they share common templates, yet at the end of the
    day they are all combined into one rule package. Decision tables are essentially a tool to generate DRL rules
    automatically.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         A real world example using multiple tables for grouping like rules 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/multi_table.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How Decision Tables Work</title>

    <para>The key point to keep in mind is that in a decision table each row is a rule, and each column in that row is
    either a condition or action for that rule.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         Rows and columns 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/row_col.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The spreadsheet looks for the <firstterm>RuleTable</firstterm> keyword to indicate the start of a rule table
    (both the starting row and column). Other keywords are also used to define other package level attributes (covered
    later). It is important to keep the keywords in one column. By convention the second column ("B") is used for this,
    but it can be any column (convention is to leave a margin on the left for notes). In the following diagram, C is
    actually the column where it starts. Everything to the left of this is ignored.</para>

    <para>If we expand the hidden sections, it starts to make more sense how it works; note the keywords in column
    C.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         Expanded for rule templates 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/expanded.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>Now the hidden magic which makes it work can be seen. The RuleSet keyword indicates the name to be used in the
    <emphasis>rule package</emphasis> that will encompass all the rules. This name is optional, using a default, but it
    <emphasis>must</emphasis> have the <emphasis>RuleSet</emphasis> keyword in the cell immediately to the right.</para>

    <para>The other keywords visible in Column C are Import and Sequential which will be covered later. The RuleTable
    keyword is important as it indicates that a chunk of rules will follow, based on some rule templates. After the
    RuleTable keyword there is a name, used to prefix the names of the generated rules. The sheet name and row numbers
    are appended to guarantee unique rule names.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>The RuleTable name combined with the sheet name must be unique across all spreadsheet files in the same
      KnowledgeBase. If that's not the case, some rules might have the same name and only 1 of them will be applied.
      To show such ignored rules, <link linkend="changingTheDefaultBuildResultSeverity">raise the severity of such rule
      name conflicts</link>.</para>
    </warning>

    <para> The column of RuleTable indicates the column in which the rules start; columns to the
    left are ignored.</para>

    <note>
      <para>In general the keywords make up name-value pairs.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Referring to row 14 (the row immediately after RuleTable), the keywords CONDITION and ACTION indicate that the
    data in the columns below are for either the LHS or the RHS parts of a rule. There are other attributes on the rule
    which can also be optionally set this way.</para>

    <para>Row 15 contains declarations of <firstterm>ObjectTypes</firstterm>. The content in this row is optional, but
    if this option is not in use, the row must be left blank; however this option is usually found to be quite useful.
    When using this row, the values in the cells below (row 16) become constraints on that object type. In the above
    case, it generates <code>Person(age=="42")</code> and <code>Cheese(type=="stilton")</code>, where 42 and "stilton"
    come from row 18. In the above example, the "==" is implicit; if just a field name is given the translator assumes
    that it is to generate an exact match.</para>

    <note>
      <para>An ObjectType declaration can span columns (via merged cells), meaning that all columns below the merged
      range are to be combined into one set of constraints within a single pattern matching a single fact at a time, as
      opposed to non-merged cells containing the same ObjectType, but resulting in different patterns, potentially
      matching different or identical facts.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Row 16 contains the rule templates themselves. They can use the "$param" placeholder to indicate where data
    from the cells below should be interpolated. (For multiple insertions, use "$1", "$2", etc., indicating parameters
    from a comma-separated list in a cell below.) Row 17 is ignored; it may contain textual descriptions of the column's
    purpose.</para>

    <para>Rows 18 and 19 show data, which will be combined (interpolated) with the templates in row 15, to generate
    rules. If a cell contains no data, then its template is ignored. (This would mean that some condition or action does
    not apply for that rule row.) Rule rows are read until there is a blank row. Multiple RuleTables can exist in a
    sheet. Row 20 contains another keyword, and a value. The row positions of keywords like this do not matter (most
    people put them at the top) but their column should be the same one where the RuleTable or RuleSet keywords should
    appear. In our case column C has been chosen to be significant, but any other column could be used instead.</para>

    <para>In the above example, rules would be rendered like the following (as it uses the "ObjectType" row):</para>

    <screen>//row 18
rule "Cheese_fans_18"
when
    Person(age=="42")
    Cheese(type=="stilton")
then
    list.add("Old man stilton");
end
</screen>

    <note>
      <para>The constraints <code>age=="42"</code> and <code>type=="stilton"</code> are interpreted as single
      constraints, to be added to the respective ObjectType in the cell above. If the cells above were spanned, then
      there could be multiple constraints on one "column".</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Spreadsheet Syntax</title>

    <section>
      <title>Spreadsheet Structure</title>

      <para>There are two types of rectangular areas defining data that is used for generating a DRL file. One, marked
      by a cell labelled <code>RuleSet</code>, defines all DRL items except rules. The other one may occur repeatedly
      and is to the right and below a cell whose contents begin with <code>RuleTable</code>. These areas represent the
      actual decision tables, each area resulting in a set of rules of similar structure.</para>

      <para>A Rule Set area may contain cell pairs, one below the <code>RuleSet</code> cell and containing a keyword
      designating the kind of value contained in the other one that follows in the same row.</para>

      <para>The columns of a Rule Table area define patterns and constraints for the left hand sides of the rules
      derived from it, actions for the consequences of the rules, and the values of individual rule attributes. Thus, a
      Rule Table area should contain one or more columns, both for conditions and actions, and an arbitrary selection of
      columns for rule attributes, at most one column for each of these. The first four rows following the row with the
      cell marked with <code>RuleTable</code> are earmarked as header area, mostly used for the definition of code to
      construct the rules. It is any additional row below these four header rows that spawns another rule, with its data
      providing for variations in the code defined in the Rule Table header.</para>

      <para>All keywords are case insensitive.</para>

      <para>Only the first worksheet is examined for decision tables.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Rule Set Entries</title>

      <para>Entries in a Rule Set area may define DRL constructs (except rules), and specify rule attributes. While
      entries for constructs may be used repeatedly, each rule attribute may be given at most once, and it applies to
      all rules unless it is overruled by the same attribute being defined within the Rule Table area.</para>

      <para>Entries must be given in a vertically stacked sequence of cell pairs. The first one contains a keyword and
      the one to its right the value, as shown in the table below. This sequence of cell pairs may be interrupted by
      blank rows or even a Rule Table, as long as the column marked by <code>RuleSet</code> is upheld as the one
      containing the keyword.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Entries in the Rule Set area</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Keyword</entry>

              <entry>Value</entry>

              <entry>Usage</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>RuleSet</entry>

              <entry>The package name for the generated DRL file. Optional, the default is
              <code>rule_table</code>.</entry>

              <entry>Must be First entry.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Sequential</entry>

              <entry>"true" or "false". If "true", then salience is used to ensure that rules fire from the top
              down.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, at most once. If omitted, no firing order is imposed.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>EscapeQuotes</entry>

              <entry>"true" or "false". If "true", then quotation marks are escaped so that they appear literally in the
              DRL.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, at most once. If omitted, quotation marks are escaped.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Import</entry>

              <entry>A comma-separated list of Java classes to import.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, may be used repeatedly.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Variables</entry>

              <entry>Declarations of DRL globals, i.e., a type followed by a variable name. Multiple global definitions
              must be separated with a comma.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, may be used repeatedly.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Functions</entry>

              <entry>One or more function definitions, according to DRL syntax.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, may be used repeatedly.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Queries</entry>

              <entry>One or more query definitions, according to DRL syntax.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, may be used repeatedly.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Declare</entry>

              <entry>One or more declarative types, according to DRL syntax.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, may be used repeatedly.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>For defining rule attributes that apply to all rules in the generated DRL file you can use any of the
      entries in the following table. Notice, however, that the proper keyword must be used. Also, each of these
      attributes may be used only once.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Rule attribute entries in the Rule Set area</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Keyword</entry>

              <entry>Initial</entry>

              <entry>Value</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>PRIORITY</entry>

              <entry>P</entry>

              <entry>An integer defining the "salience" value for the rule. Overridden by the "Sequential" flag.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>DURATION</entry>

              <entry>D</entry>

              <entry>A long integer value defining the "duration" value for the rule.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>TIMER</entry>

              <entry>T</entry>

              <entry>A timer definition. See "Timers and Calendars".</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CALENDARS</entry>

              <entry>E</entry>

              <entry>A calendars definition. See "Timers and Calendars".</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>NO-LOOP</entry>

              <entry>U</entry>

              <entry>A Boolean value. "true" inhibits looping of rules due to changes made by its consequence.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>LOCK-ON-ACTIVE</entry>

              <entry>L</entry>

              <entry>A Boolean value. "true" inhibits additional activations of all rules with this flag set within the
              same ruleflow or agenda group.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>AUTO-FOCUS</entry>

              <entry>F</entry>

              <entry>A Boolean value. "true" for a rule within an agenda group causes activations of the rule to
              automatically give the focus to the group.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>ACTIVATION-GROUP</entry>

              <entry>X</entry>

              <entry>A string identifying an activation (or XOR) group. Only one rule within an activation group will
              fire, i.e., the first one to fire cancels any existing activations of other rules within the same
              group.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>AGENDA-GROUP</entry>

              <entry>G</entry>

              <entry>A string identifying an agenda group, which has to be activated by giving it the "focus", which is
              one way of controlling the flow between groups of rules.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>RULEFLOW-GROUP</entry>

              <entry>R</entry>

              <entry>A string identifying a rule-flow group.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Rule Tables</title>

      <para>All Rule Tables begin with a cell containing "RuleTable", optionally followed by a string within the same
      cell. The string is used as the initial part of the name for all rules derived from this Rule Table, with the row
      number appended for distinction. (This automatic naming can be overridden by using a NAME column.) All other cells
      defining rules of this Rule Table are below and to the right of this cell.</para>

      <para>The next row defines the column type, with each column resulting in a part of the condition or the
      consequence, or providing some rule attribute, the rule name or a comment. The table below shows which column
      headers are available; additional columns may be used according to the table showing rule attribute entries given
      in the preceding section. Note that each attribute column may be used at most once. For a column header, either
      use the keyword or any other word beginning with the letter given in the "Initial" column of these tables.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Column Headers in the Rule Table</title>

        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Keyword</entry>

              <entry>Initial</entry>

              <entry>Value</entry>

              <entry>Usage</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>NAME</entry>

              <entry>N</entry>

              <entry>Provides the name for the rule generated from that row. The default is constructed from the text
              following the RuleTable tag and the row number.</entry>

              <entry>At most one column</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>DESCRIPTION</entry>

              <entry>I</entry>

              <entry>A text, resulting in a comment within the generated rule.</entry>

              <entry>At most one column</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CONDITION</entry>

              <entry>C</entry>

              <entry>Code snippet and interpolated values for constructing a constraint within a pattern in a
              condition.</entry>

              <entry>At least one per rule table</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>ACTION</entry>

              <entry>A</entry>

              <entry>Code snippet and interpolated values for constructing an action for the consequence of the
              rule.</entry>

              <entry>At least one per rule table</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>METADATA</entry>

              <entry>@</entry>

              <entry>Code snippet and interpolated values for constructing a metadata entry for the rule.</entry>

              <entry>Optional, any number of columns</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Given a column headed CONDITION, the cells in successive lines result in a conditional element.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the first cell below CONDITION develops into a pattern for the rule condition, with the snippet
          in the next line becoming a constraint. If the cell is merged with one or more neighbours, a single pattern
          with multiple constraints is formed: all constraints are combined into a parenthesized list and appended to
          the text in this cell. The cell may be left blank, which means that the code snippet in the next row must
          result in a valid conditional element on its own.</para>

          <para>To include a pattern without constraints, you can write the pattern in front of the text for another
          pattern.</para>

          <para>The pattern may be written with or without an empty pair of parentheses. A "from" clause may be appended
          to the pattern.</para>

          <para>If the pattern ends with "eval", code snippets are supposed to produce boolean expressions for inclusion
          into a pair of parentheses after "eval".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the second cell below CONDITION is processed in two steps.</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The code snippet in this cell is modified by interpolating values from cells farther down in the
              column. If you want to create a constraint consisting of a comparison using "==" with the value from the
              cells below, the field selector alone is sufficient. Any other comparison operator must be specified as
              the last item within the snippet, and the value from the cells below is appended. For all other constraint
              forms, you must mark the position for including the contents of a cell with the symbol
              <code>$param</code>. Multiple insertions are possible by using the symbols <code>$1</code>,
              <code>$2</code>, etc., and a comma-separated list of values in the cells below.</para>

              <para>A text according to the pattern
              <code>forall(</code><emphasis>delimiter</emphasis><code>){</code><emphasis>snippet</emphasis><code>}</code>
              is expanded by repeating the <emphasis>snippet</emphasis> once for each of the values of the
              comma-separated list of values in each of the cells below, inserting the value in place of the symbol
              <code>$</code> and by joining these expansions by the given <emphasis>delimiter</emphasis>. Note that the
              forall construct may be surrounded by other text.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If the cell in the preceding row is not empty, the completed code snippet is added to the
              conditional element from that cell. A pair of parentheses is provided automatically, as well as a
              separating comma if multiple constraints are added to a pattern in a merged cell.</para>

              <para>If the cell above is empty, the interpolated result is used as is.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the third cell below CONDITION is for documentation only. It should be used to indicate the
          column's purpose to a human reader.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the fourth row on, non-blank entries provide data for interpolation as described above. A blank
          cell results in the omission of the conditional element or constraint for this rule.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Given a column headed ACTION, the cells in successive lines result in an action statement.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the first cell below ACTION is optional. If present, it is interpreted as an object
          reference.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the second cell below ACTION is processed in two steps.</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The code snippet in this cell is modified by interpolating values from cells farther down in the
              column. For a singular insertion, mark the position for including the contents of a cell with the symbol
              <code>$param</code>. Multiple insertions are possible by using the symbols <code>$1</code>,
              <code>$2</code>, etc., and a comma-separated list of values in the cells below.</para>

              <para>A method call without interpolation can be achieved by a text without any marker symbols. In this
              case, use any non-blank entry in a row below to include the statement.</para>

              <para>The forall construct is available here, too.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If the first cell is not empty, its text, followed by a period, the text in the second cell and a
              terminating semicolon are stringed together, resulting in a method call which is added as an action
              statement for the consequence.</para>

              <para>If the cell above is empty, the interpolated result is used as is.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the third cell below ACTION is for documentation only. It should be used to indicate the
          column's purpose to a human reader.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the fourth row on, non-blank entries provide data for interpolation as described above. A blank
          cell results in the omission of the action statement for this rule.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>Using <code>$1</code> instead of <code>$param</code> works in most cases, but it will fail if the
        replacement text contains a comma: then, only the part preceding the first comma is inserted. Use this
        "abbreviation" judiciously.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Given a column headed METADATA, the cells in successive lines result in a metadata annotation for the
      generated rules.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the first cell below METADATA is ignored.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the second cell below METADATA is subject to interpolation, as described above, using values
          from the cells in the rule rows. The metadata marker character <code>@</code> is prefixed automatically, and
          thus it should not be included in the text for this cell.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Text in the third cell below METADATA is for documentation only. It should be used to indicate the
          column's purpose to a human reader.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the fourth row on, non-blank entries provide data for interpolation as described above. A blank
          cell results in the omission of the metadata annotation for this rule.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>

      <para>The various interpolations are illustrated in the following example.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Interpolating cell data</title>

        <para>If the template is <code>Foo(bar == $param)</code> and the cell is <code>42</code>, then the result is
        <code>Foo(bar == 42)</code>.</para>

        <para>If the template is <code>Foo(bar &lt; $1, baz == $2)</code> and the cell contains <code>42,43</code>, the
        result will be <code>Foo(bar &lt; 42, baz ==43)</code>.</para>

        <para>The template <code>forall(&amp;&amp;){bar != $}</code> with a cell containing <code>42,43</code> results
        in <code>bar != 42 &amp;&amp; bar != 43</code>.</para>
      </example>

      <para>The next example demonstrates the joint effect of a cell defining the pattern type and the code snippet
      below it. <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/spanned_column.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> This spreadsheet section shows how the <code>Person</code> type declaration spans 2 columns, and
      thus both constraints will appear as <code>Person(age == ..., type == ...)</code>. Since only the field names are
      present in the snippet, they imply an equality test.</para>

      <para>In the following example the marker symbol <code>$param</code> is used. <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/with_param.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> The result of this column is the pattern <code>Person(age == "42"))</code>. You may have noticed
      that the marker and the operator "==" are redundant.</para>

      <para>The next example illustrates that a trailing insertion marker can be omitted. <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/operator_completion.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> Here, appending the value from the cell is implied, resulting in <code>Person(age &lt;
      "42")).</code></para>

      <para>You can provide the definition of a binding variable, as in the example below. . <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/with_binding.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> Here, the result is <code>c: Cheese(type == "stilton").</code> Note that the quotes are provided
      automatically. Actually, anything can be placed in the object type row. Apart from the definition of a binding
      variable, it could also be an additional pattern that is to be inserted literally.</para>

      <para>A simple construction of an action statement with the insertion of a single value is shown below.
      <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/consequence.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> The cell below the ACTION header is left blank. Using this style, anything can be placed in the
      consequence, not just a single method call. (The same technique is applicable within a CONDITION column as
      well.)</para>

      <para>Below is a comprehensive example, showing the use of various column headers. It is not an error to have no
      value below a column header (as in the NO-LOOP column): here, the attribute will not be applied in any of the
      rules. <screenshot>
          <info>
             Example usage of keywords for imports, headers, etc. 
          </info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/Key.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>And, finally, here is an example of Import, Variables and Functions. <screenshot>
          <info>
             Example usage of keywords for functions, etc. 
          </info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/keywords.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot> Multiple package names within the same cell must be separated by a comma. Also, the pairs of type
      and variable names must be comma-separated. Functions, however, must be written as they appear in a DRL file. This
      should appear in the same column as the "RuleSet" keyword; it could be above, between or below all the rule
      rows.</para>

      <note>
        <para>It may be more convenient to use Import, Variables, Functions and Queries repeatedly rather than packing
        several definitions into a single cell.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating and integrating Spreadsheet based Decision Tables</title>

    <para>The API to use spreadsheet based decision tables is in the drools-decisiontables module. There is really only
    one class to look at: <literal>SpreadsheetCompiler</literal>. This class will take spreadsheets in various formats,
    and generate rules in DRL (which you can then use in the normal way). The <literal>SpreadsheetCompiler</literal> can
    just be used to generate partial rule files if it is wished, and assemble it into a complete rule package after the
    fact (this allows the separation of technical and non-technical aspects of the rules if needed).</para>

    <para>To get started, a sample spreadsheet can be used as a base. Alternatively, if the plug-in is being used (Rule
    Workbench IDE), the wizard can generate a spreadsheet from a template (to edit it an xls compatible spreadsheet
    editor will need to be used). <screenshot>
        <info>
           Wizard in the IDE 
        </info>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/wizard.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Managing Business Rules in Decision Tables</title>

    <section>
      <title>Workflow and Collaboration</title>

      <para>Spreadsheets are well established business tools (in use for over 25 years). Decision tables lend themselves
      to close collaboration between IT and domain experts, while making the business rules clear to business analysts,
      it is an ideal separation of concerns.</para>

      <para>Typically, the whole process of authoring rules (coming up with a new decision table) would be something
      like:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Business analyst takes a template decision table (from a repository, or from IT)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Decision table business language descriptions are entered in the table(s)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Decision table rules (rows) are entered (roughly)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Decision table is handed to a technical resource, who maps the business language (descriptions) to
          scripts (this may involve software development of course, if it is a new application or data model)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Technical person hands back and reviews the modifications with the business analyst.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The business analyst can continue editing the rule rows as needed (moving columns around is also fine
          etc).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In parallel, the technical person can develop test cases for the rules (liaising with business analysts)
          as these test cases can be used to verify rules and rule changes once the system is running.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using spreadsheet features</title>

      <para>Features of applications like Excel can be used to provide assistance in entering data into spreadsheets,
      such as validating fields. Lists that are stored in other worksheets can be used to provide valid lists of values
      for cells, like in the following diagram. <screenshot>
          <info>
             Wizard in the IDE 
          </info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/lists.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Some applications provide a limited ability to keep a history of changes, but it is recommended to use an
      alternative means of revision control. When changes are being made to rules over time, older versions are archived
      (many open source solutions exist for this, such as Subversion or Git).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rule Templates</title>

    <para>Related to decision tables (but not necessarily requiring a spreadsheet) are "Rule Templates" (in the
    drools-templates module). These use any tabular data source as a source of rule data - populating a template to
    generate many rules. This can allow both for more flexible spreadsheets, but also rules in existing databases for
    instance (at the cost of developing the template up front to generate the rules).</para>

    <para>With Rule Templates the data is separated from the rule and there are no restrictions on which part of the
    rule is data-driven. So whilst you can do everything you could do in decision tables you can also do the
    following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>store your data in a database (or any other format)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>conditionally generate rules based on the values in the data</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>use data for any part of your rules (e.g. condition operator, class name, property name)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>run different templates over the same data</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>As an example, a more classic decision table is shown, but without any hidden rows for the rule meta data (so
    the spreadsheet only contains the raw data to generate the rules).</para>

    <screenshot>
      <info>
         Template data 
      </info>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Decision_Tables/template1.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>See the <filename>ExampleCheese.xls</filename> in the examples download for the above spreadsheet.</para>

    <para>If this was a regular decision table there would be hidden rows before row 1 and between rows 1 and 2
    containing rule metadata. With rule templates the data is completely separate from the rules. This has two handy
    consequences - you can apply multiple rule templates to the same data and your data is not tied to your rules at
    all. So what does the template look like?</para>

    <programlisting>
1  template header
2  age
3  type
4  log
5
6  package org.drools.examples.templates;
7
8  global java.util.List list;
9
10 template "cheesefans"
11
12 rule "Cheese fans_@{row.rowNumber}"
13 when
14    Person(age == @{age})
15    Cheese(type == "@{type}")
16 then
17    list.add("@{log}");
18 end
19
20 end template
</programlisting>

    <para>Annotations to the preceding program listing: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Line 1: All rule templates start with <code>template header</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lines 2-4: Following the header is the list of columns in the order they appear in the data. In this
          case we are calling the first column <code>age</code>, the second <code>type</code> and the third
          <code>log</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Line 5: An empty line signifies the end of the column definitions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lines 6-9: Standard rule header text. This is standard rule DRL and will appear at the top of the
          generated DRL. Put the package statement and any imports and global and function definitions into this
          section.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Line 10: The keyword <code>template</code> signals the start of a rule template. There can be more than
          one template in a template file, but each template should have a unique name.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lines 11-18: The rule template - see below for details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Line 20: The keywords <code>end template</code> signify the end of the template.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The rule templates rely on MVEL to do substitution using the syntax @{token_name}. There is currently one
    built-in expression, @{row.rowNumber} which gives a unique number for each row of data and enables you to generate
    unique rule names. For each row of data a rule will be generated with the values in the data substituted for the
    tokens in the template. With the example data above the following rule file would be generated:</para>

    <programlisting>
package org.drools.examples.templates;

global java.util.List list;

rule "Cheese fans_1"
when
  Person(age == 42)
  Cheese(type == "stilton")
then
  list.add("Old man stilton");
end

rule "Cheese fans_2"
when
  Person(age == 21)
  Cheese(type == "cheddar")
then
  list.add("Young man cheddar");
end
</programlisting>

    <para>The code to run this is simple:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">
DecisionTableConfiguration dtableconfiguration =
    KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newDecisionTableConfiguration();
dtableconfiguration.setInputType( DecisionTableInputType.XLS );

KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();

kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( getSpreadsheetName(),
                                                    getClass() ),
              ResourceType.DTABLE,
              dtableconfiguration );
</programlisting>
  </section>
</section>
