<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  
  <title>Introduction</title>
    
    
    <para>What happens to a business process when something unexpected happens during the process? Most
      of the time, when creating and designing a new process definition, the first step is to
      describe the <emphasis>normative</emphasis> or desirable behaviour. However, a process
      definition that only describes all of the normal tasks and their execution order is
      incomplete.</para>
    
    <para>The next step is to think about what might go <emphasis>wrong</emphasis> when the business 
      process is run. What would happen if any of the human or technical actors in the process do 
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> respond in unexpexected ways?  Will any of the technical systems that the 
      process interacts with return unexpected results -- or not return any results at all?</para>
    
    <para>Deviations from the normative or "happy" flow of a business process are called 
      <emphasis>exceptions</emphasis>. In some cases, exceptions might not be that unusual, such as 
      trying to debit an empty bank account. However, some processes might contain many complex 
      situations involving exceptions, all of which must be handled correctly.</para>
    
    <note>
      <para>The rest of chapter assumes that you know how to create custom <code>&lt;task&gt;</code>
        nodes and how to implement and register <code>WorkItemHandler</code> implementations. More
        information about these topics can be found in the <link linkend='jBPMDomainSpecificProcesses' 
          endterm="jBPMDomainSpecificProcesses.title"/> chapter.</para>
    </note>
  
</section>
