<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>jBPM Eclipse Plugin</title>
  
  <para>The jBPM Eclipse plugin provides developers (and very technical users) with an environment 
  to edit and test processes, and integrate it deeply with their applications.  It provides the following
  features (on top of the Eclipse IDE):</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Wizards for creation of</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a jBPM project</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a BPMN2 process</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>jBPM Perspective (showing the most commonly used views in a predefined layout)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>
    
    <para>The jBPM installer is capable of downloading and installing an Eclipse installation, including
    the Drools and jBPM Eclipse plugin (with a full jBPM runtime preconfigured) and the Eclipse BPMN2 Modeler.
    </para>
    
    <tip><para>Using the jBPM installer is definitely the recommended starting point for most users.</para></tip>
    
    <para>You can however also download and install the jBPM Eclipse Plugin manually.  To do so, you need to:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Download Eclipse (Kepler recommended, but older versions like Indigo or Juno should also
      still work)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Start Eclipse</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Select "Install New Software ..." from the Help menu. Add the Drools and jBPM update
      site <link xlink:href="http://downloads.jboss.org/jbpm/release/6.0.0.Final/org.drools.updatesite/">
      http://downloads.jboss.org/jbpm/release/6.0.0.Final/org.drools.updatesite/</link>.  You should see
      the plugins as shown below.  Note that you can also download and unzip the Drools and jBPM update site
      to your local file system and use that as local update site instead.</para>
      
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/UpdateSite.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

      <para>Select the JBoss jBPM Core and JBoss Drools Core plugins and click "Next >". Click "Next >"
      again after reviewing your selecting, accept the terms of the license 
      agreement and click "Finish" to download and install the plugins.  If you get a warning about
      installing software that contains unsigned content, click OK.  After successful installation,
      Eclipse should ask you to restart, click Yes.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The plugin should now be installed.  To check, check if you can for example see the
      new jBPM Project wizard: under the "File" menu, select "New Project ..." and there you should be 
      able to see "New jBPM Project" under the jBPM category.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Register a jBPM runtime to get started, see the section on jBPM runtimes in this chapter
      for more information.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Note that, when doing a manual install, you still need to manually install the Eclipse BPMN 2.0
    Modeler plugin as well. Check out the chapter on the Eclipse BPMN 2.0 Modeler on how to do that.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>jBPM Project Wizard</title>
  
    <para>The aim of the new project wizard is to set up an executable
    sample project to start using processes immediately. This will set up a
    basic structure, the classpath, sample process and a test case to get you
    started.  To create a new jBPM project, in the "File" menu select "New" and then
    "Project ..." and under the jBPM category, select "jBPM Project".  A dialog as shown
    below should pop up.</para>
    
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/WizardProject.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Fill in a name for your project and if necessary change the location where this project
    should be located (by default Eclipse will generate it inside your Eclipse workspace folder) and
    click "Next >".</para>
    
    <para>Now you can optionally include a sample process in your project to get started.  You can select
    to either use a simple "Hello World" process, a slightly more advanced process including human tasks
    and persistence or simply an empty project.  You can also select to include a JUnit test class that you
    can use to test your process. These can serve as a starting point, and will give you
    something executable almost immediately, which you can then modify to your needs. </para>
    
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/WizardProject2.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>Finally, the last page in the wizard allows you select a jBPM runtime, as shown below.
    You can either use the default runtime (as configured for you workspace, in your workspace
    preferences), or you can select a specific runtime for this project.  For more information
    about runtimes and how to create them, see the section on jBPM runtimes in this chapter.</para>
    
    <para>You can also select which version of jBPM you want to generate sample code for.  By
    default it will generate an example using the latest jBPM 6.x API, but you could also generate
    examples using the old jBPM 5.x API.  Note that you yourself are responsible for making sure that
    the code you generate can be understood by the runtime (for example, if you create an example using
    jBPM6 API but select a jBPM5 runtime, your sample will not compile).  Also note that, if you want
    to execute a jBPM5 example on jBPM6, you will need to have the knowledge-api JAR inside your
    jBPM6 runtime, as this is responsible for the backwards compatibility of the jBPM5 API in jBPM6.
    </para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/WizardProject3.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   
    <para>When you selected the simple 'hello world' example, the result is shown
    below. Feel free to experiment with the plug-in at this point.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>New jBPM project artifacts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/WizardProjectStructure.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The newly created project contains an example process file (sample.bpmn)
    in the src/main/resources directory and an example Java file (ProcessTest.java) that
    can be used to test the process in a jBPM engine. You'll find this in
    the folder src/main/java, in the com.sample package. All the other JARs that
    are necessary during execution are also added to the classpath in a custom
    classpath container called jBPM Library.</para>

    <para>You can also convert an existing Java project to a jBPM project by selecting the
    "Convert to jBPM Project" action.  Right-click the project you want to convert and under
    the "Configure" category (at the bottom) select "Convert to jBPM Project".  This will add
    the jBPM Library to your project's classpath.</para>
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>New BPMN2 Process Wizard</title>

    <para>You can create a new process simply as an empty text file with extension ".bpmn",
    or use the "New BPMN2 Process" wizard to do so. To create a new process, in the 
    "File" menu select "New" and then "Other ..." and under the jBPM category, select 
    "BPMN2 Process" and click "Next >".  In the next dialog, you should select the folder
    where the process should be created (for example the src/main/resources folder of your
    project) and a name for the process.  Clicking "Finish" should create your new process
    (by default it should only contain one start node) and open it so you can start editing
    it.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>jBPM Runtime</title>
    
    <para>A jBPM runtime is a collection of JAR files that represent one specific release of the
    jBPM project JARs. To create a runtime, download the binary distribution of the version of
    jBPM you want to use and unzip on your local file system.  You must then point the IDE to the 
    release of your choice by selecting the folder where these JARs are located. If you want to 
    create a new runtime based on the latest jBPM project JARs included in the plugin itself, you
    can also easily do that. You are required to specify a default jBPM runtime for your Eclipse
    workspace, but each individual project can override the default and select the appropriate runtime
    for that project specifically.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Defining a jBPM Runtime</title>

      <para>To define one or more jBPM runtimes using the Eclipse
      preferences view you open up your Preferences, by selecting the
      "Preferences" menu item in the menu "Window". A "Preferences" dialog
      should show all your settings. On the left side of this dialog, under
      the jBPM category, select "Installed jBPM runtimes". The panel on
      the right should then show the currently defined jBPM runtimes. For example,
      if you used the jBPM Installer, it should look like the figure
      below.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/PreferencesRuntimes.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>To define a new jBPM runtime, click on the "Add" button. A dialog
      such as the one shown below should pop up, asking for the name of your
      runtime and the location on your file system where it can be
      found.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/PreferencesAddRuntime.png"
                     format="PNG" role=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>In general, you have two options:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you simply want to use the default JAR files as included in
          the jBPM Eclipse plugin, you can create a new jBPM runtime
          automatically by clicking the "Create a new jBPM Runtime ..."
          button. A file browser will show up, asking you to select the folder
          on your file system where you want this runtime to be created. The
          plugin will then automatically copy all required dependencies to the
          specified folder.  Make sure to select a unique name for the newly
          created runtime and click "OK" to register this runtime.</para>
          
          <tip><para>Note that creating a jBPM runtime from the default JAR files
          as included in the jBPM Eclipse plugin is only recommended to get you
          started the first time and for very simple use cases.  The runtime that is
          created this way only contains the minimal set of JARs, and therefore doesn't
          support a significant set of features, including for example persistence.
          Make sure to create a full runtime (using the second approach) for real 
          development.</para></tip>
          
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you want to use one specific release of the jBPM project,
          you should create a folder on your file system that contains all the
          necessary jBPM libraries and dependencies (for example by downloading
          the binary distribution and unzipping it on your local file system).
          Instead of creating a new jBPM runtime as explained above, give your
          runtime a unique name and click the "Browse ..." button to select the
          location of this folder containing all the required JARs.  Click "OK"
          to register this runtime.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>After clicking the OK button, the runtime should show up in your
      table of installed jBPM runtimes, as shown below. Click on the checkbox in
      front of one of the installed runtimes to make it the default jBPM
      runtime. The default jBPM runtime will be used as the runtime of all
      your new jBPM projects (in case you didn't select a project-specific
      runtime).</para>

      <para>You can add as many jBPM runtimes as you need.  Note that you will
      need to restart Eclipse if you changed the default runtime and you want
      to make sure that all the projects that are using the default runtime 
      update their classpath accordingly.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting a runtime for your jBPM project</title>

      <para>Whenever you create a jBPM project (using the New jBPM Project
      wizard or by converting an existing Java project to a jBPM project),
      the plugin will automatically add all the required JARs to the classpath
      of your project.</para>

      <para>When creating a new jBPM project, the plugin will automatically
      use the default Drools runtime for that project, unless you specify a
      project-specific one. You can do this in the final step of the New
      jBPM Project wizard, as shown below, by deselecting the "Use default
      Drools runtime" checkbox and selecting the appropriate runtime in the
      drop-down box. If you click the "Configure workspace settings ..." link,
      the workspace preferences showing the currently installed jBPM
      runtimes will be opened, so you can add new runtimes there.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Eclipse/WizardProject3.png"
                     format="PNG" role=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can change the runtime of a jBPM project at any time by
      opening the project properties and selecting the jBPM category, as
      shown below. Mark the "Enable project specific settings" checkbox and
      select the appropriate runtime from the drop-down box. If you click the
      "Configure workspace settings ..." link, the workspace preferences
      showing the currently installed jBPM runtimes will be opened, so you
      can add new runtimes there. If you deselect the "Enable project specific
      settings" checkbox, it will use the default runtime as defined in your
      global workspace preferences.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/PreferencesProject.png"
                     format="PNG" role=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>jBPM Maven Project Wizard</title>
  
    <para>The aim of the new Maven project wizard is to set up an executable
    sample project to start using processes immediately (but not as normal Java project with
    all jBPM dependencies added using a jBPM library but by using Maven (and thus a pom.xml)
    to define your project's properties and dependencies. This wizard will set up a Maven project
    using a pom.xml, and include a sample process and Java class to execute it.  To create a new
    jBPM Maven project, in the "File" menu select "New" and then
    "Project ..." and under the jBPM category, select "jBPM Project (Maven)".  Give your project
    a name and click finish.  The result should be as shown below.</para>
    
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/WizardMavenProject.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>The pom.xml that is generated for your project contains the following:</para>
    <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;project xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/POM/4.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/maven-4.0.0.xsd"&gt;

  &lt;modelVersion&gt;4.0.0&lt;/modelVersion&gt;

  &lt;groupId&gt;com.sample&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;jbpm-example&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.0.0-SNAPSHOT&lt;/version&gt;

  &lt;name&gt;jBPM :: Sample Maven Project&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;A sample jBPM Maven project&lt;/description&gt;

  &lt;properties&gt;
    &lt;jbpm.version&gt;6.0.0.Final&lt;/jbpm.version&gt;
  &lt;/properties&gt;

  &lt;repositories&gt;
    &lt;repository&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;jboss-public-repository-group&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;JBoss Public Repository Group&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/&lt;/url&gt;
      &lt;releases&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;
        &lt;updatePolicy&gt;never&lt;/updatePolicy&gt;
      &lt;/releases&gt;
      &lt;snapshots&gt;
        &lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;
        &lt;updatePolicy&gt;daily&lt;/updatePolicy&gt;
      &lt;/snapshots&gt;
    &lt;/repository&gt;
  &lt;/repositories&gt;

  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.jbpm&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;jbpm-test&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;${jbpm.version}&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;</programlisting>

  <para>In the properties section, you can specify which version of jBPM you would like to use
  (by default it uses 6.0.0.Final).  It adds the JBoss Nexus Maven repository (where all the jBPM
  JARs and their dependencies are located) to your project and configures the dependencies.</para>
  
  <note><para>By default, only the jbpm-test JAR is specified as a dependency, as this has transitive
  dependencies to almost all of the core dependencies you will need.  You are free to update the
  dependencies section however to include only the dependencies you need.</para></note>
  
  <para>The project also contains a sample process, under src/main/resources, in the com.sample
  package, and a kmodule.xml configuration file under the META-INF folder.  The kmodule.xml defines
  which resources (processes, rules, etc.) are to be loaded as part of your project.  In this case,
  it is defining a kbase called "kbase" that will load all the resources in the com.sample folder:</para>
  
  <programlisting>&lt;kmodule xmlns="http://jboss.org/kie/6.0.0/kmodule"&gt;
  &lt;kbase name="kbase" packages="com.sample"/&gt;
&lt;/kmodule&gt;</programlisting>

  <para>Finally, it also contains a Java class that can be used to execute the sample process.
  It will first create a kbase called "kbase" (by inspecting the kmodule.xml file and thus
  loading the <code>sample.bpmn</code> process) and then use a <code>RuntimeManager</code> to
  get access to a <code>KieSession</code> and <code>TaskService</code>.  In this case, it is used
  to start a process and then complete the tasks created by this process one by one.</para>
  
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Drools Eclipse plugin</title>
    
    <para>The Drools Eclipse Plugin, which is bundled as part of the same Eclipse Update Site
    as the jBPM Eclipse Plugin, provides similar features for creating and editing business rules,
    and execute them using the Drools engine.  This for example allows you to create and edit .drl
    files containing business rules.  You can combine your processes and rules inside one project
    and execute them together on the same KieSession.</para>
  </section>
    
</section>
