<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Specification</title>

  <para>This sections introduces the specification with the included packages
  javax.rules and javax.rules.admin. If you have read this section, you should
  know, which classes are included and what their purpose is.</para>

  <para>The Java Rule Engine API is divided in two packages. You use
  "javax.rules" mainly for executing the rule engine and "javax.rules.admin"
  for administration.</para>

  <section>
    <title>javax.rules</title>

    <para>The next sections are dealing with the interfaces, classes and
    exceptions which are included in the javax.rules package.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Interfaces</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>Handle</interfacename></para>

          <para>The Handle is used to retrieve an Object back from the
          <classname>WorkingMemory</classname> , which was added there in a
          <classname>StatefulRuleSession</classname> . With the
          <classname>Handle</classname> you can modify or remove an
          <classname>Object</classname> from the
          <classname>WorkingMemory</classname> . To modify an Object call
          <methodname>updateObject()</methodname> from the
          <classname>StatefulRuleSession</classname> . To remove it, call
          <methodname>removeObject()</methodname> with the
          <classname>Handle</classname> as the Parameter. Inside of the
          implementation of the Java Rule Engine API will be called the
          <methodname>modifyObject()</methodname> and
          <methodname>retractObject()</methodname> methods of the encapsulated
          Knowledge (Drools and jBPM) API.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>ObjectFilter</interfacename></para>

          <para>This interface is used to filter objects for
          RuleSession.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>RuleExecutionSetMetadata</interfacename></para>

          <para>The RuleExecutionSetMetadata is used to store name,
          description and URI for a RuleExecutionSet.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>RuleRuntime</interfacename></para>

          <para>The RuleRuntime is the key to a RuleSession. The RuleRuntime
          obtained from the RuleServiceProvider.</para>

          <para>If you retrieve a RuleRuntime call createRuleSession() to open
          a RuleSession.</para>

          <para>Through the RuleRuntime you can retrieve a list of URIs of all
          RuleExecutionSets, which were registered by a RuleAdministrator. You
          need the URI as a String to open a RuleSession to the rule engine.
          The rule engine will use the rules of the RuleExecutionSet inside of
          the RuleSession.</para>

          <para>Important: The Map is used for Globals. Globals were formerly
          called ApplicationData (in Drools 2.x). The key needs to be the
          identifier of the Global and the Value the object you want to use as
          a Global.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>RuleSession</interfacename></para>

          <para>The RuleSession is the object you are working with, if you
          want to contact the rule engine.</para>

          <para>If you are getting a RuleSession from the RuleRuntime, then it
          will be either a StatefulRuleSession or a
          StatelessRuleSession.</para>

          <para>Please call in both cases the release()-method that all
          resources will be freed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>StatefulRuleSession </interfacename></para>

          <para>A stateful Rule Session you are using, if you need to run the
          rule engine more than once. You get the chance to assert objects,
          execute rules, assert objects again etc..</para>

          <para>You will get a Handle for every object which you are asserting
          to the Rule Session. Do not lose it, you will need it, to retract or
          modify objects in the Working Memory. You are having no direct
          contact to Drools´ Working Memory which is used inside the
          implementation, for this you got the RuleSession.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>StatelessRuleSession </interfacename></para>

          <para>A stateless RuleSession means, that you are having only one
          contact to the rule engine. You are giving a list of objects to the
          rule engine and the rule engine asserts them all and starts
          execution immediately. The result is a list of objects. The content
          of the result list depends on your rules. If your rules are not
          modifying or retracting any objects from the Working Memory, you
          should get all objects, you added back.</para>

          <para>There is a possibility using an ObjectFilter which will filter
          the resulting list of objects before you get it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Classes</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><classname>RuleServiceProvider</classname></para>

          <para>The RuleServiceProvider gives you the RuleAdministrator or a
          RuleRuntime, which you need to open a new Rule Session. To get the
          RuleServiceProvider call
          RuleServiceProviderManager.getRuleServiceProvider().</para>

          <para>In J2EE environment you can bind the RuleServiceProvider to
          the JNDI and make a lookup to get it in all your
          applications.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleServiceProviderManager </classname></para>

          <para>The RuleServiceProvider is often compared with the
          DriverManager, which you use in JDBC. It works like setting up the
          Driver for a DataBase.</para>

          <para>To load the Drools Rule Service Provider use:</para>

          <para><code>Class ruleServiceProviderClass =
          Class.forName("org.drools.jsr94.rules.RuleServiceProviderImpl");</code></para>

          <para>If you did not register it, yet, do it now:</para>

          <para><code>RuleServiceProviderManager.registerRuleServiceProvider(
          "http://jboss.com/products/rules", ruleServiceProviderClass);
          </code></para>

          <para>Now you can get your RuleServiceProvider calling:</para>

          <para><code>RuleServiceProviderManager.getRuleServiceProvider("http://jboss.com/products/rules")</code>;</para>

          <para>If you do not need the RuleServiceProvider any more,
          deregister it:</para>

          <para><code>RuleServiceProviderManager.deregisterRuleServiceProvider(
          "http://jboss.com/products/rules"); </code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Exceptions</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><classname>ConfigurationException</classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown when a user configuration error has
          been made.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>InvalidHandleException</classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown when a client passes an invalid
          Handle to the rule engine.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> InvalidRuleSessionException </classname></para>

          <para>The InvalidRuleSessionException should be thrown when a method
          is invoked on a RuleSession and the internal state of the
          RuleSession is invalid. This may have occurred because a
          StatefulRuleSession has been serialized and external resources can
          no longer be accessed. This exception is also used to signal that a
          RuleSession is in an invalid state (such as an attempt to use it
          after the release method has been called) (Taken from JCP API
          Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>RuleException</classname></para>

          <para>Base class for all Exception classes in the javax.rules
          package (Taken from JCP API Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>RuleExecutionException</classname></para>

          <para>This exception is not thrown in the Drools 3 JSR 94
          implementation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleExecutionSetNotFoundException
          </classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown if a client requests a
          RuleExecutionSet from the RuleRuntime and the URI or
          RuleExecutionSet cannot be found (Taken from JCP API
          Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleSessionCreateException </classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown when a client requests a RuleSession
          from the RuleRuntime and an error occurs that prevents a RuleSession
          from being returned (Taken from JCP API Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleSessionTypeUnsupportedException
          </classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown when a client requests a RuleSession
          and the vendor does not support the given type (defined in the
          RuleRuntime) or the RuleExecutionSet itself does not support the
          requested mode (Taken from JCP API Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>javax.rules.admin</title>

    <para>In this section all the interfaces and exceptions from the
    javax.rules.admin package are explained.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Interfaces</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>LocalRuleExecutionSetProvider</interfacename></para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>Rule</interfacename></para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>RuleAdministrator</interfacename></para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>RuleExecutionSet</interfacename></para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><interfacename>RuleExecutionSetProvider</interfacename></para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Exceptions</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><classname>RuleAdministrationException</classname></para>

          <para>Base class for all administration RuleException classes in the
          javax.rules.admin package (Taken from JCP API Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleExecutionSetCreateException
          </classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown if an error occurs while creating a
          rule execution set (Taken from JCP API Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleExecutionSetDeregistrationException
          </classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown if an exception occurs while
          unregistering a rule execution set from a URI (Taken from JCP API
          Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname> RuleExecutionSetRegisterException
          </classname></para>

          <para>This exception is thrown if an exception occurs while
          registering a rule execution set to a URI (Taken from JCP API
          Documentation).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
