<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="Overview/" xml:id="jBPMAsyncExecution"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Concurrency and asynchronous execution</title>

  <section>
    <title>Concurrency</title>

    <para>In the following text, we will refer to two types of
    "multi-threading": logical and technical. Technical multi-threading is
    what happens when multiple threads or processes are started on a computer,
    for example by a Java or C program. Logical multi-threading is what we see
    in a BPM process after the process reaches a parallel gateway, for
    example. From a functional standpoint, the original process will then
    split into two processes that are executed in a parallel fashion.</para>

    <para>Of course, the jBPM engine supports logical multi-threading: for
    example, processes that include a parallel gateway. We've chosen to
    implement logical multi-threading using one thread: a jBPM process that
    includes logical multi-threading will only be executed in one technical
    thread. The main reason for doing this is that multiple (technical)
    threads need to be be able to communicate state information with each
    other if they are working on the same process. This requirement brings
    with it a number of complications. While it might seem that
    multi-threading would bring performance benefits with it, the extra logic
    needed to make sure the different threads work together well means that
    this is not guaranteed. There is also the extra overhead incurred because
    we need to avoid race conditions and deadlocks.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Engine execution</title>

      <para>In general, the jBPM engine executes actions in serial. For
      example, when the engine encounters a script task in a process, it will
      synchronously execute that script and wait for it to complete before
      continuing execution. Similarly, if a process encounters a parallel
      gateway, it will sequentially trigger each of the outgoing branches, one
      after the other. This is possible since execution is almost always
      instantaneous, meaning that it is extremely fast and produces almost no
      overhead. As a result, the user will usually not even notice this.
      Similarly, action scripts in a process are also synchronously executed,
      and the engine will wait for them to finish before continuing the
      process. For example, doing a Thread.sleep(...) as part of a script will
      not make the engine continue execution elsewhere but will block the
      engine thread during that period.</para>

      <para>The same principle applies to service tasks. When a service task
      is reached in a process, the engine will also invoke the handler of this
      service synchronously. The engine will wait for the
      completeWorkItem(...) method to return before continuing execution. It
      is important that your service handler executes your service
      asynchronously if its execution is not instantaneous.</para>

      <para>An example of this would be a service task that invokes an
      external service. Since the delay in invoking this service remotely and
      waiting for the results might be too long, it might be a good idea to
      invoke this service asynchronously. This means that the handler will
      only invoke the service and will notify the engine later when the
      results are available. In the mean time, the process engine then
      continues execution of the process.</para>

      <para>Human tasks are a typical example of a service that needs to be
      invoked asynchronously, as we don't want the engine to wait until a
      human actor has responded to the request. The human task handler will
      only create a new task (on the task list of the assigned actor) when the
      human task node is triggered. The engine will then be able to continue
      execution on the rest of the process (if necessary) and the handler will
      notify the engine asynchronously when the user has completed the
      task.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multiple knowledge sessions and persistence</title>

      <para>The simplest way to run multiple processes is to run them all
      using one knowledge session. However, there are cases in which it's
      necessary to run multiple processes in different knowledge sessions,
      even in different (technical) threads. Both are supported by
      jBPM.</para>

      <para>When we add persistence (using a database, for example) to a
      situation in which we have multiple knowledge sessions (and processes),
      there is a guideline that users should be aware of. The following
      paragraphs explain why this guideline is important to follow.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>Please make sure to use a database that allows row-level locks
        as well as table-level locks.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>For example, a user could have a situation in which there are 2
      (or more) threads running, each with its own knowledge session instance.
      On each thread, jBPM processes are being started using the local
      knowledge session instance.</para>

      <para>In this use case, a race condition exists in which both thread A
      and thread B will have coincidentally simultaneously finished a process.
      At this point, because persistence is being used, both thread A and B
      will be committing changes to the database. If row-level locks are not
      possible, then the following situation can occur:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Thread A has a lock on the ProcessInstanceInfo table, having
          just committed a change to that table.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Thread A wants a lock on the SessionInfo table in order to
          commit a change there.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Thread B has the opposite situation: it has a lock on the
          SessionInfo table, having just committed a change there.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Thread B wants a lock on the ProcessInstanceInfo table, even
          though Thread A already has a lock on it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This is a deadlock situation which the database and application
      will not be able to solve. However, if row-level locks are possible (and
      enabled!!) in the database (and tables used), then this situation will
      not occur.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asynchronous execution</title>

    <section>
      <title>Asynchronous handlers</title>

      <para>How can we implement an asynchronous service handler? To start
      with, this depends on the technology you're using. If you're only using
      Java, you could execute the actual service in a new thread:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public class MyServiceTaskHandler implements WorkItemHandler {

        
  public void executeWorkItem(WorkItem workItem, WorkItemManager manager) {
    new Thread(new Runnable() {
      public void run() {
        // Do the heavy lifting here ...
      }
    }).start();
  }

  public void abortWorkItem(WorkItem workItem, WorkItemManager manager) {
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para>It's advisable to have your handler contact a service that
      executes the business operation, instead of having it perform the actual
      work. If anything goes wrong with a business operation, it doesn't
      affect your process. The loose coupling that this provides also gives
      you greater flexibility in reusing services and developing them.</para>

      <para>For example, you can have your human task handler simply invoke
      the human task service to add a task there. To implement an asynchronous
      handler, you usually have to simply do an asynchronous invocation of
      this service. This usually depends on the technology you use to do the
      communication, but this might be as simple as asynchronously invoking a
      web service, or sending a JMS message to the external service.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>jbpm executor</title>

      <para>In version 6, jBPM introduces new component called jbpm executor
      which provides quite advanced features for asynchronous execution. It
      delivers generic environment for background execution of commands.
      Commands are nothing more than business logic encapsulated within simple
      interface. It does not have any process runtime related information,
      that means no need to complete work items, or anything of that sort. It
      purely focuses on the business logic to be executed. It receives data
      via CommandContext and returns results of the execution with
      ExecutionResults.</para>

      <para>Before looking into details on jBPM support for asynchronous
      execution let's look at what are the common requirements for such
      execution:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>allows asynchronous execution of given piece of business
          logic</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>allows to retry in case of resources are temporarily
          unavailable e.g. external system interaction</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>allows to handle errors in case all retries have been
          attempted</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>provides cancellation option</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>provides history log of execution</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When confronting these requirements with the "simple async
      handler" (executed as separate thread) you can directly notice that all
      of these would need to be implemented all over again by different
      systems. Due to that a common, generic component has been provided out
      of the box to simplify and empower usage.</para>

      <para>jBPM executor operates on commands, which are essential piece of
      code that is going to be executed as background job.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">/**
 * Executor's Command are dedicated to contain purely business logic that should be executed. 
 * It should not have any reference to underlying process engine and should not be concerned
 * with any process runtime related logic such us completing work item, sending signals, etc.
 * &lt;br/&gt;
 * Information that are taken from process will be delivered as part of data instance of 
 * &lt;code&gt;CommandContext&lt;/code&gt;. Depending on the execution context that data can vary but 
 * in most of the cases following will be given:
 * &lt;ul&gt;
 *  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 *  &lt;li&gt;businessKey - usually unique identifier of the caller&lt;/li&gt;
 *  &lt;li&gt;callbacks - FQCN of the &lt;code&gt;CommandCollback&lt;/code&gt; that shall be used on command completion&lt;/li&gt;
 * &lt;/ul&gt;
 * When executed as part of the process (work item handler) additional data can be expected:
 * &lt;ul&gt;
 *  &lt;li&gt;workItem - the actual work item that is being executed with all its parameters&lt;/li&gt;
 *  &lt;li&gt;processInstanceId - id of the process instance that triggered this work&lt;/li&gt;
 *  &lt;li&gt;deploymentId - if given process instance is part of an active deployment&lt;/li&gt;
 * &lt;/ul&gt;
 * Important note about implementations is that it shall always be possible to be initialized with default constructor
 * as executor service is an async component so it will initialize the command on demand using reflection.
 * In case there is a heavy logic on initialization it should be placed in another service implementation that 
 * can be looked up from within command.
 */
public interface Command {
    
    /**
     * Executed this command's logic.
     * @param ctx - contextual data given by the executor service
     * @return returns any results in case of successful execution
     * @throws Exception in case execution failed and shall be retried if possible
     */
    public ExecutionResults execute(CommandContext ctx) throws Exception;
}</programlisting>

      <para>Looking at the interface above, there is no specific integration
      with the jBPM runtime engine, it's decoupled from it to put main focus
      on the actual logic that shall be executed as part of that command
      rather to worry about integration with process engine. This design
      promotes reuse of already existing logic by simply wrapping it with
      Command implementation.</para>

      <para>Input data is transferred from process engine to command via
      CommandContext. It acts purely as data transfer object and puts single
      requirement on the data it holds - all objects must be
      serializable.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">/**
 * Data holder for any contextual data that shall be given to the command upon execution.
 * Important note that every object that is added to the data container must be serializable 
 * meaning it must implement &lt;code&gt;java.io.Seriazliable&lt;/code&gt;
 *
 */
public class CommandContext implements Serializable {

    private static final long serialVersionUID = -1440017934399413860L;
    private Map&lt;String, Object&gt; data;

    public CommandContext() {
        data  = new HashMap&lt;String, Object&gt;();
    }

    public CommandContext(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; data) {
        this.data = data;
    }

    public void setData(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; data) {
        this.data = data;
    }

    public Map&lt;String, Object&gt; getData() {
        return data;
    }

    public Object getData(String key) {
        return data.get(key);
    }

    public void setData(String key, Object value) {
        data.put(key, value);
    }

    public Set&lt;String&gt; keySet() {
        return data.keySet();
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return "CommandContext{" + "data=" + data + '}';
    }
}</programlisting>

      <para>Next outcome is provided to process engine via ExecutionResults,
      which is very similar in nature to the CommandContext and acts as data
      transfer object.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">/**
 * Data holder for command's result data. Whatever command produces should be placed in
 * this results so they can be later on referenced by name by the requester - e.g. process instance.
 *
 */
public class ExecutionResults implements Serializable {

    private static final long serialVersionUID = -1738336024526084091L;
    private Map&lt;String, Object&gt; data = new HashMap&lt;String, Object&gt;();

    public ExecutionResults() {
    }

    public void setData(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; data) {
        this.data = data;
    }

    public Map&lt;String, Object&gt; getData() {
        return data;
    }

    public Object getData(String key) {
        return data.get(key);
    }

    public void setData(String key, Object value) {
        data.put(key, value);
    }

    public Set&lt;String&gt; keySet() {
        return data.keySet();
    }

    @Override
    public String toString() {
        return "ExecutionResults{" + "data=" + data + '}';
    }
    
    
}</programlisting>

      <para>Executor covers all requirements listed above and provides user
      interface as part of jbpm console and kie workbench (kie-wb)
      applications.</para>

      <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Async/executor-ui.png"
                       format="PNG" role=""/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Above screenshot illustrates history view of executor's job queue.
      As can be seen on it there are several options available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>view details of the job</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>cancel given job</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>create new job</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>WorkItemHandler backed with jbpm executor</title>

        <para>jBPM (again in version 6) provides an out of the box async work
        item handler that is backed by the jbpm executor. So by default all
        features that executor delivers will be available for background
        execution within process instance. AsyncWorkItemHandler can be
        configured in two ways:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>as generic handler that expects to get the command name as
            part of work item parameters</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>as specific handler for given type of work item - for
            example web service</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Option 1 is by default configured for jbpm console and kie-wb
        web applications and is registered under <emphasis
        role="bold">async</emphasis> name in every ksession that is
        bootstrapped within the applications. So whenever there is a need to
        execute some logic asynchronously following needs to be done at
        modeling time (using jbpm web designer):</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>specify async as TaskName property</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>create data input called CommandClass</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>assign fully qualified class name for the CommandClass data
            input</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Next follow regular way to complete process modeling. Note that
        all data inputs will be transferred to executor so they must be
        serializable.</para>

        <para>Second option allows to register different instances of
        AsyncWorkItemHandler for different work items. Since it's registered
        for dedicated work item most likely the command will be dedicated to
        that work item as well. If so CommandClass can be specified on
        registration time instead of requiring it to be set as work item
        parameters. To register such handlers for jbpm console or kie-wb
        additional class is required to inform what shall be registered. A CDI
        bean that implements WorkItemHandlerProducer interface needs to be
        provided and placed on the application classpath so CDI container will
        be able to find it. Then at modeling time TaskName property needs to
        be aligned with those used at registration time.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuration</title>

        <para>jbpm executor is configurable to allow fine tuning of its
        environment. In general jbpm executor runs as a thread pool that
        periodically checks for waiting jobs and executes them when needed.
        Configuration of jbpm executor is done via system properties:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>org.kie.executor.disabled = true|false - allows to
            completely disable executor component</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>org.kie.executor.pool.size = Integer - allows to specify
            thread pool size where default it 1</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>org.kie.executor.retry.count = Integer - allows to specify
            number of retries in case of errors while running a job</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>org.kie.executor.interval = Integer - allows to specify
            interval (in seconds) that executor will use while checking for
            waiting jobs where default is 3 seconds</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
