<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Overview</title>
        <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-1-Overview/Overview.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    
    <para>This figure gives an overview of the different components of the jBPM project.  jBPM can
    integrate with a lot of other services (and we've shown a few using grey boxes on the figure),
    but here we focus on the components that are part of the jBPM project itself.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>The process engine is the core of the project and is required if you want to
        execute business processes (all other components are optional, as indicated by the dashed
        border).  Your application services typically invoke the core engine (to start processes or to
        signal events) whenever necessary.
          <itemizedlist>
             <listitem>An optional core service is the history log; this will log all information
        about the current and previous state of all your process instances.</listitem>
             <listitem>Another optional core service is the human task service that will take care of
        the human task life cycle if human actors participate in the process.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>Two types of graphical editors are supported for defining your business processes:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>The Eclipse plugin is an extension to the Eclipse IDE, targeted towards developers,
            and allows you to create business processes using drag and drop, advanced debugging, etc.</listitem>
            <listitem>The web-based designer allows business users to manage business processes in
            a web-based environment.  A web-based form builder also allows you to create, generate or
            edit forms related to those processes (to start the process or to complete one of the
            user tasks).</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>The Guvnor repository is an optional component that can be used to store all your
        business processes.  It supports collaboration, versioning, etc.  There is integration
        with both the Eclipse plugin and web-based designer, supporting round-tripping between
        the different tools.</listitem>
        <listitem>The web-based management console allows business users to manage
        their runtime (manage business processes like start new processes, inspect running instances, etc.),
        to manage their task list and to perform Business Activity Monitoring (BAM) and see reports.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>Each of the components are described in more detail below.</para>
</section>