<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Sudoku Example</title>

    <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Sudoku
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.sudoku.Main
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> Java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> sudokuSolver.drl, sudokuValidator.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Demonstrates the solving of logic problems, and complex pattern matching.
</programlisting>

    <para>This example demonstrates how Drools can be used to find a solution
    in a large potential solution space based on a number of constraints. We
    use the popular puzzle of Sudoku. This example also shows how Drools can
    be integrated into a graphical interface and how callbacks can be used to
    interact with a running Drools rules engine in order to update the
    graphical interface based on changes in the Working Memory at
    runtime.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Sudoku Overview</title>

      <para>Sudoku is a logic-based number placement puzzle. The objective is
      to fill a 9x9 grid so that each column, each row, and each of the nine
      3x3 zones contains the digits from 1 to 9, once, and only once.</para>

      <para>The puzzle setter provides a partially completed grid and the
      puzzle solver's task is to complete the grid with these
      constraints.</para>

      <para>The general strategy to solve the problem is to ensure that when
      you insert a new number it should be unique in its particular
      3x3 zone, row and column.</para>

      <para>See <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudoku">Wikipedia</link>
      for a more detailed description.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Example</title>

      <para>Download and install drools-examples as described above and then
      execute <filename>java org.drools.examples.sudoku.Main</filename>. This
      example requires Java 5.</para>

      <para>A window will be displayed with a relatively simple partially
      filled grid. <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku1.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Click on the "Solve" button and the Drools-based engine will fill
      out the remaining values. The Console window will display detailed
      information about the rules which are executing to solve the puzzle
      in a human readable form.</para>

      <para><screen>Rule #3 determined the value at (4,1) could not be 4 as this value already exists in the same column at (8,1)
Rule #3 determined the value at (5,5) could not be 2 as this value already exists in the same row at (5,6)
Rule #7 determined (3,5) is 2 as this is the only possible cell in the column that can have this value
Rule #1 cleared the other PossibleCellValues for (3,5) as a ResolvedCellValue of 2 exists for this cell.
Rule #1 cleared the other PossibleCellValues for (3,5) as a ResolvedCellValue of 2 exists for this cell.
... 
Rule #3 determined the value at (1,1) could not be 1 as this value already  exists in the same zone at (2,1)
Rule #6 determined (1,7) is 1 as this is the only possible cell in the row that can have this value
Rule #1 cleared the other PossibleCellValues for (1,7) as a ResolvedCellValue of 1 exists for this cell.
Rule #6 determined (1,1) is 8 as this is the only possible cell in the row that can have this value</screen></para>

      <para>Once all of the activated rules for the solving logic have
      executed, the engine executes a second rule base to check that the
      solution is complete and valid. In this case it is, and the "Solve"
      button is disabled and displays a text like
      <code>"Solved (1052ms)"</code>.<screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku2.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>The example comes with a number of grids which can be loaded and
      solved. Click on "File", then "Samples" and "Medium" to load a more
      challenging grid. Note that the solve button is enabled when the new
      grid is loaded.
      <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku3.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Click on the "Solve" button again to solve this new grid.
      <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku4.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Now, let us load a Sudoku grid that is deliberately invalid. Click
      on "File", "Samples" and "!DELIBERATELY BROKEN!". Note that this grid
      starts with some issues, for example the value 5 appears twice in the
      first row.<screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku5.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Nevertheless, click on the "Solve" button to apply the solving
      rules to this invalid grid. Note that the "Solve" button is relabelled
      to indicate that the resulting solution is invalid. <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku6.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>In addition, the validation rule set outputs all of the issues
      which are discovered to the console. <programlisting>
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (6,0) and (4,0)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (4,0) and (6,0)
There are two cells on the same row with the same value at (2,4) and (2,2)
There are two cells on the same row with the same value at (2,2) and (2,4)
There are two cells on the same row with the same value at (6,3) and (6,8)
There are two cells on the same row with the same value at (6,8) and (6,3)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (7,4) and (0,4)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (0,4) and (7,4)
There are two cells on the same row with the same value at (0,8) and (0,0)
There are two cells on the same row with the same value at (0,0) and (0,8)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (1,2) and (3,2)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (3,2) and (1,2)
There are two cells in the same zone with the same value at (6,3) and (7,3)
There are two cells in the same zone with the same value at (7,3) and (6,3)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (7,3) and (6,3)
There are two cells on the same column with the same value at (6,3) and (7,3)</programlisting></para>

      <para>We will look at the solving rule set later in this section, but
      for the moment we should note that some theoretically solvable solutions
      can not be solved by the engine as it stands. Click on
      "File", "Samples" and then "Hard 3" to load a sparsely populated grid.
      <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku7.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Now click on the "Solve" button and note that the current rules
      are unable to complete the grid, even though (if you are a Sudoku
      aficionado) you may be able to see a way forward with the solution.
      <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/SodukiExample/sudoku8.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>At the present time, the solving functionality has been achieved
      by the use of ten rules. This rule set could be extended to enable the
      engine to tackle more complex logic for filling grids such as
      this.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Java Source and Rules Overview</title>

      <para>The Java source code can be found in the
      /src/main/java/org/drools/examples/sudoku directory, with the two DRL
      files defining the rules located in the
      /src/main/rules/org/drools/examples/sudoku directory.</para>

      <para>The package <code>org.drools.examples.sudoku.swing</code>
      contains a set of classes which implement a framework for Sudoku
      puzzles. Note that this package does not have any dependencies on
      the Drools libraries. <code>SudokuGridModel</code>
      defines an interface which can be implemented to store a Sudoku puzzle
      as a 9x9 grid of <code>Integer</code> values, some of which may be null,
      indicating that the value for the cell has not yet been resolved.
      <code>SudokuGridView</code> is
      a Swing component which can visualize any implementation of
      <code>SudokuGridModel</code>. <code>SudokuGridEvent</code> and
      <code>SudokuGridListener</code> are used to
      communicate state changes between the model and the view: events are
      fired when a cell's value is resolved or changed. If you are familiar
      with the model-view-controller patterns in other Swing components such
      as <code>JTable</code> then this pattern should be familiar.
      <code>SudokuGridSamples</code> provides a number of partially filled
      Sudoku puzzles for demonstration purposes.</para>

      <para>Package <code>org.drools.examples.sudoku.rules</code> contains an
      implementation of <code>SudokuGridModel</code> which is based on Drools.
      Two Java objects are used, both of which extend
      <code>AbstractCellValue</code> and represent a value for a specific cell
      in the grid, including the row and column location of the cell, an index
      of the 3x3 zone the cell is contained in, and the value of the cell.
      <code>PossibleCellValue</code> indicates that we do not currently know
      for sure what the value in a cell is. There can be from 2 to 9 possible
      cell values for a given cell. <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> indicates 
      that we have determined what the value
      for a cell must be. There can only be one resolved cell value for a
      given cell. <code>DroolsSudokuGridModel</code> implements
      <code>SudokuGridModel</code> and is responsible for converting an
      initial two dimensional array of partially specified cells into a set
      of <code>CellValue</code> Java object, creating a Working Memory
      based on <filename>solverSudoku.drl</filename> and inserting the
      <code>CellValue</code> objects into the Working Memory. When the 
      <code>solve()</code> method is called it calls in turn
      <code>fireAllRules()</code> on this Working Memory to try to solve
      the puzzle. <code>DroolsSudokuGridModel</code> attaches a 
      <code>WorkingMemoryListener</code> to the Working Memory, which
      allows it to be called back on insert and retract events as the
      puzzle is solved. When a new <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> is inserted
      into the Working Memory, this callback allows the implementation to
      fire a <code>SudokuGridEvent</code> to its
      <code>SudokuGridListener</code> clientele, which can then update
      themselves in realtime. Once all the rules fired by the solver Working
      Memory have executed, <code>DroolsSudokuGridModel</code> runs a
      second set of rules, based on <filename>validatorSudoku.drl</filename>
      which works with the same set of Java objects to determine whether the
      resulting grid is a valid and a full solution.</para>

      <para>The class <code>org.drools.examples.sudoku.Main</code> implements
      a Java application combining the components desribed.</para>

      <para>The packae <code>org.drools.examples.sudoku</code> contains two
      DRL files. <filename>solverSudoku.drl</filename> defines the rules
      which attempt to solve a Sudoku puzzle, and
      <filename>validator.drl</filename> defines the rules which determin
      whether the current state of the Working Memory represents a valid
      solution. Both use <code>PossibleCellValue</code> and
      <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> objects as their facts and
      both output information to the Console window as their rules fire. In a
      real-world situation we would insert logging information and use the
      <code>WorkingMemoryListener</code> to display this information to a
      user, rather than use the console in this fashion.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sudoku Validator Rules (validatorSudoku.drl)</title>

      <para>We start with the validator rules as this rule set is shorter and
      simpler than the solver rule set.</para>

      <para>The first rule simply checks that no <code>PossibleCellValue</code>
      objects remain in the Working Memory. Once the puzzle is solved, only
      <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> objects should be present, one for
      each cell.</para>

      <para>The other three rules each match all of the
      <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> objects and bind them to the
      variable <code>$resolved1</code>. They then look for
      <code>ResolvedCellValues</code> that
      contain the same value and are located, respectively, in the same row,
      column, or 3x3 zone. If these rules are fired they add a message to a
      global list of strings describing the reason the solution is invalid.
      <code>DroolsSudokoGridModel</code> injects this list before it runs
      the rule set and checks whether it is empty or not after having called
      <code>fireAllRules()</code>. If it is not empty then it prints all the
      strings in the list and sets a flag to indicate that the grid is not
      solved.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sudoku Solving Rules (solverSudoku.drl)</title>

      <para>Now let us look at the more complex rule set used to solve Sudoku
      puzzles.</para>

      <para>Rule #1 is basically a book-keeping rule. Several of the other
      rules insert <code>ResolvedCellValues</code> into the working memory
      at specific rows and columns after they have determined that a given
      cell must have a
      certain value. At this point, it is important to clear the Working
      Memory of any inserted <code>PossibleCellValues</code> at the same
      row and column
      with invalid values. This rule is therefore given a higher salience than
      the remaining rules to ensure that as soon as the LHS is true,
      activations for the rule move to the top of the Agenda and are fired. In
      turn, this prevents the spurious firing of other rules due to the
      combination of a <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> and one or more
      <code>PossibleCellValues</code> being present in the same cell.
      This rule also calls <code>update()</code> on the
      <code>ResolvedCellValue</code>, even though its value has not in
      fact been modified to ensure that Drools fires an event to any
      <code>WorkingMemoryListeners</code>  attached to the Working Memory
      so that they can update themselves - in
      this case so that the GUI can display the new state of the grid.</para>

      <para>Rule #2 identifies cells in the grid which have only one possible
      value. The first line of the <literal>when</literal> clause matches all of the
      <code>PossibleCellValue</code> objects in the Working Memory. The
      second line demonstrates a use of the <literal>not</literal> keyword. This rule
      will only fire if no other <code>PossibleCellValue</code> objects
      exist in the Working Memory at the same
      row and column but with a different value. When the rule fires, the
      single <code>PossibleCellValue</code> at the row and column is
      retracted from the Working Memory and is replaced by a new
      <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> at the same
      row and column with the same value.</para>

      <para>Rule #3 removes <code>PossibleCellValues</code> with a given
      value from a row when they have the same value as a
      <code>ResolvedCellValue</code>. In other words, when a cell is filled
      with a resolved value, we need to remove the
      possibility of any other cell on the same row having this value. The
      first line of the when clause matches all <code>ResolvedCellValue</code>
      objects in the Working Memory. The second line matches
      <code>PossibleCellValues</code> which have both the same row and the
      same value as these <code>ResolvedCellValue</code>
      objects. If any are found, the rule activates and, when fired retracts
      the <code>PossibleCellValue</code> which can no longer be a solution
      for that cell.</para>

      <para>Rules #4 and #5 act in the same way as Rule #3 but check for
      redundant <code>PossibleCellValues</code> in a given column and a 
      given zone of the grid as a <code>ResolvedCellValue</code>
      respectively.</para>

      <para>Rule #6 checks for the scenario where a possible cell value only
      appears once in a given row. The first line of the LHS matches against
      all <code>PossibleCellValue</code> facts in the Working Memory, storing
      the result in a number of local variables. The second line checks that
      no other <code>PossibleCellValue</code> objects with the same value
      exist on this row. The third to fifth lines check that there is not
      a <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> with the same value in the same zone,
      row or column so that this rule does not fire prematurely.
      It is interesting to note that we could remove lines 3 to 5 and give
      rules #3, #4 and #5 a higher salience to make sure they always fire
      before rules #6,#7 and #8. When the rule fires, we know that
      <code>$possible</code> must represent the value for the cell;
      so, as in Rule #2, we retract <code>$possible</code> and replace it
      with the equivalent, new <code>ResolvedCellValue</code>.</para>

      <para>Rules #7 and #8 act in the same way as Rule #2 but check for
      single <code>PossibleCellValues</code> in a given column and a given
      zone of the grid, respectively.</para>

      <para>Rule #9 represents the most complex currently implemented rule.
      This rule implements the logic that, if we know that a pair of given
      values can only occur in two cells on a specific row, (for example we
      have determined the values of 4 and 6 can only appear in the first row
      in cells [0,3] and [0,5]) and this pair of cells can not hold other 
      values, then, although we do not know which of the pair contains a 
      four and which contains a six, we do know that these two values must be
      in these two cells, and hence we can remove the possibility of them
      occuring anywhere else in the same row.</para>

<!--  TODO: more detail here and I think the  rule can be cleaned up in
      the DRL file before fully documenting  it. -->

      <para>Rules #10 and #11 act in the same way as rule #9 but check for the
      existance of only two possible values in a given column and zone,
      respectively.</para>

      <para>To solve harder grids, the rule set would need to be extended
      further with more complex rules that encapsulate more complex
      reasoning.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Suggestions for Future Developments</title>

      <para>There are a number of ways in which this example could be
      developed. The reader is encouraged to consider these as
      excercises.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Agenda groups are a great declarative tool for
          phased execution. In this example, it is easy to see we have two
          phases: "resolution" and "validation". Right now, they are executed
          by creating two separate rule bases, each for one "job".
          Presumably it would be better to define agenda groups for all the
          rules, spliting them in "resolution" rules and "validation" rules,
          all loaded in a single rule base. The engine executes resolution and
          right after that, executes validation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Auto-focus is a great way of handling exceptions
          to the regular rules execution. In our case, if we detect an
          inconsistency, either in the input data or in the resolution rules,
          why should we spend time continuing the execution if it will be
          invalid anyway? It is better to simply (and immediately)
          report the inconsistency as soon as it is found. To do that, since
          we now have a single rulebase with all rules, we simply need to
          define the auto-focus attribute for all rules validating puzzle
          consistency.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Logical insert: an inconsistency only exists while wrong data
          is in the working memory. As so, we could state that the
          validation rules logically insert inconsistencies and as soon as the
          offending data is retracted, the inconsistency no longer
          exists.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>session.iterateObjects()</code>: although a valid
          use case having a global list to add the found problems, I think
          it would be more
          interesting to ask the Stateful Session by the desired list of
          problems, using <code>session.iterateObjects( new ClassObjectFilter(
          Inconsistency.class ) ).</code> Having the inconsistency class
          can also allow us to paint in red the offending cells in the
          GUI.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>kcontext.getKnowledgeRuntime().halt()</code>: even
          reporting the error as soon as it is found, we need a way to tell
          the engine to stop   evaluating rules. We
          can do that creating a rule that, in the presence of inconsistencies,
          calls <code>halt()</code> to stop evaluation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Queries: looking at the method
          <code>getPossibleCellValues(int row, int col)</code> in
          <code>DroolsSudokuGridModel</code>, we see it iterating over all
          <code>CellValue</code> objects, looking for the few it wants. That
          is a great opportunity to demonstrate Drools queries. We just
          define a query to
          return the objects we want and iterate over it, cleanly and nicely.
          Other queries may be defined as needed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Globals as services: the main objective of this change is to
          attend the next proposed change , but it is nice by its own.
          In order to teach the use of globals as services, it
          would be nice to set up a callback, so that each rule that finds the
          <code>ResolvedCellValue</code> for a given cell can call, to
          notify and update the corresponding cell in the GUI, providing
          immediate feedback for
          the user. Also, the last found cell could have its number painted in
          a different color to facilitate the identification of the rules'
          conclusions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Step by step execution: now that we have immediate user
          feedback, we can make use of the restricted run feature in Drools,
          i.e., we could add a button in the GUI, that, when activated,
          causes the execution of a single rule, by calling
          <code>fireAllRules( 1 )</code>. This way, the user would see,
          step by step, what the engine is doing.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
