<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="../../">
    <title>Miss Manners and Benchmarking</title>

    <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Miss Manners
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.benchmark.manners.MannersBenchmark
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> manners.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Advanced walkthrough on the Manners benchmark, covers Depth conflict resolution in depth.</programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>Miss Manners is throwing a party and being the good host she wants
      to arrange good seating. Her initial design arranges everyone in male
      female pairs, but then she worries about people have things to talk
      about; what is a good host to do? So she decides to note the hobby of
      each guest so she can then arrange guests in not only male and female
      pairs but also ensure that a guest has someone to talk about a common
      hobby, from either their left or right side.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Miss Manners' Guests</title>

        <mediaobject>

          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="100%"
                     align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/MannersExample/guests_at_table.png"
                       format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <section>
        <title>BenchMarking</title>

        <para>5 benchmarks were established in the 1991 paper "Effects of
        Database Size on Rule System Performance: Five Case Studies" by Brant,
        Timothy Grose, Bernie Lofaso, &amp; Daniel P. Miranker.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Manners</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Uses a depth-first search approach to determine the
                seating arrangements of boy/girl and one common hobby for
                dinner guests</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Waltz</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>line labeling for simple scenes by constraint
                propagation</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>WaltzDB</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>More general version of Walts to be able to adapt to a
                database of facts</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ARP</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Route planner for a robotic air vehicle using the A*
                search algorithm</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Weavera</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>VLSI router for channels and boxes using a black-board
                technique</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Manners has become the de facto rule engine benchmark; however
        it's behavior is now well known and many engines optimize for this
        thus negating its usefulness as a benchmark which is why Waltz is
        becoming more favorable. These 5 benchmarks are also published at the
        University of Texas <ulink
        url="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/ftp/pub/ops5-benchmark-suite/">http://www.cs.utexas.edu/ftp/pub/ops5-benchmark-suite/</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Miss Manners Execution Flow</title>

        <para>After the first Seating arrangement has been assigned a
        depth-first recursion occurs which repeatedly assigns correct Seating
        arrangements until the last seat is assigned. Manners uses a Context
        instance to control execution flow; the activity diagram is
        partitioned to show the relation of the rule execution to the current
        Context state.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Manners Activity Diagram</title>

          <mediaobject>

            <imageobject>
		    <imagedata width="100%"
                     align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/MannersExample/manners_activity_diagram.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The Data and Results</title>

        <para>Before going deeper into the rules lets first take a look at the
        asserted data and the resulting Seating arrangement. The data is a
        simple set of 5 guests who should be arranged in male/female pairs
        with common hobbies.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">The Data</emphasis></para>

        <para>Each line of the results list is printed per execution of the
        "Assign Seat" rule. They key bit to notice is that each line has pid
        one greater than the last, the significance of this will be explained
        in t he "Assign Seating" rule description. The 'l' and the 'r' refer
        to the left and right, 's' is sean and 'n' is the guest name. In my
        actual implementation I used longer notation, 'leftGuestName', but
        this is not practice in a printed article. I found the notation of
        left and right preferable to the original OPS5 '1' and '2</para>

        <literallayout>(guest (name n1) (sex m) (hobby  h1)  )
(guest (name n2) (sex f) (hobby  h1)  )
(guest (name n2) (sex f) (hobby  h3)  )
(guest (name n3) (sex m) (hobby  h3)  )
(guest (name n4) (sex m) (hobby  h1)  )
(guest (name n4) (sex f) (hobby  h2)  )
(guest (name n4) (sex f) (hobby  h3)  )
(guest (name n5) (sex f) (hobby  h2)  )
(guest (name n5) (sex f) (hobby  h1)  )
(last_seat (seat 5)  )</literallayout>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">The Results</emphasis></para>

        <literallayout>[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5] 
[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=false, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4] 
[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=false, ls=2, ln=n4, rs=3, rn=n3] 
[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=false, ls=3, rn=n3, rs=4, rn=n2] 
[Seating id=5, pid=4, done=false, ls=4, ln=n2, rs=5, rn=n1]</literallayout>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Indepth look</title>

      <section>
        <title>Cheating</title>

        <para>Manners has been around a long time and is a contrived benchmark
        meant to exercise the cross product joins and agenda, many people not
        understanding this tweak the example to achieve better performance,
        making their use of the Manners benchmark pointless. Known cheats to
        Miss Manners are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using arrays for a guests hobbies, instead of asserting each
            one as a single fact. This massively reduces the cross
            products.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The altering of the sequence of data can also reducing the
            amount of matching increase execution speed</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Changing NOT CE (conditional element) such that the test
            algorithm only uses the "first-best-match". Basically, changing
            the test algorithm to backward chaining. the results are only
            comparable to other backward chaining rule engines or ports of
            Manners.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Removing the context so the rule engine matches the guests
            and seats pre-maturely. A proper port will prevent facts from
            matching using the context start.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Any change which prevents the rule engine from performing
            combinatorial pattern matching</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If no facts are retracted in the reasoning cycle, as a
            result of NOT CE, the port is incorrect.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Conflict Resolution</title>

        <para>Manners benchmark was written for OPS5 which has two conflict
        resolution strategies, LEX and MEA; LEX is a chain of several
        strategies including Salience, Recency, Complexity. The Recency part
        of the strategy drives the depth first (LIFO) firing order. The Clips
        manual documents the recency strategy as:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <attribution>Clips Reference Manual</attribution>

          <para>Every fact and instance is marked internally with a "time tag"
          to indicate its relative recency with respect to every other fact
          and instance in the system. The pattern entities associated with
          each rule activation are sorted in descending order for determining
          placement. An activation with a more recent pattern entities is
          placed before activations with less recent pattern entities. To
          determine the placement order of two activations, compare the sorted
          time tags of the two activations one by one starting with the
          largest time tags. The comparison should continue until one
          activation’s time tag is greater than the other activation’s
          corresponding time tag. The activation with the greater time tag is
          placed before the other activation on the agenda. If one activation
          has more pattern entities than the other activation and the compared
          time tags are all identical, then the activation with more time tags
          is placed before the other activation on the agenda.</para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>However Jess and Clips both use the Depth strategy, which is
        simpler and lighter, which Drools also adopted. The Clips manual
        documents the Depth strategy as:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <attribution>Clips Reference Manual</attribution>

          <para>Newly activated rules are placed above all rules of the same
          salience. For example, given that fact-a activates rule-1 and rule-2
          and fact-b activates rule-3 and rule-4, then if fact-a is asserted
          before fact-b, rule-3 and rule-4 will be above rule-1 and rule-2 on
          the agenda. However, the position of rule-1 relative to rule-2 and
          rule-3 relative to rule-4 will be arbitrary.</para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>The initial Drools implementation for the Depth strategy would
        not work for manners without the use of salience on the "make_path"
        rule, the Clips support team had this to say:</para>

        <blockquote>
          <attribution>Clips Support Forum</attribution>

          <para>The default conflict resolution strategy for CLIPS, depth, is
          different than the default conflict resolution strategy used by
          OPS5. Therefore if you directly translate an OPS5 program to CLIPS,
          but use the default depth conflict resolution strategy, you're only
          likely to get the correct behavior by coincidence. The lex and mea
          conflict resolution strategies are provided in CLIPS to allow you to
          quickly convert and correctly run an OPS5 program in CLIPS</para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>Investigation into the Clips code reveals there is undocumented
        functionality in the Depth strategy. There is an accumulated time tag
        used in this strategy; it's not an extensively fact by fact comparison
        as in the recency strategy, it simply adds the total of all the time
        tags for each activation and compares.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Assign First Seat</title>

        <para>Once the context is changed to START_UP Activations are created
        for all asserted Guests; because all Activations are created as the
        result of a single Working Memory action, they all have the same
        Activation time tag. The last asserted Guest would have a higher fact
        time tag and its Activation would fire, becuase it has the highest
        accumulated fact time tag. The execution order in this rule has little
        importance, but has a big impact in the rule "Assign Seat". The
        Activation fires and asserts the first Seating arrangement, a Path and
        then sets the Context's state to create Activation for "Assign
        Seat".</para>

        <programlisting>rule assignFirstSeat
    when
        context : Context( state == Context.START_UP )
        guest : Guest()
        count : Count()
    then
        String guestName = guest.getName();
        
        Seating seating =  new Seating( count.getValue(), 1, true, 1, guestName, 1, guestName);
        insert( seating );
        
        Path path = new Path( count.getValue(), 1, guestName );
        insert( path );
        
        modify( count ) { setValue ( count.getValue() + 1 )  }

		System.out.println( "assign first seat :  " + seating + " : " + path );

        modify( context ) {
            setState( Context.ASSIGN_SEATS )
        } 
end</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Assign Seat</title>

        <para>This rule determines each of the Seating arrangements. The Rule
        creates cross product solutions for ALL asserted Seating arrangements
        against ALL the asserted guests; accept against itself or any already
        assigned Chosen solutions.</para>

        <programlisting>rule findSeating
   when 
       context : Context( state == Context.ASSIGN_SEATS )
       $s      : Seating( pathDone == true )
       $g1     : Guest( name == $s.rightGuestName )
       $g2     : Guest( sex != $g1.sex, hobby == $g1.hobby )

       count   : Count()

       not ( Path( id == $s.id, guestName == $g2.name) )
       not ( Chosen( id == $s.id, guestName == $g2.name, hobby == $g1.hobby) )
   then
       int rightSeat = $s.getRightSeat();
       int seatId = $s.getId();
       int countValue = count.getValue();
       
       Seating seating = new Seating( countValue, seatId, false, rightSeat, $s.getRightGuestName(), rightSeat + 1, $g2.getName() );
       insert( seating );     
                            
       Path path = new Path( countValue, rightSeat + 1, $g2.getName()  );
       insert( path );
       
       Chosen chosen = new Chosen( seatId, $g2.getName(), $g1.getHobby() );
       insert( chosen  );

	   System.err.println( "find seating : " + seating + " : " + path + " : " + chosen);

       modify( count ) {setValue(  countValue + 1 )}        
       modify( context ) {setState( Context.MAKE_PATH )} 
end</programlisting>

        <para>However, as can be seen from the printed results shown earlier,
        it is essential that only the Seating with the highest pid cross
        product be chosen – yet how can this be possible if we have
        Activations, of the same time tag, for nearly all existing Seating and
        Guests. For example on the third iteration of "Assing Seat" these are
        the produced Activations, remember this is from a very small data set
        and with larger data sets there would be many more possible Activated
        Seating solutions, with multiple solutions per pid:</para>

        <literallayout>=&gt;[ActivationCreated(35): rule=findSeating 
[fid:19:33]:[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=true, ls=2, ln=n4, rs=3, rn=n3] 
[fid:4:4]:[Guest name=n3, sex=m, hobbies=h3] 
[fid:3:3]:[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h3]

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(35): rule=findSeating 
[fid:15:23]:[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4] 
[fid:5:5]:[Guest name=n4, sex=m, hobbies=h1] 
[fid:2:2]:[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h1] 

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(35): rule=findSeating 
[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5] 
[fid:9:9]:[Guest name=n5, sex=f, hobbies=h1] 
[fid:1:1]:[Guest name=n1, sex=m, hobbies=h1]</literallayout>

        <para>The creation of all these redundant Activations might seem
        pointless, but it must be remembered that Manners is not about good
        rule design; it's purposefully designed as a bad ruleset to fully
        stress test the cross product matching process and the agenda, which
        this clearly does. Notice that each Activation has the same time tag
        of 35, as they were all activated by the change in Context to
        ASSIGN_SEATS. With OPS5 and LEX it would correctly fire the Activation
        with the last asserted Seating. With Depth the accumulated fact time
        tag ensures the Activation with the last asserted Seating
        fires.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Make Path and Path Done</title>

        <para>"Make Path" must always fires before "Path Done". A Path is
        asserted for each Seating arrangement up to the last asserted Seating.
        Notice that "Path Done" is a subset of "Make Path", so how do we
        ensure that "Make Path" fires first?</para>

        <programlisting>rule makePath
    when 
        Context( state == Context.MAKE_PATH )
        Seating( seatingId:id, seatingPid:pid, pathDone == false )
        Path( id == seatingPid, pathGuestName:guestName, pathSeat:seat )
        not Path( id == seatingId, guestName == pathGuestName )
    then
        insert( new Path( seatingId, pathSeat, pathGuestName ) );
end</programlisting>

        <programlisting>rule pathDone
    when
        context : Context( state == Context.MAKE_PATH ) 
        seating : Seating( pathDone == false ) 
    then
        modify( seating ) {setPathDone( true )} 
        
		modify( context ) {setState( Context.CHECK_DONE)}
end</programlisting>

        <figure>
          <title>Rete Diagram</title>

          <mediaobject>

            <imageobject>
		    <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/MannersExample/make_path.png" format="PNG"
                         scalefit="1" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Both rules end up on the Agenda in conflict and with identical
        activation time tags, however the accumulate fact time tag is greater
        for "Make Path" so it gets priority.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Continue and Are We Done</title>

        <para>"Are We Done" only activates when the last seat is assigned, at
        which point both rules will be activated. For the same reason that
        "Make Path" always wins over "Path Done" "Are We Done" will take
        priority over "Continue".</para>

        <programlisting>rule areWeDone
    when
        context : Context( state == Context.CHECK_DONE ) 
        LastSeat( lastSeat: seat )
        Seating( rightSeat == lastSeat ) 
    then
        modify( context ) {setState(Context.PRINT_RESULTS )}
end
</programlisting>

        <programlisting>rule continue
    when
        context : Context( state == Context.CHECK_DONE ) 
    then
        modify( context ) {setState( Context.ASSIGN_SEATS )}
end
</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Output Summary</title>

      <literallayout><emphasis role="bold">Assign First seat</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5]
=&gt;[fid:14:14]:[Path id=1, seat=1, guest=n5]

==&gt;[ActivationCreated(16): rule=findSeating
[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5]
[fid:9:9]:[Guest name=n5, sex=f, hobbies=h1]
[fid:1:1]:[Guest name=n1, sex=m, hobbies=h1]

==&gt;[ActivationCreated(16): rule=findSeating
[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1 , pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5]
[fid:9:9]:[Guest name=n5, sex=f, hobbies=h1]
[fid:5:5]:[Guest name=n4, sex=m, hobbies=h1]*

<emphasis role="bold">Assign Seating</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:15:17] :[Seating id=2 , pid=1 , done=false, ls=1, lg=n5, rs=2, rn=n4]
=&gt;[fid:16:18]:[Path id=2, seat=2, guest=n4]
=&gt;[fid:17:19]:[Chosen id=1, name=n4, hobbies=h1]

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(21): rule=makePath 
[fid:15:17] : [Seating id=2, pid=1, done=false, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4]
[fid:14:14] : [Path id=1, seat=1, guest=n5]*

==&gt;[ActivationCreated(21): rule=pathDone
[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=false, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4]*

<emphasis role="bold">Make Path</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:18:22:[Path id=2, seat=1, guest=n5]]

<emphasis role="bold">Path Done</emphasis>

<emphasis role="bold">Continue Process</emphasis>
=&gt;[ActivationCreated(25): rule=findSeating
[fid:15:23]:[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4]
[fid:7:7]:[Guest name=n4, sex=f, hobbies=h3]
[fid:4:4] : [Guest name=n3, sex=m, hobbies=h3]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(25): rule=findSeating
[fid:15:23]:[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4]
[fid:5:5]:[Guest name=n4, sex=m, hobbies=h1]
[fid:2:2]:[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h1], [fid:12:20] : [Count value=3]

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(25): rule=findSeating
[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5]
[fid:9:9]:[Guest name=n5, sex=f, hobbies=h1]
[fid:1:1]:[Guest name=n1, sex=m, hobbies=h1]

<emphasis role="bold">Assign Seating</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:19:26]:[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=false, ls=2, lnn4, rs=3, rn=n3]]
=&gt;[fid:20:27]:[Path id=3, seat=3, guest=n3]]
=&gt;[fid:21:28]:[Chosen id=2, name=n3, hobbies=h3}]

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(30): rule=makePath
[fid:19:26]:[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=false, ls=2, ln=n4, rs=3, rn=n3]
[fid:18:22]:[Path id=2, seat=1, guest=n5]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(30): rule=makePath 
[fid:19:26]:[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=false, ls=2, ln=n4, rs=3, rn=n3]
[fid:16:18]:[Path id=2, seat=2, guest=n4]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(30): rule=done 
[fid:19:26]:[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=false, ls=2, ln=n4, rs=3, rn=n3]*

<emphasis role="bold">Make Path</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:22:31]:[Path id=3, seat=1, guest=n5]

<emphasis role="bold">Make Path </emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:23:32] [Path id=3, seat=2, guest=n4]

<emphasis role="bold">Path Done</emphasis>

<emphasis role="bold">Continue Processing</emphasis>
=&gt;[ActivationCreated(35): rule=findSeating
[fid:19:33]:[Seating id=3, pid=2, done=true, ls=2, ln=n4, rs=3, rn=n3]
[fid:4:4]:[Guest name=n3, sex=m, hobbies=h3]
[fid:3:3]:[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h3], [fid:12:29]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(35): rule=findSeating 
[fid:15:23]:[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4] 
[fid:5:5]:[Guest name=n4, sex=m, hobbies=h1]
[fid:2:2]:[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h1]

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(35): rule=findSeating 
[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5] 
[fid:9:9]:[Guest name=n5, sex=f, hobbies=h1], [fid:1:1] : [Guest name=n1, sex=m, hobbies=h1]

<emphasis role="bold">Assign Seating</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:24:36]:[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=false, ls=3, ln=n3, rs=4, rn=n2]]
=&gt;[fid:25:37]:[Path id=4, seat=4, guest=n2]]
=&gt;[fid:26:38]:[Chosen id=3, name=n2, hobbies=h3]

==&gt;[ActivationCreated(40): rule=makePath 
[fid:24:36]:[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=false, ls=3, ln=n3, rs=4, rn=n2]
[fid:23:32]:[Path id=3, seat=2, guest=n4]*

==&gt;[ActivationCreated(40): rule=makePath 
[fid:24:36]:[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=false, ls=3, ln=n3, rs=4, rn=n2] 
[fid:20:27]:[Path id=3, seat=3, guest=n3]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(40): rule=makePath 
[fid:24:36]:[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=false, ls=3, ln=n3, rs=4, rn=n2]
[fid:22:31]:[Path id=3, seat=1, guest=n5]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(40): rule=done 
[fid:24:36]:[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=false, ls=3, ln=n3, rs=4, rn=n2]*

<emphasis role="bold">Make Path </emphasis>
=&gt;fid:27:41:[Path id=4, seat=2, guest=n4]

<emphasis role="bold">Make Path</emphasis>
=&gt;fid:28:42]:[Path id=4, seat=1, guest=n5]]

<emphasis role="bold">Make Path</emphasis>
=&gt;fid:29:43]:[Path id=4, seat=3, guest=n3]]

<emphasis role="bold">Path Done</emphasis>

<emphasis role="bold">Continue  Processing</emphasis>
=&gt;[ActivationCreated(46): rule=findSeating 
[fid:15:23]:[Seating id=2, pid=1, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=2, rn=n4] 
[fid:5:5]:[Guest name=n4, sex=m, hobbies=h1], [fid:2:2]
[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h1]

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(46): rule=findSeating 
[fid:24:44]:[Seating id=4, pid=3, done=true, ls=3, ln=n3, rs=4, rn=n2]
[fid:2:2]:[Guest name=n2, sex=f, hobbies=h1]
[fid:1:1]:[Guest name=n1, sex=m, hobbies=h1]*

=&gt;[ActivationCreated(46): rule=findSeating 
[fid:13:13]:[Seating id=1, pid=0, done=true, ls=1, ln=n5, rs=1, rn=n5]
[fid:9:9]:[Guest name=n5, sex=f, hobbies=h1]
[fid:1:1]:[Guest name=n1, sex=m, hobbies=h1]

<emphasis role="bold">Assign Seating</emphasis>
=&gt;[fid:30:47]:[Seating id=5, pid=4, done=false, ls=4, ln=n2, rs=5, rn=n1]
=&gt;[fid:31:48]:[Path id=5, seat=5, guest=n1]
=&gt;[fid:32:49]:[Chosen id=4, name=n1, hobbies=h1]
</literallayout>
    </section>
  </section>
