<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="../../">
      <title>Pet Store Example</title>

      <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Pet Store 
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.PetStore
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> Java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> PetStore.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Demonstrate use of Agenda Groups, Global Variables and integration with a GUI,
including callbacks from within the rules
</programlisting>

      <para>The Pet Store example shows how to integrate Rules with a GUI,
      in this case a Swing based desktop application. Within the rules file,
      it demonstrates how to use Agenda groups and auto-focus to control
      which of a set of rules is allowed to fire at any given time. It also
      illustrates the mixing of the Java and MVEL dialects within the rules,
      the use of accumulate functions and the way of calling Java functions
      from within the ruleset.</para>

      <para>All of the Java code is contained in one file,
      <filename>PetStore.java</filename>, defining the following principal
      classes (in addition to several classes to handle Swing Events):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Petstore</code> contains the <code>main()</code>
          method that we will look at shortly.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>PetStoreUI</code> is responsible for creating and
          displaying the Swing based GUI. It contains several smaller
          classes, mainly for responding to various GUI events such as
          mouse button clicks.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>TableModel</code> holds the table data. Think of it
          as a JavaBean that extends the Swing class
          <code>AbstractTableModel</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>CheckoutCallback</code> allows the GUI to interact
          with the Rules.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Ordershow</code> keeps the items that we wish to
          buy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Purchase</code> stores details of the order and
          the products we are buying.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Product</code> is a JavaBean holding details of
          the product available for purchase, and its price.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Much of the Java code is either plain JavaBeans or Swing-based.
      Only a few Swing-related points will be discussed in this section,
      but a good tutorial about Swing components can be found at Sun's
      Swing website, in
      <ulink url="???">
      <uri>http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/uiswing/</uri>
      </ulink>.</para>

      <para>The pieces of Java code in <filename>Petstore.java</filename>
      that relate to rules and facts are shown below.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating the PetStore RuleBase in PetStore.main</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();

kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "PetStore.drl",
                                                    PetStore.class ),
              ResourceType.DRL );
KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages() );

// Create the stock.
Vector<Product> stock = new Vector<Product>();
stock.add( new Product( "Gold Fish", 5 ) );
stock.add( new Product( "Fish Tank", 25 ) );
stock.add( new Product( "Fish Food", 2 ) );

// A callback is responsible for populating the
// Working Memory and for firing all rules.
PetStoreUI ui = new PetStoreUI( stock,
                                new CheckoutCallback( kbase ) );
ui.createAndShowGUI();
]]></programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The code shown above loads the rules from a DRL file on the
      classpath. Unlike other examples where the facts are asserted and
      fired straight away, this example defers this step to later. The
      way it does this is via the second last line where a
      <code>PetStoreUI</code> object is created using a constructor 
      accepting the <code>Vector</code> object <code>stock</code>
      collecting our products, and an instance of
      the <code>CheckoutCallback</code> class containing the Rule Base
      that we have just loaded.</para>

      <para>The Java code that fires the rules is within the 
      <code>CheckoutCallBack.checkout()</code> method. This is triggered
      (eventually) when the Checkout button is pressed by the user.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Firing the Rules - extract from CheckoutCallBack.checkout()</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[public String checkout(JFrame frame, List<Product> items) {
    Order order = new Order();

    // Iterate through list and add to cart
    for ( Product p: items ) {
        order.addItem( new Purchase( order, p ) );
    }

    // Add the JFrame to the ApplicationData to allow for user interaction

    StatefulKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatefulKnowledgeSession();
    ksession.setGlobal( "frame", frame );
    ksession.setGlobal( "textArea", this.output );

    ksession.insert( new Product( "Gold Fish", 5 ) );
    ksession.insert( new Product( "Fish Tank", 25 ) );
    ksession.insert( new Product( "Fish Food", 2 ) );

    ksession.insert( new Product( "Fish Food Sample", 0 ) );

    ksession.insert( order );
    ksession.fireAllRules();

    // Return the state of the cart
    return order.toString();
}
]]></programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Two items get passed into this method. One is the handle to the
      <code>JFrame</code> Swing component surrounding the output text
      frame, at the bottom of the GUI. The second is a list of order items;
      this comes from the <code>TableModel</code> storing the information
      from the "Table" area at the top right section of the GUI.</para>

      <para>The for loop transforms the list of order items coming from the
      GUI into the <code>Order</code> JavaBean, also contained in the
      file <filename>PetStore.java</filename>. Note that it would be 
      possible to refer to the Swing dataset directly within the rules,
      but it is better coding practice to do it this way, using simple
      Java objects. It means that we are not tied to Swing if we wanted
      to transform the sample into a Web application.</para>

      <para>It is important to note that <emphasis>all state in this
      example is stored in the Swing components, and that the rules are
      effectively stateless.</emphasis> Each time the "Checkout" button is
      pressed, this code copies the contents of the Swing
      <code>TableModel</code> into the Session's Working Memory.</para>

      <para>Within this code, there are nine calls to the Working Memory.
      The first of these creates a new Working Memory, as a Stateful
      Knowledge Session from the Knowledge Base. Remember that we passed
      in this Knowledge Base when we created the <code>CheckoutCallBack</code>
      class in the <code>main()</code> method. The next two calls pass in
      two objects that we will hold as global variables in the rules: the
      Swing text area and the Swing frame used for writing messages.</para>

      <para>More inserts put information on products into the Working Memory,
      as well as the order list. The final call is the standard
      <code>fireAllRules()</code>. Next, we look at what this method causes
      to happen within the rules file.</para>
      
      <example>
        <title>Package, Imports, Globals and Dialect: extract from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting>package org.drools.examples

import org.drools.WorkingMemory
import org.drools.examples.PetStore.Order
import org.drools.examples.PetStore.Purchase
import org.drools.examples.PetStore.Product
import java.util.ArrayList
import javax.swing.JOptionPane;

import javax.swing.JFrame 
        
global JFrame frame 
global javax.swing.JTextArea textArea</programlisting>
      </example>
    
      <para>The first part of file <filename>PetStore.drl</filename>
      contains the standard package and import statements to make various
      Java classes available to the rules. New to us are the two globals
      <code>frame</code> and <code>textArea</code>. They hold references
      to the Swing components <code>JFrame</code> and <code>JTextArea</code>
      components that were previously passed on by the Java code calling
      the <code>setGlobal()</code> method. Unlike  variables in rules,
      which expire as soon as the rule has fired, global variables retain
      their value for the lifetime of the Session.</para>

      <para>The next extract from the file <filename>PetStore.drl</filename>
      contains two functions that are referenced by the rules that we will
      look at shortly.</para>
      
      <example>
        <title>Java Functions in the Rules: extract from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[function void doCheckout(JFrame frame, WorkingMemory workingMemory) {
    Object[] options = {"Yes",
                        "No"};
                            
    int n = JOptionPane.showOptionDialog(frame,
        "Would you like to checkout?",
        "",
        JOptionPane.YES_NO_OPTION,
        JOptionPane.QUESTION_MESSAGE,
        null,
        options,
        options[0]);

    if (n == 0) {
        workingMemory.setFocus( "checkout" );
    }   
}

function boolean requireTank(JFrame frame, WorkingMemory workingMemory, Order order, Product fishTank, int total) {
    Object[] options = {"Yes",
                        "No"};
                            
    int n = JOptionPane.showOptionDialog(frame,
        "Would you like to buy a tank for your " + total + " fish?",
        "Purchase Suggestion",
        JOptionPane.YES_NO_OPTION,
        JOptionPane.QUESTION_MESSAGE,
        null,
        options,
        options[0]);
                                             
    System.out.print( "SUGGESTION: Would you like to buy a tank for your "
                      + total + " fish? - " );

    if (n == 0) {
        Purchase purchase = new Purchase( order, fishTank );
        workingMemory.insert( purchase );
        order.addItem( purchase );
        System.out.println( "Yes" );
    } else {
        System.out.println( "No" );
    }      
    return true;
}
]]></programlisting>
      </example>
  

      <para>Having these functions in the rules file just makes the Pet Store
      example more compact. In real life you probably have the functions
      in a file of their own, within the same rules package, or as a
      static method on a standard Java class, and import them, using
      <code>import function my.package.Foo.hello</code>.</para>

      <para>The purpose of these two functions is:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>doCheckout()</code> displays a dialog asking users
          whether they wish to checkout. If they do, focus is set to the
          <code>checkOut</code> agenda-group, allowing rules in that group
          to (potentially) fire.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>requireTank()</code> displays a dialog asking
          users whether they wish to buy a tank. If so, a new fish tank
          <code>Product</code> is added to the order list in Working
          Memory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>We'll see the rules that call these functions later on. The
      next set of examples are from the Pet Store rules themselves. The
      first extract is the one that happens to fire first, partly because
      it has the <kw>auto-focus</kw> attribute set to true.</para>
        
      <example>
        <title>Putting items into working memory: extract from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[// Insert each item in the shopping cart into the Working Memory 
// Insert each item in the shopping cart into the Working Memory
rule "Explode Cart"
    agenda-group "init"
    auto-focus true
    salience 10
    dialect "java"
when
    $order : Order( grossTotal == -1 )
    $item : Purchase() from $order.items
then
    insert( $item );
    kcontext.getKnowledgeRuntime().getAgenda().getAgendaGroup( "show items" ).setFocus();
    kcontext.getKnowledgeRuntime().getAgenda().getAgendaGroup( "evaluate" ).setFocus();
end]]></programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>This rule matches against all orders that do not yet have their
      <code>grossTotal</code> calculated . It loops for each purchase item
      in that order. Some parts of the "Explode Cart" rule should be familiar:
      the rule name, the salience (suggesting the order for the rules being
      fired) and the dialect set to <code>"java"</code>. There are three
      new features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><kw>agenda-group</kw> <code>"init"</code> defines the name
           of the agenda group. In this case, there is only one rule in the
           group. However, neither the Java code nor a rule consequence sets
           the focus to this group, and therefore it relies on the next
           attibute for its chance to fire.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><kw>auto-focus</kw> <code>true</code> ensures that this rule,
          while being the only rule in the agenda group, gets a chance to fire
          when <code>fireAllRules()</code> is called from the Java code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>kcontext....setFocus()</code> sets the focus to the
          <code>"show items"</code> and <code>"evaluate"</code> agenda groups
          in turn, permitting their rules to fire. In practice, we loop
          through all items on the order, inserting them into memory, then
          firing the other rules after each insert.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The next two listings show the rules within the
      <code>"show items"</code> and <code>evaluate</code> agenda groups.
      We look at them in the order that they are called.</para>
        
      <example>
        <title>Show Items in the GUI - extract from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[rule "Show Items"
    agenda-group "show items"
    dialect "mvel"
when
    $order : Order( )
    $p : Purchase( order == $order )
then
   textArea.append( $p.product + "\n");
end
]]></programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The <code>"show items"</code> agenda-group has only one rule,
      called "Show Items" (note the difference in case). For each purchase
      on the order currently in the Working Memory (or Session), it logs
      details to the text area at the bottom of the GUI. The
      <code>textArea</code> variable used to do this is one of the global
      variables we looked at earlier.</para>

      <para>The <code>evaluate</code> Agenda group also gains focus from
      the <code>"Explode Cart"</code> rule listed previously. This
      Agenda group has two rules, <code>"Free Fish Food Sample"</code> and
      <code>"Suggest Tank"</code>, shown below.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Evaluate Agenda Group: extract from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[// Free Fish Food sample when we buy a Gold Fish if we haven't already bought 
// Fish Food and don't already have a Fish Food Sample
rule "Free Fish Food Sample"
    agenda-group "evaluate"
    dialect "mvel"
when
    $order : Order()
    not ( $p : Product( name == "Fish Food") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    not ( $p : Product( name == "Fish Food Sample") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    exists ( $p : Product( name == "Gold Fish") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    $fishFoodSample : Product( name == "Fish Food Sample" );
then
    System.out.println( "Adding free Fish Food Sample to cart" );
    purchase = new Purchase($order, $fishFoodSample);
    insert( purchase );
    $order.addItem( purchase ); 
end

// Suggest a tank if we have bought more than 5 gold fish and don't already have one
rule "Suggest Tank"
    agenda-group "evaluate"
    dialect "java"
when
    $order : Order()
    not ( $p : Product( name == "Fish Tank") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    ArrayList( $total : size &gt; 5 ) from collect( Purchase( product.name == "Gold Fish" ) )
    $fishTank : Product( name == "Fish Tank" )
then
    requireTank(frame, drools.getWorkingMemory(), $order, $fishTank, $total); 
end
]]></programlisting>
      </example>
      

      <para>The rule <code>"Free Fish Food Sample"</code> will only fire if</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>we <emphasis>don't </emphasis>already have any fish food, <emphasis>and</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>we <emphasis>don't</emphasis> already have a free fish food sample,
          <emphasis>and</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>we <emphasis>do</emphasis> have a Gold Fish in our order.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the rule does fire, it creates a new product (Fish Food Sample), and adds it to the
      order in Working Memory.</para>

      <para>The rule <code>"Suggest Tank"</code> will only fire if</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>we <emphasis>don't </emphasis>already have a Fish Tank in our order,
          <emphasis>and</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>we <emphasis>do</emphasis> have more than 5 Gold Fish Products
          in our order.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If the rule does fire, it calls the <code>requireTank()</code> function
      that we looked at earlier (showing a Dialog to the user, and adding a Tank to
      the order / working memory if confirmed). When calling the
      <emphasis role="italic">requireTank</emphasis>() function the rule passes
      the global <emphasis role="italic">frame</emphasis> variable so that the
      function has a handle to the Swing GUI.</para>

      <para>The next rule we look at is <code>"do checkout"</code>.</para>
        
      <example>
        <title>Doing the Checkout - extract (6) from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting>rule "do checkout"
    dialect "java"
    when
    then
        doCheckout(frame, drools.getWorkingMemory());
end</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The rule <code>"do checkout"</code> has <emphasis role="bold">no
      agenda group set and no auto-focus attribute</emphasis>. As such, is is
      deemed part of the default (MAIN) agenda group. This group gets focus by
      default when all the rules in agenda-groups that explicity had focus set
      to them have run their course.</para>

      <para>There is no LHS to the rule, so the RHS will always call the
      <code>doCheckout()</code> function. When calling the
      <code>doCheckout()</code> function, the rule passes the global
      <code>frame</code> variable to give the function a handle to the Swing GUI.
      As we saw earlier, the <code>doCheckout()</code> function shows a
      confirmation dialog to the user. If confirmed, the function sets the focus
      to the <emphasis role="italic">checkout</emphasis> agenda-group, allowing
      the next lot of rules to fire.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Checkout Rules: extract from PetStore.drl</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[rule "Gross Total"
    agenda-group "checkout"
    dialect "mvel"
when
   $order : Order( grossTotal == -1)
   Number( total : doubleValue )
       from accumulate( Purchase( $price : product.price ), sum( $price ) )
then
    modify( $order ) { grossTotal = total };
    textArea.append( "\ngross total=" + total + "\n" );
end

rule "Apply 5% Discount"
    agenda-group "checkout"
dialect "mvel"
when
   $order : Order( grossTotal &gt;= 10 &amp;&amp; &lt; 20 )
then
   $order.discountedTotal = $order.grossTotal * 0.95;
   textArea.append( "discountedTotal total=" + $order.discountedTotal + "\n" );
end


rule "Apply 10% Discount"
    agenda-group "checkout"
    dialect "mvel"
when
   $order : Order( grossTotal &gt;= 20 )
then
   $order.discountedTotal = $order.grossTotal * 0.90;
   textArea.append( "discountedTotal total=" + $order.discountedTotal + "\n" );
end
]]></programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>There are three rules in the <emphasis role="italic">checkout</emphasis> agenda-group:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If we haven't already calculated the gross total,
          <code>Gross Total</code> accumulates the product prices into a total,
          puts this total into Working Memory, and displays it via the Swing
          <code>JTextArea</code>, using the <code>textArea</code> global
          variable yet again.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If our gross total is between 10 and 20, 
          <code>"Apply 5% Discount"</code> calculates the discounted total and
          adds it to the Working Memory and displays it in the text area.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If our gross total is not less than 20, 
          <code>"Apply 10% Discount"</code> calculates the discounted total and
          adds it to the Working Memory and displays it in the text area.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>Now that we've run through what happens in the code, let's have a
      look at what happens when we actually run the code. The file
      <filename>PetStore.java</filename> contains a <code>main()</code> method,
      so that it can be run as a standard Java application, either from the
      command line or via the IDE. This assumes you have your classpath set
      correctly. (See the start of the examples section for more information.)</para>

      <para>The first screen that we see is the Pet Store Demo. It has a list
      of available products (top left), an empty list of selected products
      (top right), checkout and reset buttons (middle) and an empty system
      messages area (bottom).</para>

      <figure>
        <title>PetStore Demo just after Launch</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetStoreExample/1-PetStore-Start-Screen.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <para>To get to this point, the following things have happened:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>main()</code> method has run and loaded the Rule Base
          <emphasis>but not yet fired the rules</emphasis>. So far, this is the
          only code in connection with rules that has been run.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A new <code>PetStoreUI</code> object has been created and given a
          handle to the Rule Base, for later use.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Various Swing components do their stuff, and the above screen
          is shown and <emphasis>waits for user input</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      
      <para>Clicking on various products from the list might give you a
      screen similar to the one below.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>PetStore Demo with Products Selected</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetStoreExample/2-stock-added-to-order-list.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <para>Note that <emphasis>no rules code has been fired here</emphasis>. This
      is only Swing code, listening for mouse click events, and adding some
      selected product to the <code>TableModel</code> object for display in the
      top right hand section. (As an aside, note that this is a classic use of
      the Model View Controller design pattern).</para>

      <para>It is only when we press the "Checkout" button that we fire our
      business rules, in roughly the same order that we walked through the
      code earlier.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Method <code>CheckOutCallBack.checkout()</code> is called
          (eventually) by the Swing class waiting for the click on the
          "Checkout" button. This inserts the data from the
          <code>TableModel</code> object (top right hand side of the GUI),
          and inserts it into the Session's Working Memory. It then fires
          the rules.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>"Explode Cart"</code> rule is the first to fire,
          given that it has <kw>auto-focus</kw> set to true. It loops through
          all the products in the cart, ensures that the products are in the
          Working Memory, and then gives the <code>"Show Items"</code> and
          <code>Evaluation</code> agenda groups a chance to fire. The rules
          in these groups add the contents of the cart to the text area
          (at the bottom of the window), decide whether or not to give us free
          fish food, and to ask us whether we want to buy a fish tank. This
          is shown in the figure below.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Do we want to buy a fish tank?</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetStoreExample/3-purchase-suggestion.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis role="italic">Do Checkout</emphasis> rule is the next to fire as it (a) No other agenda group currently has focus and (b) it is part of the default (MAIN) agenda group. It always calls the<emphasis role="italic"> doCheckout() function </emphasis>which displays a 'Would you like to Checkout?' Dialog Box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>doCheckout()</code> function sets the focus to the
          <code>checkout</code> agenda-group, giving the rules in that group
          the option to fire.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The rules in the the <code>checkout</code> agenda-group display
          the contents of the cart and apply the appropriate discount.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Swing then waits for user input</emphasis> to either
          checkout more products (and to cause the rules to fire again), or to
          close the GUI - see the figure below.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Petstore Demo after all rules have fired.</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetStoreExample/4-Petstore-final-screen.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>We could add more System.out calls to demonstrate this flow of
      events. The output, as it currently appears in the Console window, is
      given in the listing below.</para>
  
      <example>
        <title>Console (System.out) from running the PetStore GUI</title>

        <programlisting>Adding free Fish Food Sample to cart 
SUGGESTION: Would you like to buy a tank for your 6 fish? - Yes</programlisting>
      </example>
     

      <!---<para>Todo : Add Audit and Agenda Views for this sample.</para>-->
    </section>
