<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="../../">
    <title>Conway's Game Of Life</title>

    <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Conway's Game Of Life
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.conway.ConwayAgendaGroupRun
            org.drools.examples.conway.ConwayRuleFlowGroupRun
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> Java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> conway-ruleflow.drl conway-agendagroup.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Demonstrates 'accumulate', 'collect' and 'from'</programlisting>

    <para>Conway's Game Of Life, described in <ulink
    url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway's_Game_of_Life">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway's_Game_of_Life</ulink> and in
    <ulink
    url="http://www.math.com/students/wonders/life/life.html">http://www.math.com/students/wonders/life/life.html</ulink>,
    is a famous cellular automaton conceived in the early 1970's by the
    mathematician John Conway. While the system is well known as "Conway's
    Game Of Life", it really isn't a game at all. Conway's system is more like
    a simulation of a form of life. Don't be intimidated. The system
    is terribly simple and terribly interesting. Math and Computer Science
    students alike have marvelled over Conway's system for more than 30 years
    now. The application
    presented here is a Swing-based implementation of Conway's Game of Life.
    The rules that govern the system are implemented as business rules using
    Drools. This document will explain the rules that drive the simulation and
    discuss the Drools parts of the implementation.</para>

    <para>We'll first introduce the grid view, shown below, designed for the
    visualisation of the game, showing the "arena" where the life simuation
    takes place. Initially the grid is empty, meaning that there are no live
    cells in the system. Each cell is either alive or dead, with live cells
    showing a green ball. Preselected patterns of live cells can be
    chosen from the "Pattern" drop-down list. Alternatively, individual
    cells can be doubled-clicked to toggle them between live and dead. It's
    important to understand that each cell is related to its neighboring cells,
    which is fundamental for the game's rules. Neighbors include not only
    cells to the left, right, top and bottom but also cells that are connected
    diagonally, so that each cell has a total of 8 neighbors. Exceptions
    are the four corner cells which have only three neighbors, and the cells
    along the four border, with five neighbors each.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: Starting a new game</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
		<imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/ConwaysGameOfLifeExample/conway1.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>So what are the basic rules that govern this game? Its goal is to
    show the development of a population, generation by generation. Each
    generation results from the preceding one, based on the simultaneous
    evaluation of all cells. This is the simple set of rules that
    govern what the next generation will look like:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a live cell has fewer than 2 live neighbors, it dies of
        loneliness.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If a live cell has more than 3 live neighbors, it dies from
        overcrowding.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If a dead cell has exactly 3 live neighbors, it comes to
        life.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>That is all there is to it. Any cell that doesn't meet any of those
    criteria is left as is for the next generation. With those simple rules in
    mind, go back and play with the system a little bit more and step through
    some generations, one at a time, and notice these rules taking their
    effect.</para>

    <para>The screenshot below shows an example generation, with a number of
    live cells. Don't worry about matching the exact patterns represented in
    the screen shot. Just get some groups of cells added to the grid. Once you
    have groups of live cells in the grid, or select a pre-designed pattern,
    click the "Next Generation" button and notice what happens. Some of the
    live cells are killed (the green ball disappears) and some dead cells come
    to life (a green ball appears). Step through several generations and see
    if you notice any patterns. If you click on the "Start" button, the system
    will evolve itself so you don't need to click the "Next Generation" button
    over and over. Play with the system a little and then come back here for
    more details of how the application works.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: A running game</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
		<imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/ConwaysGameOfLifeExample/conway2.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Now lets delve into the code. As this is an advanced example we'll
    assume that by now you know your way around the Drools framework and are
    able to connect the presented highlight, so that we'll just focus at a
    high level overview. The example has two ways to execute, one way 
    uses Agenda Groups to manage execution flow, and the other one uses
    Rule Flow Groups to manage execution flow. These two versions are
    implemented in <code>ConwayAgendaGroupRun</code> and
    <code>ConwayRuleFlowGroupRun</code>, respectively. Here,
    we'll discuss the Rule Flow version, as it's what most people will
    use.</para>

    <para>All the <code>Cell</code> objects are inserted into the Session
    and the rules in the <kw>ruleflow-group</kw> "register neighbor" are
    allowed to execute by the Rule Flow process. This group of four rules
    creates <code>Neighbor</code> relations between some cell and its
    northeastern, northern, northwestern and western neighbors. This
    relation is bidirectional, which takes care of the other four directions.
    Border cells don't need any special treatment - they simply won't be
    paired with neighboring cells where there isn't any. By
    the time all activations have fired for these rules, all cells are related
    to all their neighboring cells.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: Register Cell Neighbour relations</title>

      <programlisting>rule "register north east"
    ruleflow-group "register neighbor"
when
    $cell: Cell( $row : row, $col : col )            
    $northEast : Cell( row  == ($row - 1), col == ( $col + 1 ) )    
then                    
    insert( new Neighbor( $cell, $northEast ) );
    insert( new Neighbor( $northEast, $cell ) );        
end

rule "register north"
    ruleflow-group "register neighbor"  
when
    $cell: Cell( $row : row, $col : col )   
    $north : Cell( row  == ($row - 1), col == $col )    
then        
    insert( new Neighbor( $cell, $north ) );
    insert( new Neighbor( $north, $cell ) );        
end

rule "register north west"
    ruleflow-group "register neighbor"
when
    $cell: Cell( $row : row, $col : col )           
    $northWest : Cell( row  == ($row - 1), col == ( $col - 1 ) )                        
then        
    insert( new Neighbor( $cell, $northWest ) );
    insert( new Neighbor( $northWest, $cell ) );        
end

rule "register west"
    ruleflow-group "register neighbor"
when
    $cell: Cell( $row : row, $col : col )          
    $west : Cell( row  == $row, col == ( $col - 1 ) )                       
then        
    insert( new Neighbor( $cell, $west ) );
    insert( new Neighbor( $west, $cell ) );         
end</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Once all the cells are inserted, some Java code applies the pattern
    to the grid, setting certain cells to Live. Then, when the user clicks
    "Start" or "Next Generation", it executes the "Generation" ruleflow. This
    ruleflow is responsible for the management of all changes of cells in each
    generation cycle.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: rule flow "Generation"</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/ConwaysGameOfLifeExample/conway_ruleflow_generation.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The rule flow process first enters the "evaluate" group, which means
    that any active rule in the group can fire. The rules in this group apply
    the Game-of-Life rules discussed in the beginning of the example,
    determining the cells to be killed and the ones to be given life. We use
    the "phase" attribute to drive the reasoning of the Cell by specific
    groups of rules; typically the phase is tied to a Rule Flow Group in the
    Rule Flow process definition. Notice that it doesn't actually change the
    state of any <code>Cell</code> objectss at this point; this is because 
    it's evaluating the grid in turn and it must complete the full evaluation
    until those changes can be applied. To achieve this, it sets the cell to
    a "phase" which is either <code>Phase.KILL</code> or
    <code>Phase.BIRTH</code>, used later to control actions applied
    to the <code>Cell</code> object.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: Evaluate Cells with state changes</title>

      <programlisting>rule "Kill The Lonely"
    ruleflow-group "evaluate"
    no-loop
when
#   A live cell has fewer than 2 live neighbors
    theCell: Cell( liveNeighbors &lt; 2, cellState == CellState.LIVE,
                   phase == Phase.EVALUATE )
then
    modify( theCell ){
        setPhase( Phase.KILL );
    }
end

rule "Kill The Overcrowded"
    ruleflow-group "evaluate"
    no-loop
when
#   A live cell has more than 3 live neighbors
    theCell: Cell( liveNeighbors &gt; 3, cellState == CellState.LIVE,
                   phase == Phase.EVALUATE )
then
    modify( theCell ){
        setPhase( Phase.KILL );
    }
end

rule "Give Birth"
    ruleflow-group "evaluate"
    no-loop
when
#   A dead cell has 3 live neighbors
    theCell: Cell( liveNeighbors == 3, cellState == CellState.DEAD,
                   phase == Phase.EVALUATE )
then
    modify( theCell ){
        theCell.setPhase( Phase.BIRTH );
    }
end
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Once all <code>Cell</code> objects in the grid have been evaluated,
    we first clear any calculation activations that occured from any previous
    data changes. This is done via the "reset calculate" rule, which clears
    any activations in the "calculate" group. We then enter a split in the
    rule flow which allows any activations in both the "kill" and the "birth"
    group to fire. These rules are responsible for applying the state
    change.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: Apply the state changes</title>

      <programlisting>rule "reset calculate"
    ruleflow-group "reset calculate"
when
then
    WorkingMemory wm = drools.getWorkingMemory();
    wm.clearRuleFlowGroup( "calculate" );
end

rule "kill"
    ruleflow-group "kill"
    no-loop
when
    theCell: Cell( phase == Phase.KILL )
then
    modify( theCell ){
        setCellState( CellState.DEAD ),
        setPhase( Phase.DONE );   
    }
end 
 
rule "birth"
    ruleflow-group "birth"
    no-loop
when
    theCell: Cell( phase == Phase.BIRTH )
then
    modify( theCell ){
        setCellState( CellState.LIVE ),
        setPhase( Phase.DONE );
    }
end </programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>At this stage, a number of <code>Cell</code> objects have been
    modified with the state changed to either <code>LIVE</code> or
    <code>DEAD</code>. Now we get to see the power of the
    <code>Neighbor</code> facts defining the cell relations. When a cell
    becomes live or dead, we use the <code>Neighbor</code> relation to
    iterate over all surrounding cells, increasing or decreasing the
    <code>liveNeighbor</code> count. Any cell that has its count changed
    is also set to to the <code>EVALUATE</code> phase, to make sure
    it is included in the reasoning during the evaluation stage of the
    Rule Flow Process. Notice that we don't have to do any iteration
    ourselves; simply by applying the relations in the rules we make
    the rule engine do all the hard work for us, with a minimal amount of
    code. Once the live count has been determined and set for all cells,
    the Rule Flow Process comes to and end. If the user has initially
    clicked the "Start" button, the engine will restart the rule flow;
    otherwise the user may request another generation.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Conway's Game of Life: Evaluate cells with state changes</title>

      <programlisting>rule "Calculate Live"
    ruleflow-group "calculate"
    lock-on-active  
when
    theCell: Cell( cellState == CellState.LIVE )
    Neighbor( cell == theCell, $neighbor : neighbor ) 
then
    modify( $neighbor ){
        setLiveNeighbors( $neighbor.getLiveNeighbors() + 1 ),
        setPhase( Phase.EVALUATE );   
    }
end 

rule "Calculate Dead"
    ruleflow-group "calculate"
    lock-on-active  
when
    theCell: Cell( cellState == CellState.DEAD )
    Neighbor( cell == theCell, $neighbor : neighbor )
then
    modify( $neighbor ){
        setLiveNeighbors( $neighbor.getLiveNeighbors() - 1 ),
        setPhase( Phase.EVALUATE );
    }
end </programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>
