<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
                    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:base="../../">
			<title>Pet Store Example</title>

			<programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Pet Store 
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.PetStore
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> Java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> PetStore.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Demonstrate use of Agenda Groups, Global Variables and integration with a GUI (including callbacks from within the Rules)
</programlisting>

			<para>The Pet Store example shows how to integrate Rules with a GUI (in this case a Swing based Desktop application). Within the rules file, it shows how to use agenda groups and auto-focus to control which of a set of rules is allowed to fire at any given time. It also shows mixing of Java and MVEL dialects within the rules, the use of accumulate functions and calling of Java functions from within the ruleset.</para>

			<para>Like the rest of the the samples, all the Java Code is contained in one file. The PetStore.java contains the following principal classes (in addition to several minor classes to handle Swing Events)</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic"> Petstore</emphasis> - containing the main() method that we will look at shortly.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">PetStoreUI</emphasis> - responsible for creating and displaying the Swing based GUI. It contains several smaller classes , mainly for responding to various GUI events such as mouse and button clicks.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">TabelModel</emphasis> - for holding the table data. Think of it as a JavaBean that extends the Swing AbstractTableModel class.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">CheckoutCallback</emphasis> - Allows the GUI to interact with the Rules.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">Ordershow </emphasis> - the items that we wish to buy.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">Purchase</emphasis> - Details of the order and the products we are buying.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">Product</emphasis> - JavaBean holding details of the product available for purchase, and it's price.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>Much of the Java code is either JavaBeans (simple enough to understand) or Swing based. We will touch on some Swing related points in the this tutorial , but a good place to get more Swing component information is <ulink url="???"><uri>http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/uiswing/</uri> available at the Sun Swing website.<citebiblioid /></ulink></para>

			<para>There are two important Rules related pieces of Java code in <emphasis role="italic">Petstore.java</emphasis>.</para>

			<example>
				<title>Creating the PetStore RuleBase - extract from PetStore.java main() method</title>

				<programlisting>PackageBuilder builder = new PackageBuilder();
builder.addPackageFromDrl( new InputStreamReader( 
PetStore.class.getResourceAsStream( "PetStore.drl" ) ) );
RuleBase ruleBase = RuleBaseFactory.newRuleBase();
ruleBase.addPackage( builder.getPackage() );

//RuleB
Vector stock = new Vector();
stock.add( new Product( "Gold Fish",5 ) );
stock.add( new Product( "Fish Tank", 25 ) );
stock.add( new Product( "Fish Food", 2 ) );

//The callback is responsible for populating working memory and
// fireing all rules
PetStoreUI ui = new PetStoreUI( stock, new CheckoutCallback( ruleBase ) );
ui.createAndShowGUI();
</programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>This code above loads the rules (drl) file from the classpath. Unlike other examples where the facts are asserted and fired straight away, this example defers this step to later. The way it does this is via the second last line where the PetStoreUI is created using a constructor the passes in the Vector called stock containing products, and an instance of the CheckoutCallback class containing the RuleBase that we have just loaded.</para>

			<para>The actual Javacode that fires the rules is within the <emphasis role="italic">CheckoutCallBack.checkout()</emphasis> method. This is triggered (eventually) when the 'Checkout' button is pressed by the user.</para>

			<example>
				<title>Firing the Rules - extract from the CheckOutCallBack.checkout() method</title>

				<programlisting>public String checkout(JFrame frame, List items) throws FactException {           
    Order order = new Order();

    //Iterate through list and add to cart
    for ( int i = 0; i &lt; items.size(); i++ ) {
        order.addItem( new Purchase( order, (Product) items.get( i ) ) );
    }

    //add the JFrame to the ApplicationData to allow for user interaction
    WorkingMemory workingMemory = ruleBase.newStatefulSession();
    workingMemory.setGlobal( "frame", frame );
    workingMemory.setGlobal( "textArea",  this.output );

    workingMemory.insert( new Product( "Gold Fish", 5 ) );
    workingMemory.insert( new Product( "Fish Tank", 25 ) );
    workingMemory.insert( new Product( "Fish Food",  2 ) );
    workingMemory.insert( new Product( "Fish Food Sample", 0 ) );            
           
    workingMemory.insert( order );
    workingMemory.fireAllRules();

    //returns the state of the cart
    return order.toString();
}
</programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>Two items get passed into this method; A handle to the JFrame Swing Component surrounding the output text frame (bottom of the GUI if / when you run the component). The second item is a list of order items; this comes from the TableModel the stores the information from the 'Table' area at the top right section of the GUI.</para>

			<para>The <emphasis role="italic">for()</emphasis> loop transforms the list of order items coming from the GUI into the Order JavaBean (also contained in the PetStore.java file). Note that it would be possible to refer to the Swing dataset directly within the rules, but it is better coding practice to do it this way (using Simple Java Objects). It means that we are not tied to Swing if we wanted to transform the sample into a Web application.</para>

			<para>It is important to note that <emphasis role="bold">all state in this example is stored in the Swing components, and that the rules are effectively stateless. </emphasis>Each time the 'Checkout' button is pressed, this code copies the contents of the Swing <emphasis>TableModel</emphasis> into the Session / Working Memory.</para>

			<para>Within this code, there are nine calls to the working memory. The first of these creates a new workingMemory (statefulSession) from the Rulebase - remember that we passed in this Rulebase when we created the CheckoutCallBack class in the <emphasis role="italic">main()</emphasis> method. The next two calls pass in two objects that we will hold as Global variables in the rules - the Swing text area and Swing frame that we will use for writing messages later.</para>

			<para>More inserts put information on products into the working memory, as well as the order list. The final call is the standard <emphasis role="italic">fireAllRules()</emphasis>. Next, we look at what this method causes to happen within the Rules file.</para>
			
			<example>
				<title>Package, Imports , Globals and Dialect - extract (1) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>package org.drools.examples

import org.drools.WorkingMemory
import org.drools.examples.PetStore.Order
import org.drools.examples.PetStore.Purchase
import org.drools.examples.PetStore.Product
import java.util.ArrayList
import javax.swing.JOptionPane;

import javax.swing.JFrame 
        
global JFrame frame 
global javax.swing.JTextArea textArea
 
dialect "mvel"
</programlisting>
			</example>
    
			<para>The first part of the <emphasis role="italic">PetStore.drl</emphasis> file contains the standard package and import statement to make various Java classes available to the rules. We've seen the dialect been defaulted to "mvel" before in other examples. What is new are the two globals <emphasis>frame and textArea. </emphasis>These hold references to the Swing JFrame and Textarea components that were previous passed by the Java code calling the <emphasis>setGlobal() </emphasis>method. Unlike normal variables in Rules , which expire as soon as the rule has fired, Global variables retain their value for the lifetime of the (Stateful in this case) Session.</para>

			<para>The next extract (below) is from the <emphasis role="bold">end</emphasis> of the PetStore.drl file. It contains two functions that are referenced by the rules that we will look at shortly.</para>
			
			<example>
				<title>Java Functions in the Rules - extract (2) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>function void doCheckout(JFrame frame, WorkingMemory workingMemory) {
    Object[] options = {"Yes",
                        "No"};
                            
    int n = JOptionPane.showOptionDialog(frame,
                                         "Would you like to checkout?",
                                         "",
                                         JOptionPane.YES_NO_OPTION,
                                         JOptionPane.QUESTION_MESSAGE,
                                         null,
                                         options,
                                         options[0]);

    if (n == 0) {
        workingMemory.setFocus( "checkout" );
    }   
}

function boolean requireTank(JFrame frame, WorkingMemory workingMemory, Order order, Product fishTank, int total) {
    Object[] options = {"Yes",
                        "No"};
                            
    int n = JOptionPane.showOptionDialog(frame,
                                         "Would you like to buy a tank for your " + total + " fish?",
                                         "Purchase Suggestion",
                                         JOptionPane.YES_NO_OPTION,
                                         JOptionPane.QUESTION_MESSAGE,
                                         null,
                                         options,
                                         options[0]);
                                             
    System.out.print( "SUGGESTION: Would you like to buy a tank for your "
                      + total + " fish? - " );

    if (n == 0) {
        Purchase purchase = new Purchase( order, fishTank );
        workingMemory.insert( purchase );
        order.addItem( purchase );
        System.out.println( "Yes" );
    } else {
        System.out.println( "No" );
    }      
    return true;
}
</programlisting>
			</example>
  

			<para>Having these functions in the rules file makes the PetStore sample more compact - in real life you probably have the functions in a file of their own (within the same rules package), or as a static method on a standard Java class (and import them using the <emphasis role="bold">import function my.package.Foo.hello </emphasis>syntax).</para>

			<para>The above functions are</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">doCheckout()</emphasis> - Displays a dialog asking the user if they wish to checkout. If they do, focus is set to the <emphasis role="italic">checkOut</emphasis> agenda-group, allowing rules in that group to (potentially) fire.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="italic">requireTank()</emphasis> - Displays a dialog asking the user if they wish to buy a tank. If so, a new FishTank <emphasis role="italic">Product</emphasis> added to the orderlist in working memory.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>We'll see later the rules that call these functions.The next set of examples are from the PetStore rules themselves. The first extract is the one that happens to fire first (partly because it has the <emphasis role="italic">auto-focus</emphasis> attibute set to true).</para>
				
			<example>
				<title>Putting each (individual) item into working memory - extract (3) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>// insert each item in the shopping cart into the Working Memory 
rule "Explode Cart"
    agenda-group "init"
    auto-focus true    
    salience 10
    dialect "java"
when
    $order : Order( grossTotal == -1 )
    $item : Purchase() from $order.items
then
   insert( $item );
   drools.setFocus( "show items" );
   drools.setFocus( "evaluate" );
end

</programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>This rule matches against all orders that do not yet have an Order.grossTotal calculated . It loops for each purchase item in that order. Some of the <emphasis role="italic">Explode Cart</emphasis> Rule should be familiar ; the rule name, the salience (suggesting of the order that the rules should be fired in) and the dialect set to <emphasis role="italic">java</emphasis>. There are three new items:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">agenda-group "init" </emphasis>- the name of the agenda group. In this case, there is only one rule in the group. However, nothing in Java code / nor a rule sets the focus to this group , so it relies on the next attibute for it's chance to fire.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">auto-focus true - </emphasis>This is the only rule in the sample, so when <emphasis role="italic">fireAllRules()</emphasis> is called from within the Java code, this rule is the first to get a chance to fire.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">drools.setFocus() </emphasis>This sets the focus to the <emphasis role="italic">show items </emphasis>and <emphasis role="italic">evaluate</emphasis> agenda groups in turn , giving their rules a chance to fire. In practice , we loop through all items on the order, inserting them into memory, then firing the other rules after each insert.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>The next two listings shows the rules within the <emphasis role="italic">show items </emphasis>and <emphasis role="italic">evaluate</emphasis> agenda groups. We look at them in the order that they are called.</para>
				
			<example>
				<title>Show Items in the GUI extract (4) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>rule "Show Items"
    agenda-group "show items"
    dialect "mvel"
when
    $order : Order( )
    $p : Purchase( order == $order )
then
   textArea.append( $p.product + "\n");
end
</programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>The <emphasis role="italic">show items</emphasis> agenda-group has only one rule, also called <emphasis role="italic">Show Items</emphasis> (note the difference in case). For each purchase on the order currently in the working memory (session) it logs details to the text area (at the bottom of the GUI). The <emphasis role="italic">textArea</emphasis> variable used to do this is one of the Global Variables we looked at earlier.</para>

			<para>The <emphasis role="italic">evaluate</emphasis> Agenda group also gains focus from the <emphasis role="italic">explode cart </emphasis>rule above. This Agenda group has two rules (below) <emphasis role="italic">Free Fish Food Sample </emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Suggest Tank</emphasis>.</para>

			<example>
				<title>Evaluate Agenda Group extract (5) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>// Free Fish Food sample when we buy a Gold Fish if we haven't already  bought 
// Fish Food and dont already have a Fish Food Sample
rule "Free Fish Food Sample"
    agenda-group "evaluate"
    dialect "mvel"
when
    $order : Order()
    not ( $p : Product( name == "Fish Food") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    not ( $p : Product( name == "Fish Food Sample") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    exists ( $p : Product( name == "Gold Fish") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    $fishFoodSample : Product( name == "Fish Food Sample" );
then
    System.out.println( "Adding free Fish Food Sample to cart" );
    purchase = new Purchase($order, $fishFoodSample);
    insert( purchase );
    $order.addItem( purchase ); 
end

// Suggest a tank if we have bought more than 5 gold fish and dont already have one
rule "Suggest Tank"
    agenda-group "evaluate"
    dialect "java"
when
    $order : Order()
    not ( $p : Product( name == "Fish Tank") &amp;&amp; Purchase( product == $p ) )
    ArrayList( $total : size &gt; 5 ) from collect( Purchase( product.name == "Gold Fish" ) )
    $fishTank : Product( name == "Fish Tank" )
then
    requireTank(frame, drools.getWorkingMemory(), $order, $fishTank, $total); 
end
</programlisting>
			</example>
      

			<para>The <emphasis role="italic">Free Fish Food Sample</emphasis> rule will only fire if</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>We <emphasis role="italic">don't </emphasis>already have any fish food.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>We <emphasis role="italic">don't</emphasis> already have a free fish food sample.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>We <emphasis role="italic">do</emphasis> have a Gold Fish in our order.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>If the rule does fire, it creates a new product (Fish Food Sample), and adds it to the Order in working memory.</para>

			<para>The <emphasis role="italic">Suggest Tank</emphasis> rule will only fire if</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>We <emphasis role="italic">don't </emphasis>already have a Fish Tank in our order</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>If we <emphasis role="italic">can</emphasis> find more than 5 Gold Fish Products in our order.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>If the rule does fire, it calls the <emphasis role="italic">requireTank</emphasis>() function that we looked at earlier (showing a Dialog to the user, and adding a Tank to the order / working memory if confirmed). When calling the <emphasis role="italic">requireTank</emphasis>() function the rule passes the global <emphasis role="italic">frame</emphasis> variable so that the function has a handle to the Swing GUI.</para>

			<para>The next rule we look at is <emphasis role="italic">do checkout.</emphasis></para>
				
			<example>
				<title>Doing the Checkout - extract (6) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>rule "do checkout"
    dialect "java"
    when
    then
        doCheckout(frame, drools.getWorkingMemory());
end</programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>The <emphasis role="italic">do checkout</emphasis> rule has <emphasis role="bold">no agenda-group set and no auto-focus attribute</emphasis>. As such, is is deemed part of the default (MAIN) agenda-group - the same as the other non PetStore examples where agenda groups are not used. This group gets focus by default when all the rules/agenda-groups that explicity had focus set to them have run their course.</para>

			<para>There is no LHS to the rule, so the RHS will always call the <emphasis role="italic">doCheckout</emphasis>() function. When calling the <emphasis role="italic">doCheckout</emphasis>() function the rule passes the global <emphasis role="italic">frame</emphasis> variable so the function has a handle to the Swing GUI. As we saw earlier, the <emphasis role="italic">doCheckout</emphasis>() function shows a confirmation dialog to the user. If confirmed, the function sets the focus to the <emphasis role="italic">checkout</emphasis> agenda-group, allowing the next lot of rules to fire.</para>

			<example>
				<title>Checkout Rules- extract (7) from PetStore.drl</title>

				<programlisting>rule "Gross Total"
    agenda-group "checkout"
    dialect "mvel"
when
   $order : Order( grossTotal == -1)
   Number( total : doubleValue ) from accumulate( Purchase( $price : product.price ),
                 sum( $price ) )
then
    modify( $order ) { grossTotal = total };
    textArea.append( "\ngross total=" + total + "\n" );
end

rule "Apply 5% Discount"
    agenda-group "checkout"
dialect "mvel"
when
   $order : Order( grossTotal &gt;= 10 &amp;&amp; &lt; 20 )
then
   $order.discountedTotal = $order.grossTotal * 0.95;
   textArea.append( "discountedTotal total=" + $order.discountedTotal + "\n" );
end


rule "Apply 10% Discount"
    agenda-group "checkout"
dialect "mvel"
when
   $order : Order( grossTotal &gt;= 20 )
then
   $order.discountedTotal = $order.grossTotal * 0.90;
   textArea.append( "discountedTotal total=" + $order.discountedTotal + "\n" );
end
</programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>There are three rules in the <emphasis role="italic">checkout</emphasis> agenda-group</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">Gross Total </emphasis> - if we haven't already calculated the gross total, accumulates the product prices into a total, puts this total into working memory, and displays it via the Swing TextArea (using the <emphasis role="italic">textArea </emphasis>global variable yet again).</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">Apply 5% Discount</emphasis> - if our gross total is between 10 and 20, then calculate the discounted total and add it to working memory / display in the text area.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">Apply 10% Discount</emphasis> - if our gross total is equal to or greater than 20, calculate the discounted total and add it to working memory / display in the text area.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			
			<para>Now we've run through what happens in the code, lets have a look at what happens when we run the code for real. The <emphasis role="italic">PetStore.java </emphasis>example contains a <emphasis role="italic">main()</emphasis> method, so it can be run as a standard Java application (either from the command line or via the IDE). This assumes you have your classpath set correctly (see the start of the examples section for more information).</para>

			<para>The first screen that we see is the Pet Store Demo. It has a List of available products (top left) , an empty list of selected products (top right), checkout and reset buttons (middle) and an empty system messages area (bottom).</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Figure 1 - PetStore Demo just after Launch</title>

				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetstoreExample/1-PetStore-Start-Screen.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para>To get to this point, the following things have happened:</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <emphasis role="italic">main()</emphasis> method has run and loaded the RuleBase <emphasis role="bold">but not yet fired the rules</emphasis>. This is the only rules related code to run so far.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>A new <emphasis role="italic">PetStoreUI</emphasis> class is created and given a handle to the RuleBase (for later use).</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Various Swing Components do their stuff, and the above screen is shown and <emphasis role="bold">waits for user input</emphasis>.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			
			<para>Clicking on various products from the list might give you a screen similar to the one below.</para>

			<figure>
				<title>Figure 2 - PetStore Demo with Products Selected</title>

				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetstoreExample/2-stock-added-to-order-list.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			
			<para>Note that <emphasis role="bold">no rules code has been fired here</emphasis>. This is only swing code, listening for the mouse click event, and added the clicked product to the <emphasis>TableModel</emphasis> object for display in the top right hand section (as an aside , this is a classic use of the Model View Controller - MVC - design pattern).</para>

			<para>It is only when we press the <emphasis role="bold">Checkout</emphasis> that we fire our business rules, in roughly the same order that we walked through the code earlier.</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <emphasis role="italic">CheckOutCallBack.checkout()</emphasis> method is called (eventually) by the Swing class waiting for the click on the checkout button. This inserts the data from the <emphasis>TableModel</emphasis> object (top right hand side of the GUI), and handles from the GUI into the session / working memory. It then fires the rules.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>The <emphasis role="italic">Explode Cart</emphasis> rule is the first to fire, given that has <emphasis role="italic">auto-focus </emphasis>set to true. It loops through all the products in the cart, makes sure the products are in the working memory, then gives the <emphasis role="italic">Show Items</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Evaluation</emphasis> agenda groups a chance to fire. The rules in these groups, add the contents of the cart to the text area (bottom), decide whether or not to give us free fish food and whether to ask if we want to buy a fish tank (Figure 3 below).</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<figure>
				<title>Figure 3 - Do we want to buy a fish tank?</title>

				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetstoreExample/3-purchase-suggestion.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The <emphasis role="italic">Do Checkout</emphasis> rule is the next to fire as it (a) No other agenda group currently has focus and (b) it is part of the default (MAIN) agenda group. It always calls the<emphasis role="italic"> doCheckout() function </emphasis>which displays a 'Would you like to Checkout?' Dialog Box.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>The <emphasis role="italic">doCheckout() function</emphasis> sets the focus to the <emphasis role="italic">checkout </emphasis>agenda-group, giving the rules in that group the option to fire.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>The rules in the the <emphasis role="italic">checkout</emphasis> agenda-group, display the contents of the cart and apply the appropriate discount.</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="bold">Swing then waits for user input</emphasis> to either checkout more products (and to cause the rules to fire again) or to close the GUI - Figure 4 below.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<figure>
				<title>Figure 4 - Petstore Demo after all rules have fired.</title>

				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/PetstoreExample/4-Petstore-final-screen.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

			<para>Should we choose, we could add more System.out calls to demonstrate this flow of events. The current output of the console of the above sample is as per the listing below.</para>
	
			<example>
				<title>Console (System.out) from running the PetStore GUI</title>

				<programlisting>Adding free Fish Food Sample to cart 
SUGGESTION: Would you like to buy a tank for your 6 fish? - Yes</programlisting>
			</example>
     

			<!---<para>Todo : Add Audit and Agenda Views for this sample.</para>-->
		</section>