<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <section>
    <title>Downloads</title>
    
    <para>All releases can be downloaded from <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/projects/jbpm/files/">
    SourceForge</ulink>. Select the version you want to download and then select which artefact you want:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>bin: all the jBPM binaries (jars) and their dependencies</listitem>
        <listitem>src: the sources of the core components</listitem>
        <listitem>gwt-console: the jbpm console, a zip file containing both the server and client war</listitem>
        <listitem>docs: the documentation</listitem>
        <listitem>examples: some jBPM examples, can be imported into Eclipse</listitem>
        <listitem>installer: the jbpm-installer, downloads and installs a demo setup of jBPM</listitem>
        <listitem>installer-full: the jbpm-installer, downloads and installs a demo setup of jBPM, already
        contains a number of dependencies prepackages (so they don't need to be downloaded separately)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Getting started</title>
    
    <para>If you like to take a quick tutorial that will guide you through most of the components
    using a simple example, take a look at the Installer chapter.  This will teach you how to download
    and use the installer to create a demo setup, including most of the components.  It uses a simple
    example to guide you through the most important features.  Screencasts are available to help you
    out as well.</para>
    
    <para>If you like to read more information first, the following chapters first focus on the core
    engine (API, BPMN 2.0, etc.).  Further chapters will then describe the other components and other
    more complex topics like domain-specific processes, flexible processes, etc.  After reading the core
    chapters, you should be able to jump to other chapters that you might find interesting.</para>
    
    <para>You can also start playing around with some examples that are offered in a separate download.
    Check out the examples chapter to see how to start playing with these.</para>
    
    <para>After that, you should be ready to start creating your own processes and integrate the engine
    with your application, for example by starting from the installer or another example, or by starting
    from scratch.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Community</title>
    
    <para>Here are a lot of useful links if we want to become part of the jBPM community:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>A feed of <ulink url="http://planet.jboss.org/view/feed.seam?name=jbossjbpm">
        blog entries</ulink> related to jBPM</listitem>
        <listitem>The <ulink url="http://twitter.com/jbossjbpm">#jbossjbpm twitter account</ulink>.</listitem>
        <listitem>A <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=217">
        user forum</ulink> for asking questions and giving answers</listitem>
        <listitem>A <ulink url="https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/JBPM">JIRA bug tracking system</ulink>
        for bugs, feature requests and roadmap</listitem>
        <listitem>A <ulink url="https://hudson.jboss.org/hudson/job/jBPM/">continuous build server</ulink>
        for getting the <ulink url="https://hudson.jboss.org/hudson/job/jBPM/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/jbpm-distribution/target/">
        latest snapshots</ulink></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>Please feel free to join us in our IRC channel at irc.codehaus.org #jbpm.  This is where most
    of the real-time discussion about the project takes place and where you can find most of the 
    developers most of their time as well.  Don't have an IRC client installed? Simply go to 
    <ulink url="http://irc.codehaus.org">http://irc.codehaus.org</ulink>, input your desired nickname,
    and specify #jbpm. Then click login to join the fun.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Sources</title>
    
    <section>
      <title>License</title>
      
      <para>The jBPM code itself is using the Apache License v2.0.</para>
      
      <para>Some other components we integrate with have their own license:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>The new Eclipse BPMN2 plugin is Eclipse Public License (EPL) v1.0.</listitem>
        <listitem>The web-based designer is based on Oryx/Wapama and is MIT License</listitem>
        <listitem>The BPM console is GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL) v2.1</listitem>
        <listitem>The Drools project is Apache License v2.0.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Source code</title>
      
      <para>jBPM now uses git for its source code version control system.  The sources of the jBPM
      project can be found here (including all releases starting from jBPM 5.0-CR1):</para>
      <para><ulink url="https://github.com/droolsjbpm/jbpm">https://github.com/droolsjbpm/jbpm</ulink></para>
      
      <para>The source of some of the other components we integrate with can be found here:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Other components related to the jBPM and Drools project can be found <ulink url="https://github.com/droolsjbpm">here</ulink>.</listitem>
        <listitem>The jBPM Eclipse plugin can be found <ulink url="http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/jbosstools/trunk/bpmn/plugins/org.jboss.tools.jbpm/">here</ulink>.</listitem>
        <listitem>The new Eclipse BPMN2 plugin can be found <ulink url="https://github.com/droolsjbpm/bpmn2-eclipse-editor">here</ulink>.</listitem>
        <listitem>The web-based designer can be found <ulink url="https://github.com/tsurdilo/process-designer">here</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem>The BPM console can be found <ulink url="https://github.com/bpmc/bpm-console">here</ulink></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Building from source</title>
      
      <para>If you're interested in building the source code, contributing, releasing, etc. make
      sure to read this <ulink url="https://github.com/droolsjbpm/droolsjbpm-build-bootstrap/blob/master/README.md">README</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    
  </section>
  
</chapter>
