<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>Installing and using</title>

  <para>Drools provides an eclipse based IDE (which is optional), but at its
  core only Java 1.4 (J2SE) is required.</para>

  <para>A simple way to get started is to download and install the eclipse
  plug in - this will also require the Eclipse GEF framework to be installed
  (see below, if you don't have it installed already). This will provide you
  with all the dependencies you need to get going: you can simply create a new
  rule project and everything will be done for you. Refer to the chapter on
  the Rule Workbench and IDE for detailed instructions on this. Installing the
  eclipse plugin is generally as simple as unzipping a file into your eclipse
  plugin directory.</para>

  <para>Use of the eclipse plug in is not required. Rule files are just
  textual input (or spreadsheets as the case may be) and the IDE (also known
  as the Rule Workbench) is just a convenience. People have integrated the
  rule engine in many ways, there is no "one size fits all".</para>

  <para>Alternatively, you can download the binary distribution, and include
  the relevant jars in your projects classpath.</para>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Dependencies and jars</title>

    <para>Drools is broken down into a few modules, some are required during
    rule development/compiling, and some are required at runtime. In many
    cases, people will simply want to include all the dependencies at runtime,
    and this is fine. It allows you to have the most flexibility. However,
    some may prefer to have their "runtime" stripped down to the bare minimum,
    as they will be deploying rules in binary form - this is also possible.
    The core runtime engine can be quite compact, and only require a few 100
    kilobytes across 2 jar files.</para>

    <para>The following is a description of the important libraries that make
    up JBoss Rules</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>drools-core.jar - this is the core engine, runtime component.
        Contains both the RETE engine and the LEAPS engine. This is the only
        runtime dependency if you are pre-compiling rules (and deploying via
        Package or RuleBase objects).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drools-compiler.jar - this contains the compiler/builder
        components to take rule source, and build executable rule bases. This
        is often a runtime dependency of your application, but it need not be
        if you are pre-compiling your rules. This depends on
        drools-core</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drools-jsr94.jar - this is the JSR-94 compliant implementation,
        this is essentially a layer over the drools-compiler component. Note
        that due to the nature of the JSR-94 specification, not all features
        are easily exposed via this interface. In some cases, it will be
        easier to go direct to the drools API, but in some environments the
        JSR-94 is mandated.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drools-decisiontables.jar - this is the decision tables
        'compiler' component, which uses the drools-compiler component. This
        supports both excel and CSV input formats.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>There are quite a few other dependencies which the above components
    require, most of which are for the drools-compiler, drools-jsr94 or
    drools-decisiontables module. Some of these (such as the XML libraries)
    may not be required if you run in a Java 1.5 environment. Some key ones to
    note are "JCI" - which is the apache Java Compiler Interface utility which
    provides runtime compiling capability, "POI" which provides the
    spreadsheet parsing ability, and "antlr" which provides the parsing for
    the rule language itself.</para>

    <para>NOTE: if you are using Drools in J2EE or servlet containers and you
    come across classpath issues with "JDT", then you can switch to the janino
    compiler. Set the system property "drools.compiler": For example:
    -Ddrools.compiler=JANINO.</para>

    <para>For up to date info on dependencies in a release, consult the
    README_DEPENDENCIES.txt file, which can be found in the lib directory of
    the download bundle, or in the root of the project directory.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Runtime</title>

    <para>The "runtime" requirements mentioned here are if you are deploying
    rules as their binary form (either as Package objects, or RuleBase objects
    etc). This is an optional feature that allows you to keep your runtime
    very light. You may use drools-compiler to produce rule packages "out of
    process", and then deploy them to a runtime system. This runtime system
    only requires drools-core.jar for execution. This is an optional
    deployment pattern, and many people do not need to "trim" their
    application this much, but it is an ideal option for certain
    environments.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing IDE (Rule Workbench)</title>

    <para>The rule workbench (for Eclipse) requires that you have eclipse 3.2
    or greater, as well as Eclipse GEF 3.2 or greater. You can install it
    either by downloading the plugin or, or using the update site.</para>

    <para>Another option is to use the JBoss IDE, which comes with all the
    plug in requirements pre packaged, as well as a choice of other tools
    seperate to rules. You can choose just to install rules from the "bundle"
    that JBoss IDE ships with.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing GEF (a required dependency)</title>

      <para>GEF is the eclipse Graphical Editing Framework, which is used for
      graph viewing components in the plug in.</para>

      <para>If you don't have GEF installed, you can install it using the
      built in update mechanism (or downloading GEF from the eclipse.org
      website not recommended). JBoss IDE has GEF already, as do many other "distributions" of
      Eclipse, so this step may be redundant for some people.</para>

      <para>First you open the Help-&gt;Software updates-&gt;Find and install
      from the help menu. Then you choose the Calisto update site:</para>

	  <para>If you aren't using Calisto you can use the following update site do download GEF</para>
	  <programlisting>http://europa-mirror1.eclipse.org/tools/gef/update-site/releases/</programlisting>
	
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="gef_update.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Next you choose the GEF plug in:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="install_gef.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Press next, and agree to install the plug in (an eclipse restart
      may be required). Once this is completed, then you can continue on
      installing the rules plug in.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from zip file</title>

      <para>To install from the zip file, download and unzip the file. Inside
      the zip you will see a plugin directory, and the plugin jar itself. You
      place the plugin jar into your eclipse applications plugin directory,
      and restart eclipse.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from the update site</title>

      <para>Using the update site is a handy way to install the plug in, and
      keep it up to date (the eclipse platform will check for updates as
      needed). It gives you a good chance of staying up to date with
      improvements, fixes etc.</para>

      <para>Some firewalls may cause trouble with using update sites in
      eclipse, if you have issues, then install it manually from the plugin.
      Also, if you have previously installed the plug in manually, you will
      need to manually remove it from your plug in directory.</para>

      <para>Step 1. Use the eclipse help menu to find the feature installer.
      <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Access the software updates menu</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="help_menu.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 2: Choose the option for installing a new feature (obviously
      in future, if you want to check for updates, you use the other option
      !). <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Search for new features</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="search_new_features.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 3: This screen will show what update sites are already
      configured for your Eclipse instance. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Update sites</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="update_sites_existing.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 4: This screen is where you enter in the remote site details.
      You give it a name eg "JBoss Rules" and the url. <programlisting>URL: http://anonsvn.labs.jboss.com/labs/jbossrules/updates/drools-ide-update/</programlisting>
      <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>New remote site</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="new_remote_site.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 5: Select the new update site you just added. Eclipse will
      remember this for when it checks for updates automatically in the
      future. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Choose the newly added update site</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="update_sites.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 6: You should see the available features (Drools IDE)
      retrieved from the update site. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Available features</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="search_results.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 7: The licence agreement. Choose the option to accept the
      licence agreement. Once this happens, the workbench will start
      downloading. Might be an opportune time to go have a coffee. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Licence</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="licence.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 8: Confirm that this is the feature you want. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Confirmation</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="confirm.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 9: Press Accept to accept the fact that the feature is not
      digitally signed. No one signs their features, its a silly default
      screen in Eclipse. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Verify</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="digital_sign.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 10: The workbench will need to restart now for the feature to
      take effect. <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>Restart the workbench</screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="restart.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Now go have another coffee, and then take a look at the chapter on
      the Rule Workbench for what you can do with it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>