<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xml:id="releaseNotes_5.4.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>What is New and Noteworthy in Drools 5.4.0</title>

  <section xml:id="releaseNotes_5.4.0_Expert">
    <title>Drools Expert</title>

    <section>
      <title>Traits</title>

      <para>Traits were introduced in the 5.3 release, and details on them can be found in the N&amp;N for there. This
      release adds an example so that people have something simple to run, to help them understand. In the
      drools-examples source project open the classes and drl for the namespace "/org/drools/examples/traits". There you
      will find an example around classifications of students and workers.</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Students and Workers" no-loop when
    $p : Person( $name : name, 
                 $age : age &lt; 25,  
                 $weight : weight )
then
    IWorker w = don( $p, IWorker.class, true );
    w.setWage( 1200 );
    update( w );

    IStudent s = don( $p, IStudent.class, true );
    s.setSchool( "SomeSchool" );
    update( s );
end


rule "Working Students" salience -10 when
    $s : IStudent( $school : school, 
                   $name : name,
                   this isA IWorker, 
                   $wage : fields[ "wage" ] )
then
    System.out.println( $name + " : I have " + $wage + " to pay the fees at " + $school );
end</programlisting>

      <para>A two part detailed article has been written up at a blog, which will later be improved and rolled into the
      main documentation. For now you can read them here.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link
          xlink:href="http://blog.athico.com/2011/12/new-feature-spotlight-traits-part-1.html">http://blog.athico.com/2011/12/new-feature-spotlight-traits-part-1.html</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          xlink:href="http://blog.athico.com/2011/12/dynamic-typing-in-rules-traits-part-2.html">http://blog.athico.com/2011/12/dynamic-typing-in-rules-traits-part-2.html</link></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Simulation and Test</title>

      <para>The simulation project that was first started in 2009, <link
      xlink:href="http://blog.athico.com/2009/07/drools-simulation-and-test-framework.html">http://blog.athico.com/2009/07/drools-simulation-and-test-framework.html</link>,
      has undergone an over haul and is now in a usable state. We have not yet promoted this to
      <literal>knowledge-api</literal>, so it's considered unstable and will change during the beta process. For now
      though, the adventurous people can take a look at the unit tests and start playing.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/simulation.jpg" scale="80"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>

    <section>
      <para>The Simulator runs the Simulation. The Simulation is your scenario definition. The Simulation consists of 1
      to n Paths, you can think of a Path as a sort of Thread. The Path is a chronological line on which Steps are
      specified at given temporal distances from the start. You don't specify a time unit for the Step, say 12:00am,
      instead it is always a relative time distance from the start of the Simulation (note: in Beta2 this will be
      relative time distance from the last step in the same path). Each Step contains one or more Commands, i.e. create
      a <literal>StatefulKnowledgeSession</literal> or insert an object or start a process. These are the very same
      commands that you would use to script a knowledge session using the batch execution, so it's re-using existing
      concepts.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>1.1 Simulation</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>1..n Paths</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>1..n Steps</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>1..n Commands</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>All the steps, from all paths, are added to a priority queue which is ordered by the temporal distance, and
      allows us to incrementally execute the engine using a time slicing approach. The simulator pops of the steps from
      the queue in turn. For each Step it increments the engine clock and then executes all the Step's Commands.</para>

      <para>Here is an example Command (notice it uses the same Commands as used by the CommandExecutor):</para>

      <programlisting>new InsertObjectCommand( new Person( "darth", 97 ) )</programlisting>

      <para>Commands can be grouped together, especially Assertion commands, via test groups. The test groups are mapped
      to JUnit "test methods", so as they pass or fail using a specialised JUnit Runner the Eclipse GUI is updated - as
      illustrated in the above image, showing two passed test groups named "test1" and "test2".</para>

      <para>Using the JUnit integration is trivial. Just annotate the class with @RunWith(JUnitSimulationRunner.class).
      Then any method that is annotated with @Test and returns a Simulation instance will be invoked executing the
      returned Simulation instance in the Simulator. As test groups are executed the JUnit GUI is updated.</para>

      <para>When executing any commands on a KnowledgeBuilder, KnowledgeBase or StatefulKnowledgeSession the system
      assumes a "register" approach. To get a feel for this look at the <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/droolsjbpm/droolsjbpm-integration/blob/8100e28668537aa5fe04ce5dd0a62f3dc779b30f/drools-simulator/src/test/java/org/drools/simulation/impl/SimulationTest.java">org.drools.simulation.impl.SimulationTest</link> at github
      (path may change over time).</para>

      <programlisting>cmds.add( new NewKnowledgeBuilderCommand( null ) );
cmds.add( new SetVariableCommandFromLastReturn( "path1",
                                                KnowledgeBuilder.class.getName() ) );

cmds.add( new KnowledgeBuilderAddCommand( ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource( str.getBytes() ),
                                          ResourceType.DRL, null ) );</programlisting>

      <para>Notice the set command. "path1" is the context, each path has it's own variable context. All paths inherit
      from a "root" context. "KnowledgeBuilder.class.getName() " is the name that we are setting the return value of the
      last command. As mentioned before we consider the class names of those classes as registers, any further commands
      that attempt to operate on a knowledge builder will use what ever is assigned to that, as in the case of
      KnowledgeBuilderAddCommand. This allows multiple kbuilders, kbases and ksessions to exist in one context under
      different variable names, but only the one assigned to the register name is the one that is currently executed
      on.</para>

      <para>The code below show the rough outline used in SimulationTest:</para>

      <programlisting>Simulation simulation = new SimulationImpl();
PathImpl path = new PathImpl( simulation,
                              "path1" );                              
simulation.getPaths().put( "path1",
                           path );                                      
List&lt;Step&gt; steps = new ArrayList&lt;Step&gt;();
path.setSteps( steps );
List&lt;Command&gt; cmds = new ArrayList&lt;Command&gt;();
.... add commands to step here ....
// create a step at temporal distance of 2000ms from start
steps.add( new StepImpl( path,
                         cmds,
                         2000 ) ); </programlisting>

      <para>We know the above looks quite verbose. SimulationTest just shows our low level canonical model, the idea is
      that high level representations are built ontop of this. As this is a builder API we are currently focusing on two
      sets of fluents, compact and standard. We will also work on a spreadsheet UI for building these, and eventually a
      dedicated textual dsl.</para>

      <para>The compact fluent is designed to provide the absolute minimum necessary to run against a single ksession. A
      good place to start is <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/droolsjbpm/droolsjbpm-integration/blob/8100e28668537aa5fe04ce5dd0a62f3dc779b30f/drools-simulator/src/test/java/org/drools/simulation/impl/CompactFluentTest.java">org.drools.simulation.impl.CompactFluentTest</link>,
      a snippet of which is shown below. Notice we set "yoda" to "y" and can then assert on that. Currently inside of
      the test string it executes using mvel. The eventual goal is to build out a set of <link
      xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/hamcrest/">hamcrest</link> matchers that will allow assertions against the
      state of the engine, such as what rules have fired and optionally with with data.</para>

      <programlisting>FluentCompactSimulation f = new FluentCompactSimulationImpl();
f.newStatefulKnowledgeSession()
    .getKnowledgeBase()
    .addKnowledgePackages( ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource( str.getBytes() ),
                           ResourceType.DRL )
    .end()
    .newStep( 100 ) // increases the time 100ms
    .insert( new Person( "yoda",
                         150 ) ).set( "y" )
    .fireAllRules()
    // show testing inside of ksession execution
    .test( "y.name == 'yoda'" )
    .test( "y.age == 160" );</programlisting>

      <para>Note that the test is not executing at build time, it's building a script to be executed later. The script
      underneath matches what you saw in SimulationTest. Currently the way to run a simulation manually is shown below.
      Atlhough you already saw in SimulationTest that JUnit will execute these automatically. We'll improve this over
      itme.</para>

      <programlisting>SimulationImpl sim = (SimulationImpl) ((FluentCompactSimulationImpl) f).getSimulation();
Simulator simulator = new Simulator( sim,
                                     new Date().getTime() );
simulator.run();</programlisting>

      <para>The standard fluent is almost a 1 to 1 mapping to the cannonical path, step and command structure in
      SimulationTest- just more compact. Start by looking in <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/droolsjbpm/droolsjbpm-integration/blob/8100e28668537aa5fe04ce5dd0a62f3dc779b30f/drools-simulator/src/test/java/org/drools/simulation/impl/StandardFluentTest.java">org.drools.simulation.impl.StandardFluentTest</link>. This fluent allows you to run any number of
      paths and steps, along with a lot more control over multiple kbuilders, kbases and ksessions.</para>

      <programlisting>FluentStandardSimulation f = new FluentStandardSimulationImpl();      
f.newPath("init")
     .newStep( 0 )
          // set to ROOT, as I want paths to share this
         .newKnowledgeBuilder()
             .add( ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource( str.getBytes() ),
                   ResourceType.DRL )
         .end(ContextManager.ROOT, KnowledgeBuilder.class.getName() )
         .newKnowledgeBase()
             .addKnowledgePackages()
         .end(ContextManager.ROOT, KnowledgeBase.class.getName() )
    .end()
 .newPath( "path1" )
    .newStep( 1000 )
        .newStatefulKnowledgeSession()
            .insert( new Person( "yoda", 150 ) ).set( "y" )
            .fireAllRules()
            .test( "y.name == 'yoda'" )
            .test( "y.age == 160" )
        .end()
    .end()
 .newPath( "path2" )
    .newStep( 800 )
        .newStatefulKnowledgeSession()
            .insert( new Person( "darth", 70 ) ).set( "d" )
            .fireAllRules()
            .test( "d.name == 'darth'" )
            .test( "d.age == 80" )
        .end()
    .end()
 .end</programlisting>

      <para>There is still an aweful lot to do, this is designed to eventually provide a unified simulation and testing
      environment for rules, workflow and event processing over time, and eventually also over distributed
      architectures.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Flesh out the api to support more commands, and also to encompass jBPM commands</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Improve out of the box usability, including moving interfaces to knowlege-api and hiding "new"
          constructors with factory methods</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Commands are already marshallable to json and xml. They should be updated to allow full round tripping
          from java api commands and json/xml documents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Develop hamcrest matchers for testing state</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>What rule(s) fired, including optionally what data was used with the executing rule (Drools)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>What rules are active for a given fact</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>What rules activated and de-activated for a given fact change</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Process variable state (jBPM)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Wait node states (jBPM)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Design and build tabular authoring tools via spreadsheet, targetting the web with round tripping to
          excel.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Design and develop textual DSL for authoing - maybe part of DRL (long term task).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fine Grained Property Change Listeners (Property
        Specific)</title>

      <para>Currently, when you in a RHS you call modify() on a given fact it
        triggers a revaluation of all Patterns of the matching object type in
        the knowledeg base. As some have found this can be a problem, forcing
        you to split up your objects into smaller 1 to 1 objects, to avoid
        unwanted evaluation of objects like recursion or excessive evaluation
        issues. This new feature allows a pattern to react (and then be
        re-eavluated) only to modifications made on fields constrained or bound
        inside the pattern itself.</para>

      <para>The implementation is bit mask based, so very efficient. When the
        engine executes a modify statement it uses a bit mask of fields being
        changed, the pattern will only respond if it has an overlapping bit
        mask. This does not work for update(), and is one of the reason why we
        promote modify() as it encapsulates the field changes within the
        statement.</para>

      <para>feature is off by default in order to make the behavior of the
        rule engine backward compatible with the former releases. If you want to
        activate it on a specific bean you have to annotate it with
        @propertySpecific. This annotation works both on drl type
        declarations:</para>

      <programlisting>declare Person
        @propertySpecific
        firstName : String
        lastName : String
        end</programlisting>

      <para>and on Java classes:</para>

      <programlisting>@PropertySpecific
        public static class Person {
        private String firstName;
        private String lastName;
        }</programlisting>

      <para>Given this simple type declaration, the most evident advantage of
        this new Property Specific feature, will be, for instance, that the
        following rule:</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Modify last name" when
        Person( firstName == "Mario" )
        then
        modify($person) { setLastName("Fusco") }
        end</programlisting>

      <para>will no longer end up in an infinite loop.</para>

      <para>Moreover on Java classes you can also annotate any method to say
        that its invocation actually modifies other properties. For instance in
        the former Person class you could have a method like:</para>

      <programlisting>@Modifies( { "firstName", "lastName" } )
        public void setName(String name) {
        String[] names = name.split("\\s");
        this.firstName = names[0];
        this.lastName = names[1];
        }</programlisting>

      <para>That means that if a rule has a RHS like the following:</para>

      <programlisting>modify($person) { setName("Mario Fusco") }</programlisting>

      <para>it will correctly recognize that both the firstName and lastName
        have been modified and act accordingly. Of course the @Modifies
        annotation on a method has no effect if the declaring class isn't
        annotated with @PropertySpecific.</para>

      <para>The third newly introduced annotation is on patterns and allows
        you to modify the inferred set of properties "listened" by it. So, for
        example, you can annotate a pattern in the LHS of a rule like:</para>

      <programlisting>Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( lastName ) // --&gt; listens for changes on both firstName (inferred) and lastName
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( * ) // --&gt; listens for all the properties of the Person bean
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( lastName, !firstName ) // --&gt; listens for changes on lastName and explicitly exclude firstName
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( *, !age ) // --&gt; listens for changes on all the properties except the age one</programlisting>

      <para>The usage of @watch on a type not annotated as @PropertySpecific
        will raise a compilation error. The same will happen if you mention an
        unknown property name inside @watch or use the same name more than once
        like for example in: @watch( lastName, !lastName )</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Accumulate syntax improvements</title>

      <para>Multi-function accumulate now supports inline constraints. The
        simplified EBNF is:</para>

      <programlisting>lhsAccumulate := ACCUMULATE LEFT_PAREN lhsAnd (COMMA|SEMICOLON)
        accumulateFunctionBinding (COMMA accumulateFunctionBinding)*
        (SEMICOLON constraints)?
        RIGHT_PAREN SEMICOLON?</programlisting>

      <para>E.g.:</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Accumulate example"
        when
        accumulate( Cheese( $price : price );
        $a1 : average( $price ),
        $m1 : min( $price ),
        $M1 : max( $price );    // a semicolon, followed by inline constraints
        $a1 &gt; 10 &amp;&amp; $M1 &lt;= 100, // inline constraint
        $m1 == 5                // inline constraint
        )
        then
        // do something
        end
      </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>XLS \ CSV Decision tables support declared types</title>

      <para>A new RuleSet property has been added called "Declare".</para>

      <para>This provides a slot in the RuleSet definition to define declared
        types.</para>

      <para>In essence the slot provides a descrete location to add type
        declarations where, previously, they may have been added to a Queries or
        Functions definition.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>RuleSet "Declare"</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-xls-declare.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Wumpus World</title>

      <para>A working version of Wumpus World, an AI example covered in in the
        book "Artificial Intelligence : A Modern Approach", is now available
        among the other examples. A more detailed overview of Wumpus World can
        be found <link
            xlink:href="http://www.cis.temple.edu/~giorgio/cis587/readings/wumpus.shtml">here</link></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision Tables support "timer" and "calendar" attributes</title>

      <para>Support has been added for the "timer" and "calendar" attributes.</para>

      <table>
        <title>New attributes</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Keyword</entry>

              <entry>Initial</entry>

              <entry>Value</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>TIMER</entry>

              <entry>T</entry>

              <entry>A timer definition. See "Timers and Calendars".</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CALENDARS</entry>

              <entry>E</entry>

              <entry>A calendars definition. See "Timers and Calendars".</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>KnowledgeBuilder supports building of cross referencing drl files</title>

      <para>KnowledgeBuilder has a new batch mode, with a fluent interface, that allows to build multiple DRLs at once
        as in the following example:</para>

      <programlisting>KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();
        kbuilder.batch()
        .add(ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource(rules1.getBytes()), ResourceType.DRL)
        .add(ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource(rules2.getBytes()), ResourceType.DRL)
        .add(ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource(declarations.getBytes()), ResourceType.DRL)
        .build();</programlisting>

      <para>In this way it is no longer necessary to build the DRLs files in the right order (e.g. first the DRLs
        containing the type declarations and then the ones with the rules using them) and it will also be possible to have
        circular references among them.</para>

      <para>Moreover the KnowledgeBuilder (regardless if you are using the batch mode or not) also allows to discard
        what has been added with the last DRL(s) building. This can be useful to recover from having added a wrong DRL to
        the KnowledgeBuilder as it follows:</para>

      <programlisting>kbuilder.add(ResourceFactory.newByteArrayResource(wrongDrl.getBytes()), ResourceType.DRL);
        if ( kbuilder.hasErrors() ) {
        kbuilder.undo();
        }</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fine grained property change listeners</title>

      <para>In Drools when you invoke update() or modify() on a given object it will trigger a revaluation of all
        patterns of the matching object type in the knowledge base. As some have experienced, this can be a problem that
        often can lead to unwanted and useless evaluations and in the worst cases to infinite recursions. The only
        workaround to avoid it was to split up your objects into smaller ones having a 1 to 1 relationship with the
        original object.</para>

      <para>This new feature allows the pattern matching to only react to modification of properties actually
        constrained or bound inside of a given pattern. That will help with performance and recursion and avoid artificial
        object splitting.</para>

      <para>By default this feature is off in order to make the behavior of the rule engine backward compatible with the
        former releases. When you want to activate it on a specific bean you have to annotate it with @propertyReactive.
        This annotation works both on drl type declarations:</para>

      <programlisting>declare Person
        @propertyReactive
        firstName : String
        lastName : String
        end</programlisting>

      <para>and on Java classes:</para>

      <programlisting>@PropertyReactive
        public static class Person {
        private String firstName;
        private String lastName;
        }</programlisting>

      <para>In this way, for instance, if you have a rule like the following:</para>

      <programlisting>rule "Every person named Mario is a male" when
        $person : Person( firstName == "Mario" )
        then
        modify ( $person )  { setMale( true ) }
        end</programlisting>

      <para>you won't have to add the no-loop attribute to it in order to avoid an infinite recursion because the engine
        recognizes that the pattern matching is done on the 'firstName' property while the RHS of the rule modifies the
        'male' one. Note that this feature does not work for update(), and this is one of the reasons why we promote
        modify() since it encapsulates the field changes within the statement. Moreover, on Java classes, you can also
        annotate any method to say that its invocation actually modifies other properties. For instance in the former
        Person class you could have a method like:</para>

      <programlisting>@Modifies( { "firstName", "lastName" } )
        public void setName(String name) {
        String[] names = name.split("\\s");
        this.firstName = names[0];
        this.lastName = names[1];
        }</programlisting>

      <para>That means that if a rule has a RHS like the following:</para>

      <programlisting>modify($person) { setName("Mario Fusco") }</programlisting>

      <para>it will correctly recognize that the values of both properties 'firstName' and 'lastName' could have
        potentially been modified and act accordingly, not missing of reevaluating the patterns constrained on them. At
        the moment the usage of @Modifies is not allowed on fields but only on methods. This is coherent with the most
        common scenario where the @Modifies will be used for methods that are not related with a class field as in the
        Person.setName() in the former example. Also note that @Modifies is not transitive, meaning that if another method
        internally invokes the Person.setName() one it won't be enough to annotate it with @Modifies( { "name" } ), but it
        is necessary to use @Modifies( { "firstName", "lastName" } ) even on it. Very likely @Modifies transitivity will
        be implemented in the next release.</para>

      <para>For what regards nested accessors, the engine will be notified only for top level fields. In other words a
        pattern matching like:</para>

      <programlisting>Person ( address.city.name == "London ) </programlisting>

      <para>will be revaluated only for modification of the 'address' property of a Person object. In the same way the
        constraints analysis is currently strictly limited to what there is inside a pattern. Another example could help
        to clarify this. An LHS like the following:</para>

      <programlisting>$p : Person( )
        Car( owner = $p.name )</programlisting>

      <para>will not listen on modifications of the person's name, while this one will do:</para>

      <programlisting>Person( $name : name )
        Car( owner = $name )</programlisting>

      <para>To overcome this problem it is possible to annotate a pattern with @watch as it follows:</para>

      <programlisting>$p : Person( ) @watch ( name )
        Car( owner = $p.name )</programlisting>

      <para>Indeed, annotating a pattern with @watch allows you to modify the inferred set of properties for which that
        pattern will react. Note that the properties named in the @watch annotation are actually added to the ones
        automatically inferred, but it is also possible to explicitly exclude one or more of them prepending their name
        with a ! and to make the pattern to listen for all or none of the properties of the type used in the pattern
        respectively with the wildcrds * and !*. So, for example, you can annotate a pattern in the LHS of a rule
        like:</para>

      <programlisting>// listens for changes on both firstName (inferred) and lastName
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( lastName )

        // listens for all the properties of the Person bean
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( * )

        // listens for changes on lastName and explicitly exclude firstName
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( lastName, !firstName )

        // listens for changes on all the properties except the age one
        Person( firstName == $expectedFirstName ) @watch( *, !age )</programlisting>

      <para>Since doesn't make sense to use this annotation on a pattern using a type not annotated with
        @PropertyReactive the rule compiler will raise a compilation error if you try to do so. Also the duplicated usage
        of the same property in @watch (for example like in: @watch( firstName, ! firstName ) ) will end up in a
        compilation error. In a next release we will make the automatic detection of the properties to be listened smarter
        by doing analysis even outside of the pattern.</para>

      <para>It also possible to enable this feature by default on all the types of your model or to completely disallow
        it by using on option of the KnowledgeBuilderConfiguration. In particular this new PropertySpecificOption can have
        one of the following 3 values:</para>

      <programlisting>- DISABLED =&gt; the feature is turned off and all the other related annotations are just ignored
        - ALLOWED =&gt; this is the default behavior: types are not property reactive unless they are not annotated with @PropertySpecific
        - ALWAYS =&gt; all types are property reactive by default</programlisting>

      <para>So, for example, to have a KnowledgeBuilder generating property reactive types by default you could
        do:</para>

      <programlisting>KnowledgeBuilderConfiguration config = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilderConfiguration();
        config.setOption(PropertySpecificOption.ALWAYS);
        KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder(config);</programlisting>

      <para>In this last case it will be possible to disable the property reactivity feature on a specific type by
        annotating it with @ClassReactive.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fluent simulation testing</title>

      <para><emphasis>This API is experimental: future backwards incompatible changes are possible.</emphasis></para>

      <para>Using the new fluent simulation testing, you can test your rules in unit tests more easily:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">    @Test
        public void rejectMinors() {
        SimulationFluent simulationFluent = new DefaultSimulationFluent();

        Driver john = new Driver("John", "Smith", new LocalDate().minusYears(10));
        Car mini = new Car("MINI-01", CarType.SMALL, false, new BigDecimal("10000.00"));
        PolicyRequest johnMiniPolicyRequest = new PolicyRequest(john, mini);
        johnMiniPolicyRequest.addCoverageRequest(new CoverageRequest(CoverageType.COLLISION));
        johnMiniPolicyRequest.addCoverageRequest(new CoverageRequest(CoverageType.COMPREHENSIVE));


        simulationFluent
        .newKnowledgeBuilder()
        .add(ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource("org/drools/examples/carinsurance/rule/policyRequestApprovalRules.drl"),
        ResourceType.DRL)
        .end()
        .newKnowledgeBase()
        .addKnowledgePackages()
        .end()
        .newStatefulKnowledgeSession()
        .insert(john).set("john")
        .insert(mini).set("mini")
        .insert(johnMiniPolicyRequest).set("johnMiniPolicyRequest")
        .fireAllRules()
        .test("johnMiniPolicyRequest.automaticallyRejected == true")
        .test("johnMiniPolicyRequest.rejectedMessageList.size() == 1")
        .end()
        .runSimulation();
        }</programlisting>

      <para>You can even test your CEP rules in unit tests without suffering from slow tests:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">    @Test
        public void lyingAboutAge() {
        SimulationFluent simulationFluent = new DefaultSimulationFluent();

        Driver realJohn = new Driver("John", "Smith", new LocalDate().minusYears(10));
        Car realMini = new Car("MINI-01", CarType.SMALL, false, new BigDecimal("10000.00"));
        PolicyRequest realJohnMiniPolicyRequest = new PolicyRequest(realJohn, realMini);
        realJohnMiniPolicyRequest.addCoverageRequest(new CoverageRequest(CoverageType.COLLISION));
        realJohnMiniPolicyRequest.addCoverageRequest(new CoverageRequest(CoverageType.COMPREHENSIVE));
        realJohnMiniPolicyRequest.setAutomaticallyRejected(true);
        realJohnMiniPolicyRequest.addRejectedMessage("Too young.");

        Driver fakeJohn = new Driver("John", "Smith", new LocalDate().minusYears(30));
        Car fakeMini = new Car("MINI-01", CarType.SMALL, false, new BigDecimal("10000.00"));
        PolicyRequest fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest = new PolicyRequest(fakeJohn, fakeMini);
        fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest.addCoverageRequest(new CoverageRequest(CoverageType.COLLISION));
        fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest.addCoverageRequest(new CoverageRequest(CoverageType.COMPREHENSIVE));
        fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest.setAutomaticallyRejected(false);


        simulationFluent
        .newStep(0)
        .newKnowledgeBuilder()
        .add(ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource("org/drools/examples/carinsurance/cep/policyRequestFraudDetectionRules.drl"),
        ResourceType.DRL)
        .end()
        .newKnowledgeBase()
        .addKnowledgePackages()
        .end(World.ROOT, KnowledgeBase.class.getName())
        .newStatefulKnowledgeSession()
        .end()
        .newStep(1000)
        .getStatefulKnowledgeSession()
        .insert(realJohn).set("realJohn")
        .insert(realMini).set("realMini")
        .insert(realJohnMiniPolicyRequest).set("realJohnMiniPolicyRequest")
        .fireAllRules()
        .test("realJohnMiniPolicyRequest.requiresManualApproval == false")
        .end()
        .newStep(5000)
        .getStatefulKnowledgeSession()
        .insert(fakeJohn).set("fakeJohn")
        .insert(fakeMini).set("fakeMini")
        .insert(fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest).set("fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest")
        .fireAllRules()
        .test("fakeJohnMiniPolicyRequest.requiresManualApproval == true")
        .end()
        .runSimulation();
        }</programlisting>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section xml:id="releaseNotes_5.4.0_Fusion">
    <title>Drools Fusion</title>

    <section>
      <title>Entry-Point Declaration</title>

      <para>The engine now supports the declaration of entry-points. This
        allow tools and the application to inspect, select and restrict the use
        of entry-points in rules.</para>

      <para>The simplified EBNF to declare an entry-point is:</para>

      <programlisting>entryPointDeclaration := DECLARE ENTRY-POINT epName annotation* END
        epName := stringId
      </programlisting>

      <para>Example:</para>

      <programlisting>declare entry-point STStream
        @doc("A stream of StockTicks")
        end
      </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Window Declaration</title>

      <para>The engine now supports the declaration of Windows. This promotes
        a clear separation between what are the filters applied to the window
        and what are the constraints applied to the result of window. It also
        allows easy reuse of windows among multiple rules.</para>

      <para>Another benefit is a new implementation of the basic window
        support in the engine, increasing the overall performance of the rules
        that use sliding windows.</para>

      <para>The simplified EBNF to declare a window is:</para>

      <programlisting>windowDeclaration := DECLARE WINDOW ID annotation* lhsPatternBind END</programlisting>

      <para>Example:</para>

      <programlisting>declare window Ticks
        @doc("last 10 stock ticks")
        StockTick( source == "NYSE" )
        over window:length( 10 )
        from entry-point STStream
        end
      </programlisting>

      <para>Rules can then use the declared window by referencing using a FROM
        CE. Example:</para>

      <programlisting>rule "RHT ticks in the window"
        when
        accumulate( StockTick( symbol == "RHT" ) from window Ticks,
        $cnt : count(1) )
        then
        // there has been $cnt RHT ticks over the last 10 ticks
        end
      </programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="releaseNotes_5.4.0_Guvnor">
    <title>Guvnor</title>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Table - Limited Entry</title>

      <para>The Guided Decision Table editor and wizard now support the creation of "Limited Entry" tables.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Selecting the table format</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/limited-entry-1.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Defining Limited Entry constraints with the Wizard</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/limited-entry-2.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Defining Limited Entry actions with the Wizard</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/limited-entry-3.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>An example expanded, limited entry table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/limited-entry-4.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Editing a constraint in the editor</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/limited-entry-5.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Editing an action in the editor</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/limited-entry-6.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Table - Improved formatting</title>

      <para>With the introduction of support for Limited Entry, the decision table format was improved to better
      differentiate between Condition and Action columns. Furthermore the table header was improved to show more
      information for Action columns.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Improved formatting and header</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-column-formatting.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Table - Rearranging columns</title>

      <para>The ability to rearrange whole patterns as well as individual conditions in the constraints section of the
      table has been added. This allows the table author to arrange constraints to maximise performance of the resulting
      rules, by placing generalised constraints before more specific. Action columns can also be re-arranged. Both
      patterns and columns are re-arranged by dragging and dropping.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Re-arranging Condition patterns</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-rearranging-patterns.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Re-arranging columns</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-rearranging-columns.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Table - Actions to retract Facts</title>

      <para>This release brings the ability to define Action columns to retract Facts.</para>

      <para>If you are authoring an Extended Entry decision table the column definition contains basic information and
      the fact being retracted is held in the table itself.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Defining an Extended Entry retraction</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-retract-extended-entry.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If however you are authoring a Limited Entry decision table the Fact being retracted is defined in the
      column definition.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Defining a Limited Entry retraction</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-retract-limited-entry.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Table - Binding condition fields</title>

      <para>You can now bind fields in Conditions to variables. These variables can then be used in Predicate or Forumla
      conditions, and Work Item actions.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Binding a field</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-field-binding1.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>A Decision Table using bound fields</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-field-binding2.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Table - Using jBPM Work Item actions</title>

      <para>jBPM Work Items can now be used as Actions; and the corresponding Work Item Handler invoked at runtime. Work
      Item Handlers should be added to the runtime session as normal.</para>

      <para>Work Item input parameters can either be defined as a literal value in the column definition or as a Fact or
      Fact Field binding.</para>

      <para>New Actions have been created to perform the following functions:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Execute a Work Item</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set the value of a field on an existing Fact to the value of a Work Item output (result)
          parameter.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set the value of a field on a new Fact to the value of a Work Item output (result) parameter.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>New Actions</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-workitems1.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Calling a Work Item</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-workitems2.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Setting a field from a Work Item output (result) parameter</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-workitems3.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision table analysis</title>

      <para>On the bottom of Web decision tables, there's now a button <guilabel>Analyze...</guilabel> which will check
      if there issues in your decision table, such as impossible matches and conflicting matches.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Impossible match detection</title>

        <para>An impossible match is a row in a decision table that can never match. For example:</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/impossibleMatch.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>In the decision table above, row 2 is an impossible match, because there is no Person with a minimum age
        of 21 and a maximum age of 20.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Conflicting match detection</title>

        <para>A conflicting match are 2 rows in a decision table that can both match.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/conflictingMatch.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>In the decision table above, row 2 and 3 are a conflicting match, because a Person of age 67 will match
        both rows: it's unclear whether that Person has to pay a fee of 200 or 100.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>REST api changes</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Added support to create (PUT) and delete (DELETE) a Category with
          <literal>rest/categories/{categoryName}</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Removed buggy <literal>category</literal> property from <literal>Package</literal>: it was
          <literal>null</literal> upon GET and ignored upon PUT.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The REST resource to get the assets for a certain category has been moved from
          <literal>rest/categories/{categoryName}</literal> to
          <literal>rest/categories/{categoryName}/assets</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The REST resources now properly encode and decode the URL's. Note that URL path encoding is different
          than URL query encoding: the former does not accept <literal>+</literal> as encoding for space.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JBoss AS 6 war is no longer shipped in the release</title>

      <para>This does not mean that Guvnor can not be made to work in AS 6. We are just focusing on JBoss AS 7 and
      Tomcat.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Rule Templates - Interpolation keys in free-form DRL</title>

      <para>When using Rule Templates you can now define interpolation variables in free-form DRL blocks. Template Keys
      are formatted as documented in Drools Expert User Guide; i.e. @{keyName}. All Template Keys in 'free-form' LHS or
      RHS elements are considered 'Text' (i.e. you'll get a TextBox in the Template data screen). Data-types should be
      correctly escaped in the 'free-form' entry. For example: System.out.println("@{key}");</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Relational operators for Strings</title>

      <para>All guided rule editors (BRL, Rule Templates and Decision Tables) now support relation operators for String
      values.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guvnor requirements change</title>

      <para>Guvnor 5.4.x requires at least Java 6 to run. The Drools and jBPM
        will still run on Java 5. Guvnor 5.3.x hotfixes will still run on Java 5
        too.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guvnor configuration change</title>

      <para>Any custom configuration in the guvnor war in
        <filename>WEB-INF/components.xml</filename> must now happen in
        <filename>WEB-INF/beans.xml</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision table analysis</title>

      <para>On the bottom of Web decision tables, the button
        <guilabel>Analyze...</guilabel> that checks for issues in your decision
        table, now also checks for 2 new detections:</para>

      <section>
        <title>Duplicate match detection</title>

        <para>A duplicate match are 2 rows in a decision table that can both
          match but have the same actions.</para>

        <para>For example: a person between 20 and 40 has to pay a fee of 400
          and a person between 30 and 50 has to pay a fee of 400 too. These 2
          rows duplicate each other. If the fee would be different between them,
          then they would conflict each other.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Multiple values for one action detection</title>

        <para>A multiple values for one action match is 1 row in a decision
          table who's actions contradict itself. This is a common problem in
          limited entry tables, but rare in non-limited entry tables.</para>

        <para>For example: a person below 40 has to pay the standard fee (400)
          and also has to pay the youngster fee (200). Since fee can only be set
          once, that's a problem.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision table - BRL fragments</title>

      <para>BRL fragments can now be used for Condition and/or Action
        columns.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Adding a BRL fragment</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-advanced-columns.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A BRL fragment is a section of a rule created using Guvnor's (BRL)
        Guided Rule Editor: Condition columns permit the definition of "WHEN"
        sections and Action columns the definition of "THEN" sections. Fields
        defined therein as "Template Keys" become columns in the decision
        table.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>A Condition BRL fragment</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-brl-condition.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>An Action BRL fragment</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-brl-action.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Consequently any rule that could be defined with the (BRL) Guided
        Rule Editor can now be defined with a decision table; including
        free-format DRL and DSL Sentences.</para>

      <para>BRL fragments are fully integrated with other columns in the
        decision table, so that a Pattern or field defined in a regular column
        can be referenced in the BRL fragments and vice-versa.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>A decision table with BRL fragments and regular columns</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-brl-columns.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision table \ Template data copy and paste rows</title>

      <para>You can now copy and paste rows in both the guided Decision Table
        and Template Data editors.</para>

      <para>Simply right-click a row in the tables' left hand-side selector
        column and choose the appropriate operation.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Copying a row</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-copy-paste-rows.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>BRL Editor - Remove Constraint\Action Value definition</title>

      <para>When creating new constraints or actions in the BRL guided (rule)
        editor it is simple to define a value as literal, or formula or
        expression. However, up until now, changing the value type required
        deletion of the whole constraint or action. This release brings the
        ability to remove the value definition thus enabling you to change a
        literal value to a formula etc without needing to delete the whole
        constraint or action.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Copying a row</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/brl-remove-value-types.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Change-Set Editor</title>

      <para>A new Editor to create Change-Sets was added in Guvnor. Using this
        new editor you can create change-sets referencing packages, snapshots
        and even particular assets inside a package and expose them to external
        applications. For further information refer to the documentation.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Change-Set Editor</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/NewChangeSet1.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom Forms in DSL sentences</title>

      <para>Custom Forms is a feature that exists in Guvnor since 5.1.1. It
        basically allows you to define external applications that will be
        invoked by Rule Editor when a particular field of a particular Fact Type
        is being used in a rule.</para>

      <para>This feature is now also available to be used in DSL sentences.
        When defining a variable in a sentence you can now use this syntax for
        variable's definition:</para>

      <programlisting>{&lt;varName&gt;:CF:&lt;factType.fieldName&gt;}</programlisting>

      <para>If you have an active Working-Set defining a Custom Form
        configuration for factType.fieldName, the Custom Form will be invoked by
        Rule Editor while setting the value of that variable.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>BRL editor supports "timer" and "calendar" attributes</title>

      <para>Support has been added for the "timer" and "calendar" attributes.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Timer and Calendar</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/timerAndCalendarAttributes-guvnor-brl.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision Tables support "timer" and "calendar" attributes</title>

      <para>Support has been added for the "timer" and "calendar" attributes.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Timer and Calendar</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/timerAndCalendarAttributes-guvnor-dtable.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Guided Decision Tables import from XLS</title>

      <para>Uploading a XLS decision table results in the creation of numerous new assets, including (obviously)
        web-guided Decision Tables, functions, declarative types and modifications to package globals and imports etc
        (Queries are not converted, although supported in the XLS form, as Guvnor doesn't support them <link
            xlink:href="https://issues.jboss.org/browse/GUVNOR-1532">yet</link>).</para>

      <figure>
        <title>XLS decision table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-xls.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Guided decision table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-converted.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This is the first stage of "round-tripping" decision tables. We still need to add the ability to export a
        guided decision table back to XLS, plus we'd like to add tighter integration of updated XLS assets to their
        original converted cousins - so if a new version of the XLS decision table is uploaded the related assets'
        versions are updated (rather than creating new) upon conversion.</para>

      <para>This is a powerful enhancement and as such your feedback is critical to ensure we implement the feature as
        you'd like it to operate. Check it out, feedback your opinions and help guide the future work.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improved value editors for numerical types</title>

      <para>Numerical "value editors" (i.e. the text boxes for numerical values) in the BRL, Rule Template, Test
        Scenarios and Decision Table editors now support the types Byte, Short, Integer, Long, Double, Float, BigDecimal
        and BigInteger (and their primitive counterparts) correctly. The generated DRL is automatically appended with "B"
        or "I" type classifiers for BigDecimal and BigInteger values respectively, as provided for by Drools Expert. The
        Right-hand Side generates applicable DRL for BigDecimal and BigInteger values according to the rule's
        dialect.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Example of using a BigDecimal</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/guvnor-numeric-value-editors.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improved dependent enumerations support</title>

      <para>Dependent enumerations can now be used in both the Web Guided Decision Table editor and the Rule Template
        Data grid. Furthermore improvements were made to the operation of dependent enumerations in the BRL Guided Rule
        editor for sub-fields and expressions.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Dependent enumerations in the Web Guided Decision Table editor</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-dependent-enums.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improved Guided Decision Table default value support</title>

      <para>The editor to define a default value has been greatly improved:-</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A default value editor is correct for the data-type of the column's Fact\.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a "Value List" is provided, the default value needs to be one of the values in the list.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the column represents a field with an enumeration the default value must be one of the enumeration's
            members.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the column uses an operator that does not need a value (e.g. "is null") a default value cannot be
            provided.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the column field is a "dependent enumeration" the default value must be one of the permitted values
            based upon parent enumeration default values, if any.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default values are not required for Limited Entry tables.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Setting the default value of a Date column</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-default-1.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Setting the default value of a cell with a Value List</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/dtable-default-2.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Service Editor</title>

      <para>A new editor to create services was added in Guvnor. Service is a
        special asset that enables users configure KnowledgeBases and KSessions
        to be executed remotely for any sort of client application (via REST
        or SOAP).</para>
      <para>In order to expose those services, the editor generates automatically a
        war file that can be deployed on most platforms on most containers.
        For further information refer to the documentation.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>The new Service Editor</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/NewServiceConfig1.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section xml:id="releaseNotes_5.4.0_Planner">
    <title>Planner</title>

    <section>
      <title>Build-in move factories</title>

      <para>Planner now comes with 2 build-in move factories: <literal>GenericChangeMoveFactory</literal> and
      <literal>GenericSwapMoveFactory</literal>. Here's an example that uses both of them:</para>

      <programlisting>  &lt;localSearch&gt;
    &lt;selector&gt;
      &lt;selector&gt;
        &lt;moveFactoryClass&gt;org.drools.planner.core.move.generic.GenericChangeMoveFactory&lt;/moveFactoryClass&gt;
      &lt;/selector&gt;
      &lt;selector&gt;
        &lt;moveFactoryClass&gt;org.drools.planner.core.move.generic.GenericSwapMoveFactory&lt;/moveFactoryClass&gt;
      &lt;/selector&gt;
    &lt;/selector&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/localSearch&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>It's no longer required to write your own Move and MoveFactory implementations, but you still can (and mix
      those in too).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Benchmarker supports custom input and output files</title>

      <para>The Benchmarker can now read and write the input and output files
        from any format, through the <literal>ProblemIO</literal> interface. The
        default is still an XStream implementation.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New example selection screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/plannerExamplesAppScreenshot.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New example: TSP</title>

      <para>This is an implementation of the classic <emphasis>Traveling Salesman Problem</emphasis>: given a list of
        cities, find the shortest tour for a salesman that visits each city exactly once.</para>

      <para>See <link xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T5D3hTjZlRc">this video</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New example: Vehicle Routing</title>

      <para>This is an implementation of capacitated vehicle routing: Using a fleet of vehicles, transport items from
        the depot(s) to customers at different locations. Each vehicle can service multiple locations, but it has a
        limited capacity for items.</para>

      <para>In the screenshot below, there are 6 vehicles (the lines in different colors) that drop off 541 items at 33
        customer locations. Each vehicle can carry 100 items.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/vehicleRoutingScreenshot.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>See <link xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GybpV0uLrxc">this video</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Employee rostering example: better GUI</title>

      <para>The employee rostering example's GUI has been reworked to show shift assignment more clearly.</para>

      <para>See <link xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gxd-DqtK5Xc">this video</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Chaining support makes it easy to implement TSP and Vehicle Routing</title>

      <para>Untill now, implementing TSP or Vehicle Routing like problems in Planner was hard. The new chaining support
        makes it easy.</para>

      <para>You simply declare that a planning variable (<literal>previousAppearance</literal>) of this planning entity
        (<literal>VrpCustomer</literal>) is chained and therefor possibly referencing another planning entity
        (<literal>VrpCustomer</literal>) itself, creating a chain with that entity.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public class VrpCustomer implements VrpAppearance {

        ...

        @PlanningVariable(chained = true)
        @ValueRanges({
        @ValueRange(type = ValueRangeType.FROM_SOLUTION_PROPERTY, solutionProperty = "vehicleList"),
        @ValueRange(type = ValueRangeType.FROM_SOLUTION_PROPERTY, solutionProperty = "customerList",
        excludeUninitializedPlanningEntity = true)})
        public VrpAppearance getPreviousAppearance() {
        return previousAppearance;
        }

        ...
        }</programlisting>

      <para>This triggers automatic chain correction:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Release_Notes/chainCorrection.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Without any extra boilerplate code, this is compatible with:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Every optimization algorithm: including construction heuristics (first fit, first fit decreasing, ...),
            local search (tabu search, simmulated annealing), ...</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The generic build-in move factories. Note: currently there are chained alternatives for each move
            factory, but those will be unified with the originals soon.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Repeated planning, including real-time planning</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For more information, <link xlink:href="http://www.jboss.org/drools/documentation">read the Planner
        reference manual</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Tabu Search implementation: planning value tabu</title>

      <para>Property tabu has been renamed to planning entity tabu. Planning value tabu has been added. The generic
        moves support this out-of-the-box.</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;planningValueTabuSize&gt;5&lt;/planningValueTabuSize&gt;
        &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Score calculation with plain Java (no DRL)</title>

      <para>Planner can now alternatively, use a score calculation written in plain Java. Just implement this
        interface:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public interface SimpleScoreCalculator&lt;Sol extends Solution&gt; {

        Score calculateScore(Sol solution);

        }</programlisting>

      <para>See the CloudBalance example for an implementation.</para>

      <para>In this way, Planner does not use Drools at all. This allows you to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use Planner, even if your company forbids any other language than Java (including DRL).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Hook Planner up to an existing score calculation system, which you don't want to migrate to DRL at this
            time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Or just use Java if you prefer that over DRL.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>There is 2 Java ways implemented: <literal>SimpleScoreCalculator</literal> (which is simple and slow)
        and <literal>IncrementalScoreCalculator</literal> (which is fast).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Quick start tutorial</title>

      <para>The documentation now has a new chapter <emphasis>Quick start tutorial</emphasis>. It explains how to write
        the CloudBalance example from scratch. <link xlink:href="http://www.jboss.org/drools/documentation">Read the
          Planner reference manual</link>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="releaseNotes_5.4.0_Eclipse">
    <title>Eclipse plugin</title>
    <section>
      <title>Breakpoints in Rule RHS are not working with Java dialect</title>

      <para>Debugging with Java is not working. Debugging with MVEL is not affected. This will be fixed in the future releases before 5.4.0.Final</para> 
    </section>
  </section>

</section>
