<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>RuntimeManager</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>RuntimeManager has been introduced to simplify and empower usage of
    knowledge API especially in context of processes. It provides configurable
    strategies that control actual runtime execution (how KieSessions are
    provided) and by default provides following: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
           Singleton - runtime manager maintains single KieSession regardless of number of processes available 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           Per Request - runtime manager delivers new KieSession for every request 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           Per Process Instance - runtime manager maintains mapping between process instance and KieSession and always provides same KieSession whenever working with given process instance 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>Runtime Manager is primary responsible for mananging and delivering
    to the caller instances of RuntimeEngine. In turn RuntimeEngine
    encapsulates two the most important elements of jBPM engine:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>KieSession</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TaskService</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Both of these components are already configured to work with each
    other smoothly without additional configuration from end user. No more
    need to register human task handler or keeping track if it's connected to
    the service or not.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">public interface RuntimeManager {

	/**
	 * Returns &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; instance that is fully initialized:
	 * &lt;ul&gt;
	 * 	&lt;li&gt;KiseSession is created or loaded depending on the strategy&lt;/li&gt;
	 * 	&lt;li&gt;TaskService is initialized and attached to ksession (via listener)&lt;/li&gt;
	 * 	&lt;li&gt;WorkItemHandlers are initialized and registered on ksession&lt;/li&gt;
	 * 	&lt;li&gt;EventListeners (process, agenda, working memory) are initialized and added to ksession&lt;/li&gt;
	 * &lt;/ul&gt;
	 * @param context the concrete implementation of the context that is supported by given &lt;code&gt;RuntimeManager&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @return instance of the &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 */
    RuntimeEngine getRuntimeEngine(Context&lt;?&gt; context);
    
    /**
     * Unique identifier of the &lt;code&gt;RuntimeManager&lt;/code&gt;
     * @return
     */
    String getIdentifier();
   
    /**
     * Disposes &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; and notifies all listeners about that fact.
     * This method should always be used to dispose &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; that is not needed
     * anymore. &lt;br/&gt;
     * ksession.dispose() shall never be used with RuntimeManager as it will break the internal
     * mechanisms of the manager responsible for clear and efficient disposal.&lt;br/&gt;
     * Dispose is not needed if &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; was obtained within active JTA transaction, 
     * this means that when getRuntimeEngine method was invoked during active JTA transaction then dispose of
     * the runtime engine will happen automatically on transaction completion.
     * @param runtime
     */
    void disposeRuntimeEngine(RuntimeEngine runtime);
    
    /**
     * Closes &lt;code&gt;RuntimeManager&lt;/code&gt; and releases it's resources. Shall always be called when
     * runtime manager is not needed any more. Otherwise it will still be active and operational.
     */
    void close();
    
}</programlisting>

    <para>RuntimeEngine interface provides the most important methods to get
    access to engine components:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">public interface RuntimeEngine {

	/**
	 * Returns &lt;code&gt;KieSession&lt;/code&gt; configured for this &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @return
	 */
    KieSession getKieSession();
    
    /**
	 * Returns &lt;code&gt;TaskService&lt;/code&gt; configured for this &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @return
	 */
    TaskService getTaskService();   
}</programlisting>

    <para>RuntimeManager will ensure that regadless of the strategy it will
    provide same capabilities when it comes to initialization and
    configuration of the RuntimeEngine. That means</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>KieSession will be loaded with same factories (either in memory
        or JPA based)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>WorkItemHandlers will be registered on every KieSession (either
        loaded from db or newly created)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Event listeners (Process, Agenda, WorkingMemory) will be
        registered on every KieSession (either loaded from db or newly
        created)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TaskService will be configured with:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>JTA transaction mananger</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>same entity manager factory as for the KieSession</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>UserGroupCallback from environment</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>On the other hand RuntimeManager maintains the engine disposal as
    well by providing dedicated methods to dispose RuntimeEngine when it's no
    more needed to release any resources it might aquired.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Strategies</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Singleton strategy </emphasis>- instructs
    RuntimeManager to maintain single instance of RuntimeEngine (and in turn
    single instance of KieSession and TaskService). Access to the
    RuntimeEngine is synchronized and by that thread safe although it comes
    with performance penelty due to synchronization. This strategy is similar
    to what was available by default in jBPM version 5.x and it's considered
    easiest strategy and recommended to start with.</para>

    <para>It has following characteristics that are important to evaluate
    while considering it for given scenario:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>small memory footprint - single instance of runtime engine and
        task service</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>simple and compact in design and usage</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>good fit for low to medium load on process engine due to
        synchronized access</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>due to single KieSession instance all state objects (such as
        facts) are directly visible to all process instances and vice
        versa</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>not contextual - meaning when retrieving instances of
        RuntimeEngine from singleton RuntimeManager Context instance is not
        important and usually EmptyContext.get() is used although null
        argument is acceptable as well</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>keeps track of id of KieSession used between RuntimeManager
        restarts to ensure it will use same session - this id is stored as
        serialized file on disc in temp location that depends on the
        environment can be one of following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>value given by jbpm.data.dir system property</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>value given by jboss.server.data.dir system property</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>value given by java.io.tmpdir system property</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Per request strategy</emphasis> - instructs
    RuntimeManager to provide new instance of RuntimeEngine for every request.
    As request RuntimeManager will consider one or more invocations within
    single transaction. It must return same instance of RuntimeEngine within
    single transaction to ensure correctness of state as otherwise operation
    done in one call would not be visible in the other. This is sort of
    "stateless" strategy that provides only request scope state and once
    request is completed RuntimeEngine will be permanently destroyed -
    KieSession information will be removed from data base in case persistence
    was used.</para>

    <para>It has following characteristics:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>completely isolated process engine and task service operations
        for every request</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>completely stateless, storing facts makes sense only for the
        duration of the request</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>good fit for high load, stateless processes (no facts or timers
        involved that shall be preserved between requests)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>KieSession is only available during life time of request and at
        the end is destroyed</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>not contextual - meaning when retrieving instances of
        RuntimeEngine from per request RuntimeManager Context instance is not
        important and usually EmptyContext.get() is used although null
        argument is acceptable as well</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Per process instance strategy</emphasis> -
    instructs RuntimeManager to maintain strick relationship between
    KieSession and ProcessInstance. That means that KieSession will be
    available as long as ProcessInstance that it belongs to is active. This
    strategy provides most flexible approach to secure advanced capabilities
    of the engine like rule evaluation in isolation (for given process
    instance only), maximum performance and reduction of potential bottle
    necks intruduced by synchronization and at the same time reduces number of
    KieSessions to the actual number of process isntances rather than number
    of requests (in contrast to per request strategy).</para>

    <para>It has following characteristics:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>most advanced strategy to provide isolation to given process
        instance only</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>maintains strict relationship between KieSession and
        ProcessInstance to ensure it will always deliver same KieSession for
        given ProcessInstance</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>merges life cycle of KieSession with ProcessInstance making both
        to be disposed on process instance completion (complete or
        abort)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>allows to maintain data (such as facts, timers) in scope of
        process instance - only process instance will have access to that
        data</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>introduces bit of overhead due to need to look up and load
        KieSession for process instance</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>validates usage of KieSession so it cannot be (ab)used for other
        process instances, in such a case exception is thrown</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>is contextual - accepts following context instances:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>EmptyContext or null - when starting process instance as
            there is no process instance id available yet</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>ProcessInstanceIdContext - used after process instance was
            created</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>CorrelationKeyContext - used as an alternative to
            ProcessInstanceIdContext to use custom (business) key instead of
            process instance id</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>Regular usage scenario for RuntimeManager is:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>At application startup</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>build RuntimeManager and keep it for entire life time of the
            application, it's thread safe and can be (or even should be)
            accessed concurrently</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>At request</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>get RuntimeEngine from RuntimeManager using proper context
            instance dedicated to strategy of RuntimeManager</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>get KieSession and/or TaskService from RuntimeEngine</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>perform operations on KieSession and/or TaskService such as
            startProcess, completeTask, etc</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>once done with processing dispose RuntimeEngine using
            RuntimeManager.disposeRuntimeEngine method</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>At application shutdown</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>close RuntimeManager</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para/>

    <para><note>
        <para>When RuntimeEngine is obtained from RuntimeManager within active
        JTA transaction then there is no need to dispose RuntimeEngine at the
        end as RuntimeManager will automatically dipose the RuntimeEngine on
        transaction completion (regardless of the completion status commit or
        rollback)</para>
      </note></para>

    <section>
      <title>Example</title>

      <para>Here is how you can build RuntimeManager and get RuntimeEngine
      (that encapsulates KieSession and TaskService) from it:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">
    // first configure environment that will be used by RuntimeManager
    RuntimeEnvironment environment = RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder.Factory.get()
    .newDefaultInMemoryBuilder()
    .addAsset(ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource("BPMN2-ScriptTask.bpmn2"), ResourceType.BPMN2)
    .get();

    // next create RuntimeManager - in this case singleton strategy is chosen
    RuntimeManager manager = RuntimeManagerFactory.Factory.get().newSingletonRuntimeManager(environment);

    // then get RuntimeEngine out of manager - using empty context as singleton does not kep track
    // of runtime engine as there is only one
    RuntimeEngine runtime = manager.getRuntimeEngine(EmptyContext.get());

    // get KieSession from runtime runtimeEngine - already initialized with all handlers, listeners, etc that were configured
    // on the environment
    KieSession ksession = runtimeEngine.getKieSession();

    // add invocations to the process engine here,
    // e.g. ksession.startProcess(processId);

    // and last dispose the runtime engine
    manager.disposeRuntimeEngine(runtimeEngine);
  </programlisting>

      <para>This example provides simplest (minimal) way of using
      <emphasis>RuntimeManager</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>RuntimeEngine</emphasis> although it provides few quite
      valuable information:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>KieSession will be in memory only - by using
          newDefaultInMemoryBuilder</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>there will be single process available for execution - by
          adding it as an asset</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>TaskService will be configured and attached to KieSession via
          LocalHTWorkItemHandler to support user task capabilities within
          processes</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <para>The complexity of knowing when to create, dispose, register
    handlers, etc is taken away from the end user and moved to the runtime
    manager that knows when/how to perform such operations but still allows to
    have a fine grained control over this process by providing comprehensive
    configuration of the RuntimeEnvironment.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">
  public interface RuntimeEnvironment {

	/**
	 * Returns &lt;code&gt;KieBase&lt;/code&gt; that shall be used by the manager
	 * @return
	 */
    KieBase getKieBase();
    
    /**
     * KieSession environment that shall be used to create instances of &lt;code&gt;KieSession&lt;/code&gt;
     * @return
     */
    Environment getEnvironment();
    
    /**
     * KieSession configuration that shall be used to create instances of &lt;code&gt;KieSession&lt;/code&gt;
     * @return
     */
    KieSessionConfiguration getConfiguration();
    
    /**
     * Indicates if persistence shall be used for the KieSession instances
     * @return
     */
    boolean usePersistence();
    
    /**
     * Delivers concrete implementation of &lt;code&gt;RegisterableItemsFactory&lt;/code&gt; to obtain handlers and listeners
     * that shall be registered on instances of &lt;code&gt;KieSession&lt;/code&gt;
     * @return
     */
    RegisterableItemsFactory getRegisterableItemsFactory();
    
    /**
     * Delivers concrete implementation of &lt;code&gt;UserGroupCallback&lt;/code&gt; that shall be registered on instances 
     * of &lt;code&gt;TaskService&lt;/code&gt; for managing users and groups.
     * @return
     */
    UserGroupCallback getUserGroupCallback();
    
    /**
     * Delivers custom class loader that shall be used by the process engine and task service instances
     * @return
     */
    ClassLoader getClassLoader();
    
    /**
     * Closes the environment allowing to close all depending components such as ksession factories, etc 
     */
    void close();
  </programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>Building RuntimeEnvironment</title>

      <para>While RuntimeEnvironment interface provides mostly access to data
      kept as part of the environment and will be used by the RuntimeManager,
      users should take advantage of builder style class that provides fluent
      API to configure RuntimeEnvironment with predefined settings.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public interface RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder {

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder persistence(boolean persistenceEnabled);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder entityManagerFactory(Object emf);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder addAsset(Resource asset, ResourceType type);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder addEnvironmentEntry(String name, Object value);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder addConfiguration(String name, String value);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder knowledgeBase(KieBase kbase);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder userGroupCallback(UserGroupCallback callback);

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder registerableItemsFactory(RegisterableItemsFactory factory);

	public RuntimeEnvironment get();

	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder classLoader(ClassLoader cl);
	
	public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder schedulerService(Object globalScheduler); 
    
  </programlisting>

      <para>Instances of the RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder can be obtained via
      RuntimeEnvironmentBuilderFactory that provides preconfigured sets of
      builder to simplify and help users to build the environment for the
      RuntimeManager.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public interface RuntimeEnvironmentBuilderFactory {

	/**
     * Provides completely empty &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; instance that allows to manually
     * set all required components instead of relying on any defaults.
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt;
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newEmptyBuilder();
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newDefaultBuilder();
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * but it does not have persistence for process engine configured so it will only store process instances in memory
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newDefaultInMemoryBuilder();
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * This one is tailored to works smoothly with kjars as the notion of kbase and ksessions
     * @param groupId group id of kjar
     * @param artifactId artifact id of kjar
     * @param version version number of kjar
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newDefaultBuilder(String groupId, String artifactId, String version);
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * This one is tailored to works smoothly with kjars as the notion of kbase and ksessions
     * @param groupId group id of kjar
     * @param artifactId artifact id of kjar
     * @param version version number of kjar
     * @param kbaseName name of the kbase defined in kmodule.xml stored in kjar
     * @param ksessionName name of the ksession define in kmodule.xml stored in kjar
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newDefaultBuilder(String groupId, String artifactId, String version, String kbaseName, String ksessionName);
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * This one is tailored to works smoothly with kjars as the notion of kbase and ksessions
     * @param releaseId &lt;code&gt;ReleaseId&lt;/code&gt; that described the kjar
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newDefaultBuilder(ReleaseId releaseId);
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * This one is tailored to works smoothly with kjars as the notion of kbase and ksessions
     * @param releaseId &lt;code&gt;ReleaseId&lt;/code&gt; that described the kjar
     * @param kbaseName name of the kbase defined in kmodule.xml stored in kjar
     * @param ksessionName name of the ksession define in kmodule.xml stored in kjar
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newDefaultBuilder(ReleaseId releaseId, String kbaseName, String ksessionName);
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * It relies on KieClasspathContainer that requires to have kmodule.xml present in META-INF folder which 
     * defines the kjar itself.
     * Expects to use default kbase and ksession from kmodule.
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newClasspathKmoduleDefaultBuilder();
    
    /**
     * Provides default configuration of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is based on:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     * 	&lt;li&gt;DefaultRuntimeEnvironment&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * It relies on KieClasspathContainer that requires to have kmodule.xml present in META-INF folder which 
     * defines the kjar itself.
     * @param kbaseName name of the kbase defined in kmodule.xml
     * @param ksessionName name of the ksession define in kmodule.xml   
     * @return new instance of &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that is already preconfigured with defaults
     * 
     * @see DefaultRuntimeEnvironment
     */
    public RuntimeEnvironmentBuilder newClasspathKmoduleDefaultBuilder(String kbaseName, String ksessionName);</programlisting>

      <para>Besides KieSession Runtime Manager provides access to TaskService
      too as integrated component of a RuntimeEngine that will always be
      configured and ready for communication between process engine and task
      service.</para>

      <para>Since the default builder was used, it will already come with
      predefined set of elements that consists of:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Persistence unit name will be set to org.jbpm.persistence.jpa
          (for both process engine and task service)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Human Task handler will be automatically registered on
          KieSession</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JPA based history log event listener will be automatically
          registered on KieSession</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Event listener to trigger rule task evaluation (fireAllRules)
          will be automatically registered on KieSession</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para/>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Registering handlers and listeners</title>

      <para>To extend it with your own handlers or listeners a dedicated
      mechanism is provided that comes as implementation of
      RegisterableItemsFactory</para>

      <programlisting language="java">	/**
	 * Returns new instances of &lt;code&gt;WorkItemHandler&lt;/code&gt; that will be registered on &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @param runtime provides &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; in case handler need to make use of it internally
	 * @return map of handlers to be registered - in case of no handlers empty map shall be returned.
	 */
    Map&lt;String, WorkItemHandler&gt; getWorkItemHandlers(RuntimeEngine runtime);
    
    /**
	 * Returns new instances of &lt;code&gt;ProcessEventListener&lt;/code&gt; that will be registered on &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @param runtime provides &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; in case listeners need to make use of it internally
	 * @return list of listeners to be registered - in case of no listeners empty list shall be returned.
	 */
    List&lt;ProcessEventListener&gt; getProcessEventListeners(RuntimeEngine runtime);
    
    /**
	 * Returns new instances of &lt;code&gt;AgendaEventListener&lt;/code&gt; that will be registered on &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @param runtime provides &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; in case listeners need to make use of it internally
	 * @return list of listeners to be registered - in case of no listeners empty list shall be returned.
	 */
    List&lt;AgendaEventListener&gt; getAgendaEventListeners(RuntimeEngine runtime);
    
    /**
	 * Returns new instances of &lt;code&gt;WorkingMemoryEventListener&lt;/code&gt; that will be registered on &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt;
	 * @param runtime provides &lt;code&gt;RuntimeEngine&lt;/code&gt; in case listeners need to make use of it internally
	 * @return list of listeners to be registered - in case of no listeners empty list shall be returned.
	 */
    List&lt;WorkingMemoryEventListener&gt; getWorkingMemoryEventListeners(RuntimeEngine runtime);</programlisting>

      <para>A best practice is to just extend those that come out of the box
      and just add your own. Although extanstions are not always needed as the
      default implementations of RegisterableItemsFactory provides possibility
      to define custom handlers and listeners. Following is a list of
      available implementations that might be useful (they are ordered in the
      hierarchy of inheritance):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>org.jbpm.runtime.manager.impl.SimpleRegisterableItemsFactory -
          simplest possible implementations that comes empty and is based on
          reflection to produce instances of handlers and listeners based on
          given class names</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>org.jbpm.runtime.manager.impl.DefaultRegisterableItemsFactory
          - extension of the Simple implementation that introduces defaults
          described above and still provides same capabilities as Simple
          implementation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>org.jbpm.runtime.manager.impl.KModuleRegisterableItemsFactory
          - exension of default implementation that provides specific
          capabilities for kmodule and still provides same capabilities as
          Simple implementation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>org.jbpm.runtime.manager.impl.cdi.InjectableRegisterableItemsFactory
          - extension of default implementation that is tailored for CDI
          environments and provides CDI style approach to finding handlers and
          listeners via producers</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Alternatively, simple (stateless or requiring only KieSession)
      work item handlers might be registered in the well known way - defined
      as part of CustomWorkItem.conf file that shall be placed on class path.
      To use this approach do following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>create file "drools.session.conf" inside META-INF of the root
          of the class path, for web applications it will be
          WEB-INF/classes/META-INF</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>add following line to drools.session.conf file
          "drools.workItemHandlers = CustomWorkItemHandlers.conf"</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>create file "CustomWorkItemHandlers.conf" inside META-INF of
          the root of the class path, for web applications it will be
          WEB-INF/classes/META-INF</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>define custom work item handlers in MVEL style inside
          CustomWorkItemHandlers.conf</para>

          <programlisting>[
  "Log": new org.jbpm.process.instance.impl.demo.SystemOutWorkItemHandler(),
  "WebService": new org.jbpm.process.workitem.webservice.WebServiceWorkItemHandler(ksession),
  "Rest": new org.jbpm.process.workitem.rest.RESTWorkItemHandler(),
  "Service Task" : new org.jbpm.process.workitem.bpmn2.ServiceTaskHandler(ksession)
]</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>And that's it, now all these work item handlers will be registered
      for any KieSession created by that application, regardless if it uses
      RuntimeManager or not.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Registering handlers and listeners in CDI environment</title>

        <para>When using RuntimeManager in CDI environment there are dedicated
        interfaces that can be used to provide custom WorkItemHandlers and
        EventListeners to the RuntimeEngine.</para>

        <programlisting language="java">public interface WorkItemHandlerProducer {

    /**
     * Returns map of (key = work item name, value work item handler instance) of work items 
     * to be registered on KieSession
     * &lt;br/&gt;
     * Parameters that might be given are as follows:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     *  &lt;li&gt;ksession&lt;/li&gt;
     *  &lt;li&gt;taskService&lt;/li&gt;
     *  &lt;li&gt;runtimeManager&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * 
     * @param identifier - identifier of the owner - usually RuntimeManager that allows the producer to filter out
     * and provide valid instances for given owner
     * @param params - owner might provide some parameters, usually KieSession, TaskService, RuntimeManager instances
     * @return map of work item handler instances (recommendation is to always return new instances when this method is invoked)
     */
    Map&lt;String, WorkItemHandler&gt; getWorkItemHandlers(String identifier, Map&lt;String, Object&gt; params);
}</programlisting>

        <para>Event listener producer shall be annotated with proper qualifier
        to indicate what type of listeners they provide, so pick one of
        following to indicate they type:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>@Process - for ProcessEventListener</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>@Agenda - for AgendaEventListener</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>@WorkingMemory - for WorkingMemoryEventListener</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <programlisting language="java">public interface EventListenerProducer&lt;T&gt; {

    /**
     * Returns list of instances for given (T) type of listeners
     * &lt;br/&gt;
     * Parameters that might be given are as follows:
     * &lt;ul&gt;
     *  &lt;li&gt;ksession&lt;/li&gt;
     *  &lt;li&gt;taskService&lt;/li&gt;
     *  &lt;li&gt;runtimeManager&lt;/li&gt;
     * &lt;/ul&gt;
     * @param identifier - identifier of the owner - usually RuntimeManager that allows the producer to filter out
     * and provide valid instances for given owner
     * @param params - owner might provide some parameters, usually KieSession, TaskService, RuntimeManager instances
     * @return list of listener instances (recommendation is to always return new instances when this method is invoked)
     */
    List&lt;T&gt; getEventListeners(String identifier, Map&lt;String, Object&gt;  params);
}</programlisting>

        <para>Implementations of these interfaces shall be packaged as bean
        archive (includes beans.xml inside META-INF) and placed on application
        classpath (e.g. WEB-INF/lib for web application). THat is enough for
        CDI based RuntimeManager to discover them and register on every
        KieSession that is created or loaded from data store.</para>

        <para>Some parameters are provided to the producers to allow
        handlers/listeners to eb more stateful and be able to do more advanced
        things with the engine - like signal of the engine or process instance
        in case of an error. Thus all components are provided:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>KieSession</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>TaskService</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>RuntimeManager</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><note>
            <para>Whenever there is a need to interact with the process
            engine/task service from within handler or listener, recommended
            approach is to use RuntimeManager and retrieve RuntimeEngine (and
            then KieSession and/or TaskService) from it as that will ensure
            proper state managed according to strategy</para>
          </note></para>

        <para>In addition, some filtering can be applied based on identifier
        (that is given as argument to the methods) to decide if given
        RuntimeManager shall recieve handlers/listeners or not.</para>

        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
