<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="." xml:id="sect-formmodeler-UsingFormsclient"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Using forms on client applications</title>

  <para>
    This chapter intends to describe how you can embed process forms and interact with them on another webapp including the
    new Javascript API provided by the platform.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can find the library inside the <literal>kie-wb-*.war</literal> on the js file located on
    <literal>js/jbpm-forms-rest-integration.js</literal>.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>What does the API provides?</title>
    <para>
      This JavaScript API tries to be a simple mechanism to use forms on remote applications allowing to load the forms from
      different KIE Workbench instances, submit them, launch processes/tasks and execute callback functions when the actions are done.
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic methods are:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>showStartProcessForm(hostUrl, deploymentId, processId, divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Makes a call to the REST endpoint to obtain the form URL and if it gets a valid response will embed the process start form on the given div. The parameteres needed are:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>hostURL</emphasis>: the URL of the KIE Workbench instance that holds the deployments.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>deploymentId</emphasis>: the deployment identifier that contains the process to run.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>processId</emphasis>: the identifier of the process to run.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that has to contain the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if the form is going to be rendered. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to render the form. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>startProcess(divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Submits the form loaded on the given div and starts the process. The parameteres needed are:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that to contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed after the process is started. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to start the process. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>showTaskForm(hostUrl, taskId, divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Makes a call to the REST endpoint to obtain the form URL and if it gets a valid response will embed the task form on the given div. The parameteres needed are:</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>hostURL</emphasis>: the URL of the KIE Workbench instance that holds the deployments.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>taskId</emphasis>: the identifier of the task to show the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that has to contain the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if the form is going to be rendered. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to render the form. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>claimTask(divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Claims the task whose form is being rendered</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed after the task is claimed. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to claim the task. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>startTask(divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Starts the task whose form is being rendered</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed after the task is started. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to start the task. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>releaseTask(divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Releases the task whose form is being rendered</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed after the task is released. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to release the task. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>saveTask(divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Submits the form and saves the state of the task whose form is being rendered</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed after the task is saved. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to save the task. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>completeTask(divId, onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback):</command>
            Submits the form and completes task whose form is being rendered</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onsuccessCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed after the task is completed. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>onerrorCallback</emphasis> (optional): a javascript function that will be executed if any error occurs and it is impossible to complete the task. This function will receive the server response as a parameter</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>clearContainer(divId):</command>
            Cleans the div content and the related data stored on the component.</term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>divId</emphasis>: the identifier of the div that contains the form.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sample usage</title>
    <para>
      Now let's see an example how you can use the library to load the HR process form and start a new process instance.
      We are going to define a HTML page that will contain very simple components:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>"Show Process Form"</emphasis> BUTTON: The button that is going to make a call to a <emphasis>showProcessForm()</emphasis> function to embedd the process form.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>"myform"</emphasis> DIV: the div that will containt the form</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>"Start Process"</emphasis> BUTTON: the button that will call the <emphasis>startProcess()</emphasis> function that submits the form and start a new process instance. At the begining it will be hidden and only will be displayed when the form is going to be rendered.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      First we are look at the HTML code:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="html">
&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;script src="js/jbpm-forms-rest-integration.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
      var formsAPI = new jBPMFormsAPI();
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
  &lt;input type="button" id="showformButton"
      value="Show Process Form" onclick="showProcessForm()"&gt;
  &lt;p/&gt;
  &lt;div id="myform" style="border: solid black 1px; width: 500px; height: 200px;"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p/&gt;
  &lt;input type="button" id="startprocessButton"
      style="display: none;" value="Start Process" onclick="startProcess()"&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      Notice that in first place we have added the js library and created an instance of the jBPMFormsAPI object that
      will manage the form rendering.
    </para>
    <para>
      Now let's see how the <command>showProcessForm()</command> function looks like:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="javascript">
function showProcessForm() {
  var onsuccessCallback = function(response) {
    document.getElementById("showformButton").style.display = "none";
    document.getElementById("startprocessButton").style.display = "block";
  }

  var onerrorCallback = function(errorMessage) {
    alert("Unable to load the form, something wrong happened: " + errorMessage);
    formsAPI.clearContainer("myform");
  }
  formsAPI.showStartProcessForm("http://localhost:8080/kie-wb/", "org.jbpm:HR:1.0", "hiring", "myform", onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback);
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      As you can see, first we are defining the callback functions:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>onsuccessCallback:</command>
            This function is going to be called when the call to the REST endpoint and the form is going to be rendered.
            On this example we simply hide the <emphasis>"Show Process Form"</emphasis> button and show the
            <emphasis>"Start Process"</emphasis> button in  order to allow to submit the form and start the process.
            This function takes as a parameter the response of the REST call to inform the user that everything gone well.
          </term>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>onerrorCallback:</command>
            This function is going to be called if any error occurs (e.g. any communication error with the REST endpoint or unexpected js errors)
            On this example we simply show an alert showing the error message received and clear the <emphasis>"myform"</emphasis> DIV status.
          </term>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      Once we defined the callback function we proceed to call the <command>formsAPI.showStartProcessForm(...)</command> that is going
      make the REST call and embedd the form inside the specified div. Notice that we are providing a bunch of information
      in order to load the form, the URL where the KIE-Workbench is running (in this example "http://localhost:8080/kie-wb/"),
      the deployment where the process is located ("org.jbpm:HR:1.0"), the process id ("hiring"), the DIV id that is
      going to contain the form ("myform") and the callback functions (onsuccessCallback and onerrorCallback).
    </para>
    <para>
      Now let's take a look at the <emphasis>startProcess()</emphasis> that is the one that is going to submit the form
      and start the process:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="javascript">
function startProcess() {
  var onsuccessCallback = function(response) {
    document.getElementById("showformButton").style.display = "block";
    document.getElementById("startprocessButton").style.display = "none";
    formsAPI.clearContainer("myform");
    alert(response);
  }

  var onerrorCallback = function(response) {
    document.getElementById("showformButton").style.display = "block";
    document.getElementById("startprocessButton").style.display = "none";
    formsAPI.clearContainer("myform");
    alert("Unable to start the process, something wrong happened: " + response);
  }
  formsAPI.startProcess("myform", onsuccessCallback, onerrorCallback);
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      As <command>showProcessForm()</command>, first we are defining the callback functions. Both are doing basically the
      same:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show the <emphasis>"Show Process Form"</emphasis> button and hide the <emphasis>"Start Process"</emphasis>
            button to allow start another process instance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Clear the <emphasis>"myform"</emphasis> DIV status</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Show an alert with the response notifying that the process has started well or if an error occured</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Once that is done we just do the call to the <command>formsAPI.startProcess(...)</command> that will send a message
      to the component that renders the form inside the <emphasis>"myform"</emphasis> DIV and will exectue the callback
      functions when the action is done.
      Notice that we don't need the provide any other information than the DIV that contains the form and optionally the
      callback functions.
    </para>
    <para>
      With a simple code like this you'll be able to run process/task forms that are located on different Kie-Workbench
      instances from any other application.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Using forms on client applications I: Before showing the form</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/FormModeler/43_embed_form.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title>Using forms on client applications II: Showing the process form</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/FormModeler/44_embed_form.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <title>Using forms on client applications III: After process started</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/FormModeler/45_embed_form.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>
</section>
