<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Debugging</title>
    
  <para>This section describes how to debug processes using the jBPM Eclipse plugin.  This
  means that the current state of your running processes can be inspected
  and visualized during the execution.  Note that we currently don't
  allow you to put breakpoints on the nodes within a process directly.
  You can however put breakpoints inside any
  Java code you might have (i.e. your application code that is invoking
  the engine or invoked by the engine, listeners, etc.) or inside rules 
  (that could be evaluated in the context of a process).  At these
  breakpoints, you can then inspect the internal state of all your process instances.
  </para>

    <para>When debugging the application, you can use the following debug views to
    track the execution of the process:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>The process instances view, showing all running process instances (and 
        their state).  When double-clicking a process instance, the process instance view
        visually shows the current state of that process instance at that point in time.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The audit view, showing the audit log (note that you should probably
        use a threaded file logger if you want to session to save the audit event to the 
        file system on regular intervals, so the audit view can be update to show the latest
        state).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The global data view, showing the globals.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Other views related to rule execution like the working memory view 
        (showing the contents (data) in the working memory related to rule execution), the
        agenda view (showing all activated rules), etc.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

    <section>
      <title>The Process Instances View</title>

      <para>The process instances view shows the process instances currently running in the
      selected ksession.  To be able to use the process instances view, first open the
      Process Instances view (Window - Show View - Other ... and under the Drools category select
      Process Instances and Process Instance).  Tip: it might be useful to drag the Process Instance
      view to the Outline View and slightly enlarge it, as shown in the screenshot below, so you can
       see both the Process Instances and Process Instance views at the same time.</para>
      
      <para>Next, use a (regular) Java breakpoint to stop your application at a specific point (for example
      right after starting a new process instance). In the Debug perspective, select the ksession you would
      like to inspect, and the Process Instances view should show the process instances that are currently
      active inside that ksession.  For example, the screenshot below shows one running process instance
      (with id "1").  When double-clicking a process instance, the process instance viewer will 
      graphically show the progress of that process instance.  An example where the process instance is 
      waiting for a human actor to perform "Task 1" is shown below.</para>
      
      <note><para>The process instances view shows the process instances currently active inside
      the selected ksession.  Note that, when using persistence, process instances are not kept
      in memory inside the ksession, as they are stored in the database as soon as the command
      completes.  Therefore, you will not be able to use the Process Instances view when using
      persistence.  For example, when executing a JUnit test using the JbpmJUnitBaseTestCase,
      make sure to call "super(true, false);" in the constructor to create a runtime manager
      that is not using persistence.</para></note>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/Debugging.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <tip><para>When you double-click a process instance in the process instances view and
      the process instance view complains that it cannot find the process, this means
      that the plugin wasn't able to find the process definition of the selected process
      instance in the cache of parsed process definitions.  To solve this, simply change
      the process definition in question and save again (so it will be parsed) or rebuild
      the project that contains the process definition in question.</para></tip>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Audit View</title>
      <para>The audit view can be used to show the all the events inside an audit log in a tree-based
      manner.  An audit log is an XML-based log file which contains a log of all the events that
      occurred while executing a specific ksession.  To create a logger, use KieServices to create a
      new logger and attach it to a ksession. Be sure to close the logger after usage.</para>
      
      <programlisting language="java">KieRuntimeLogger logger = KieServices.Factory.get().getLoggers()
    .newThreadedFileLogger(ksession, "mylogfile", 1000);
// do something with the ksession here
logger.close();
      </programlisting>
      
      <para>To be able to use the Audit View, first open it (Window - Show View - Other ... and under
      the Drools category select Audit). To open up a log file in the audit view, open the selected
      log file in the audit view (using the "Open Log" action in the top right corner), or simply drag
      and drop the log file from the Package Explorer or Navigator into the audit view.  A tree-based
      view is generated based on the data inside the audit log.  An event is shown as a subnode of
      another event if the child event is caused by (a direct consequence of) the parent event.  
      An example is shown below.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
                     fileref="images/EclipseJBPM/audit.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <tip><para>Note that the file-based logger will only save the events on close (or when a certain
      threshold is reached).  If you want to make sure the events are saved on a regular interval
      (for example during debugging), make sure to use a threaded file logger, so the audit view can
      be update to show the latest state.  When creating a threaded file logger, you can specify the
      interval after which events should be saved to the file (in milliseconds).</para></tip>
        
    </section>

</section>
