<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Advanced Concepts and Theory</title>

  <section>
    <title>Truth Maintenance with <indexterm>
        <primary>Logical Object</primary>
      </indexterm> Logical Objects</title>

    <para>After regular inserts you have to retract facts explicitly. With
    <emphasis>logical</emphasis> assertions, the fact that was asserted will
    be automatically retracted when the conditions that asserted it in the
    first place are no longer true. Actually, it's even cleverer then that,
    because it will be retracted only if there isn't any single condition that
    supports the logical assertion.</para>

    <para>Normal insertions are said to be <emphasis>stated</emphasis>, i.e.,
    just like the intuitive meaning of "stating a fact" implies. Using a
    <code>HashMap</code> and a counter, we track how many times a particular
    equality is <emphasis>stated</emphasis>; this means we count how many
    different instances are equal.</para>

    <para>When we <emphasis>logically</emphasis> insert an object during a RHS
    execution we are said to <emphasis>justify</emphasis> it, and it is
    considered to be justified by the firing rule. For each logical insertion
    there can only be one equal object, and each subsequent equal logical
    insertion increases the justification counter for this logical assertion.
    A justification is removed by the LHS of the creating rule becoming
    untrue, and the counter is decreased accordingly. As soon as we have no
    more justifications the logical object is automatically retracted.</para>

    <para>If we try to <emphasis>logically</emphasis> insert an object when
    there is an equal <emphasis>stated</emphasis> object, this will fail and
    return null. If we <emphasis>state</emphasis> an object that has an
    existing equal object that is <emphasis>justified</emphasis> we override
    the Fact; how this override works depends on the configuration setting
    <code>WM_BEHAVIOR_PRESERVE</code>. When the property is set to discard we
    use the existing handle and replace the existing instance with the new
    Object, which is the default behavior; otherwise we override it to
    <emphasis>stated</emphasis> but we create an new
    <code>FactHandle</code>.</para>

    <para>This can be confusing on a first read, so hopefully the flow charts
    below help. When it says that it returns a new <code>FactHandle</code>,
    this also indicates the <code>Object</code> was propagated through the
    network.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Stated Insertion</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Stated_Assertion.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>Logical Insertion</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Logical_Assertion.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section>
      <title>Example Scenario</title>

      <para>An example may make things clearer. Imagine a credit card
      processing application, processing transactions for a given account and
      we have a working memory accumulating knowledge about a single account
      transaction. The rule engine is doing its best to decide whether
      transactions are possibly fraudulent or not. Imagine that this rule base
      basically has rules that kick in when there is "reason to be suspicious"
      and when "everything is normal".</para>

      <para>Of course there are many rules that operate no matter what,
      performing standard calculations, etc. Now there are possibly many
      reasons as to what could trigger a "reason to be suspicious": someone
      notifying the bank, a sequence of large transactions, transactions for
      geographically disparate locations, or even reports of credit card
      theft. Rather then smattering all the little conditions in lots of
      rules, imagine there is a fact class called "SuspiciousAccount".</para>

      <para>Then there can be a series of rules whose job is to look for
      things that may raise suspicion, and if they fire, they
      <emphasis>logically</emphasis> insert a new SuspiciousAccount()
      instance. All the other rules just have conditions like "not
      SuspiciousAccount()" or "SuspiciousAccount()" depending on their needs.
      Note that this has the advantage of allowing there to be many rules
      around raising suspicion, without touching the other rules. After all
      the facts causing the SuspiciousAccount() insertion are removed, the
      account handling reverts to a normal mode of operation where, for
      instance, a rule with "not SuspiciousAccount()" may kick in, which
      flushes through any blocked transactions.</para>

      <para>If you have followed this far, you will note that truth
      maintenance, like logical assertions, allows rules to behave a little
      like a human would, and can certainly make the rules more
      manageable.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Lazy Truth Maintenance</title>

      <para>You no longer need to enable or disable truth maintenance, via the
      kbase configuration. It is now handled automatically and turned on only
      when needed. This was done along with the code changes so that all entry
      points use the same code, previous to this the default entry point and
      named entry points used different code, to avoid TMS overhead for event
      processing.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Important note: Equality for Java objects</title>

      <para>It is important to note that for Truth Maintenance (and logical
      assertions) to work at all, your Fact objects (which may be JavaBeans)
      must override equals and hashCode methods (from java.lang.Object)
      correctly. As the truth maintenance system needs to know when two
      different physical objects are equal in value, <emphasis>both</emphasis>
      equals and hashCode must be overridden correctly, as per the Java
      standard.</para>

      <para>Two objects are equal if and only if their equals methods return
      true for each other and if their hashCode methods return the same
      values. See the Java API for more details (but do keep in mind you
      <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> override both equals and hashCode).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rete Algorithm</title>

    <para>The <emphasis>Rete</emphasis> algorithm was invented by Dr. Charles
    Forgy and documented in his PhD thesis in 1978-79. A simplified version of
    the paper was published in 1982 (<ulink
    url="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/context/505087/0">http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/context/505087/0</ulink>).
    The latin word "rete" means "net" or "network". The Rete algorithm can be
    broken into 2 parts: rule compilation and runtime execution.</para>

    <para>The compilation algorithm describes how the Rules in the Production
    Memory are processed to generate an efficient discrimination network. In
    non-technical terms, a discrimination network is used to filter data as it
    propagates through the network. The nodes at the top of the network would
    have many matches, and as we go down the network, there would be fewer
    matches. At the very bottom of the network are the terminal nodes. In Dr.
    Forgy's 1982 paper, he described 4 basic nodes: root, 1-input, 2-input and
    terminal.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Rete Nodes</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentdepth="244" contentwidth="392"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Rete_Nodes.png"
                     format=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The root node is where all objects enter the network. From there, it
    immediately goes to the ObjectTypeNode. The purpose of the ObjectTypeNode
    is to make sure the engine doesn't do more work than it needs to. For
    example, say we have 2 objects: Account and Order. If the rule engine
    tried to evaluate every single node against every object, it would waste a
    lot of cycles. To make things efficient, the engine should only pass the
    object to the nodes that match the object type. The easiest way to do this
    is to create an ObjectTypeNode and have all 1-input and 2-input nodes
    descend from it. This way, if an application asserts a new Account, it
    won't propagate to the nodes for the Order object. In Drools when an
    object is asserted it retrieves a list of valid ObjectTypesNodes via a
    lookup in a HashMap from the object's Class; if this list doesn't exist it
    scans all the ObjectTypeNodes finding valid matches which it caches in the
    list. This enables Drools to match against any Class type that matches
    with an <literal>instanceof</literal> check.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>ObjectTypeNodes</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Object_Type_Nodes.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>ObjectTypeNodes can propagate to AlphaNodes, LeftInputAdapterNodes
    and BetaNodes. AlphaNodes are used to evaluate literal conditions.
    Although the 1982 paper only covers equality conditions, many RETE
    implementations support other operations. For example, <code>Account.name
    == "Mr Trout"</code> is a literal condition. When a rule has multiple
    literal conditions for a single object type, they are linked together.
    This means that if an application asserts an Account object, it must first
    satisfy the first literal condition before it can proceed to the next
    AlphaNode. In Dr. Forgy's paper, he refers to these as IntraElement
    conditions. The following diagram shows the AlphaNode combinations for
    Cheese( name == "cheddar", strength == "strong" ):</para>

    <figure>
      <title>AlphaNodes</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Alpha_Nodes.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Drools extends Rete by optimizing the propagation from
    ObjectTypeNode to AlphaNode using hashing. Each time an AlphaNode is added
    to an ObjectTypeNode it adds the literal value as a key to the HashMap
    with the AlphaNode as the value. When a new instance enters the ObjectType
    node, rather than propagating to each AlphaNode, it can instead retrieve
    the correct AlphaNode from the HashMap,thereby avoiding unnecessary
    literal checks.</para>

    <para>There are two two-input nodes, JoinNode and NotNode, and both are
    types of BetaNodes. BetaNodes are used to compare 2 objects, and their
    fields, to each other. The objects may be the same or different types. By
    convention we refer to the two inputs as left and right. The left input
    for a BetaNode is generally a list of objects; in Drools this is a Tuple.
    The right input is a single object. Two Nodes can be used to implement
    'exists' checks. BetaNodes also have memory. The left input is called the
    Beta Memory and remembers all incoming tuples. The right input is called
    the Alpha Memory and remembers all incoming objects. Drools extends Rete
    by performing indexing on the BetaNodes. For instance, if we know that a
    BetaNode is performing a check on a String field, as each object enters we
    can do a hash lookup on that String value. This means when facts enter
    from the opposite side, instead of iterating over all the facts to find
    valid joins, we do a lookup returning potentially valid candidates. At any
    point a valid join is found the Tuple is joined with the Object; which is
    referred to as a partial match; and then propagated to the next
    node.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>JoinNode</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Join_Node.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To enable the first Object, in the above case Cheese, to enter the
    network we use a LeftInputNodeAdapter - this takes an Object as an input
    and propagates a single Object Tuple.</para>

    <para>Terminal nodes are used to indicate a single rule having matched all
    its conditions; at this point we say the rule has a full match. A rule
    with an 'or' conditional disjunctive connective results in subrule
    generation for each possible logically branch; thus one rule can have
    multiple terminal nodes.</para>

    <para>Drools also performs node sharing. Many rules repeat the same
    patterns, and node sharing allows us to collapse those patterns so that
    they don't have to be re-evaluated for every single instance. The
    following two rules share the first pattern, but not the last:</para>

    <programlisting>
    
    rule
    when
        Cheese( $cheddar : name == "cheddar" )
        $person : Person( favouriteCheese == $cheddar )
    then
        System.out.println( $person.getName() + " likes cheddar" );
    end
    
   </programlisting>

    <programlisting>
    
    rule
    when
        Cheese( $cheddar : name == "cheddar" )
        $person : Person( favouriteCheese != $cheddar )
    then
        System.out.println( $person.getName() + " does not like cheddar" );
    end
    
  </programlisting>

    <para>As you can see below, the compiled Rete network shows that the alpha
    node is shared, but the beta nodes are not. Each beta node has its own
    TerminalNode. Had the second pattern been the same it would have also been
    shared.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Node Sharing</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Engine/Node_Sharing.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
