<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="jBPMEclipse"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="EclipseModeler/" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Eclipse BPMN 2.0 Modeler</title>
  
<section>
  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>The Eclipse BPMN 2.0 Modeler allows you to specify business processes, choreographies,
  etc. using the BPMN 2.0 XML syntax (including BPMNDI for the graphical information). The editor
  itself is based on the Eclipse Graphiti framework and the Eclipse BPMN 2.0 EMF meta-model.</para>

  <para>Features:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>It supports almost all BPMN 2.0 process constructs and
    attributes (including lanes and pools, annotations and all the BPMN2 node
    types).</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Added additional support for the few custom attributes that jBPM
    introduces using a special jBPM Target Runtime.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Allows you to configure which elements and attributes you want
    use when modeling processes (so we can limit the constructs for example to
    the subset currently supported by jBPM, which is a profile supported by default,
     or even more if you like).</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>The BPMN2 Modeler project is being developed at eclipse.org, sponsored by Red Hat/JBoss.
  Red Hat understands the benefits of developing software in the community, and therefore, the Eclipse
  BPMN 2.0 Modeler was developed not just for the jBPM project only, but it can be used in a much broader
  context and is fully spec compliant.  jBPM-specific features are developed as part of a separate
  jBPM Target Runtime.  We welcome other organizations in contributing to this modeler as well and 
  (re)using the generic functionality and/or defining their own target runtime if necessary.  Not only
  is this a good thing for the community, but it also leaves the path open for the jBPM suite to evolve
  as new features are requested by customers.</para>

  <para>Many thanks go out to the people at Codehoop that did a great job in
  creating a first version of this editor.</para>
  
</section>

<section>
  <title>Installation</title>

    <para>The jBPM installer is capable of downloading and installing an Eclipse installation, including
    the Eclipse BPMN2 Modeler and the Drools and jBPM Eclipse plugin (with a full jBPM runtime preconfigured).
    </para>
    
    <tip><para>Using the jBPM installer is definitely the recommended starting point for most users.</para></tip>
    
    <para>You can however also download and install the jBPM Eclipse Plugin manually.  To do so, you need
     Eclipse 3.6.2 (Helios) or newer.  To install, startup Eclipse and install the Eclipse BPMN 2.0 Modeler
    from the following update site (from menu Help -&gt; Install new software
    and then add the update site in question by clicking the Add button,
    filling in a name and the correct URL as shown below). It will
    automatically download all other dependencies as well (e.g. Graphiti
    etc.)</para>

    <para>Eclipse 3.6 (Helios): <link xlink:href="http://download.eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/updates/helios">http://download.eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/updates/helios</link></para>

    <para>Eclipse 3.7 - 4.2.1 (Indigo - Juno): <link xlink:href="http://download.eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/updates/juno">http://download.eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/updates/juno</link></para>

    <para>Eclipse 4.3 (Kepler): <link xlink:href="http://download.eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/updates/kepler">http://download.eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/updates/kepler</link></para>

    <para>The project is hosted at eclipse.org and open for anyone to
    contribute. The project home page can he found here:</para>
    <para><link xlink:href="http://http://eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/">http://http://eclipse.org/bpmn2-modeler/</link></para>
    <para>Sources are available here (using Eclipse Public License v1.0):</para>
    <para><link xlink:href="https://git.eclipse.org/c/bpmn2-modeler/org.eclipse.bpmn2-modeler.git">https://git.eclipse.org/c/bpmn2-modeler/org.eclipse.bpmn2-modeler.git</link></para>
    <para>A community forum for posting questions and exchanging ideas is also available here:</para>
    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org/forums/">http://www.eclipse.org/forums/</link></para>
    <para>A Bugzilla bug tracking system is available for reporting new bugs, or checking the status of existing bugs, here:</para>
    <para><link xlink:href="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?product=BPMN2Modeler">https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?product=BPMN2Modeler</link></para>
    
  </section>
  
  <xi:include href="BPMN2Modeler.xml" />

</chapter>