<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="jBPMFlexibleProcesses"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="Overview/" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Flexible Processes</title>

  <para>Case management and its relation to BPM is a hot topic nowadays. There definitely
  seems to be a growing need amongst end users for more flexible and adaptive business processes,
  without ending up with overly complex solutions. Everyone seems to agree that using a 
  process-centric approach only in many cases leads to complex solutions that are hard to maintain.
  The "knowledge workers" no longer want to be locked into rigid processes but wants to have the 
  power and flexibility to regain more control over the process themselves.</para>

  <para>The term case management is often used in that context. Without trying to give a precise 
  definition of what it might or might not mean, as this has been a hot topic for discussion, it 
  refers to the basic idea that many applications in the real world cannot really be described 
  completely from start to finish (including all possible paths, deviations, exceptions, etc.). 
  Case management takes a different approach: instead of trying to model what should happen from 
  start to finish, let's give the end user the flexibility to decide what should happen at runtime. 
  In its most extreme form for example, case management doesn't even require any process definition 
  at all. Whenever a new case comes in, the end user can decide what to do next based on all the 
  case data.</para>

  <para>A typical example can be found in healthcare (clinical decision support to be more precise),
  where care plans can be used to describe how patients should be treated in specific circumstances,
  but people like general practitioners still need to have the flexibility to add additional steps 
  and deviate from the proposed plan, as each case is unique. And there are similar examples in 
  claim management, helpdesk support, etc.</para>

  <para>So, should we just throw away our BPM system then? No! Even at its most extreme form (where 
  we don't model any process up front), you still need a lot of the other features a BPM system 
  (usually) provides: there still is a clear need for audit logs, monitoring, coordinating various 
  services, human interaction (e.g. using task forms), analysis, etc. And, more importantly, many 
  cases are somewhere in between, or might even evolve from case management to more structured 
  business process over time (when we for example try to extract common approaches from many cases). 
  If we can offer flexibility as part of our processes, can't we let the users decide how and where 
  they would like to apply it?</para>

  <para>Let me give you two examples that show how you can add more and more flexibility to your 
  processes. The first example shows a care plan that shows the tasks that should be performed when 
  a patient has high blood pressure. While a large part of the process is still well-structured, 
  the general practitioner can decide himself which tasks should be performed as part of the 
  sub-process. And he also has the ability to add new tasks during that period, tasks that were not 
  defined as part of the process, or repeat tasks multiple times, etc. The process uses an ad-hoc 
  sub-process to model this kind of flexibility, possibly augmented with rules or event processing 
  to help in deciding which fragments to execute.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Healthcare: high blood pressure</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/FlexibleProcesses/Healthcare.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The second example actually goes a lot further than that. In this example, an internet provider 
  could define how cases about internet connectivity problems will be handled by the internet provider. 
  There are a number of actions the case worker can select from, but those are simply small process 
  fragments. The case worker is responsible for selecting what to do next and can even add new tasks 
  dynamically. As you can see, there is not process from start to finish anymore, but the user is 
  responsible for selecting which process fragments to execute.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Telecom: process fragments</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/FlexibleProcesses/Internet.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>And in its most extreme form, we even allow you to create case instances without a process 
  definition, where what needs to be performed is selected purely at runtime. This however doesn't 
  mean you can't figure out anymore what 's actually happening. For example, meetings can be very 
  adhoc and dynamic, but we usually want a log of what was actually discussed. The following 
  screenshot shows how our regular audit view can still be used in this case, and the end user 
  could then for example get a lot more info about what actually happened by looking at the data 
  associated with each of those steps. And maybe, over time, we can even automate part of that by 
  using a semi-structured process.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Audit log for dynamic case</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/FlexibleProcesses/Meeting.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
</chapter>
