<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The Apache Camel integration allows us to interact with a Drools
  Stateless or Stateful session through a pipeline. It simply works by
  transforming XML commands into executable commands and executing them. The
  advantage of this integration is that Apache Camel makes possible the
  implemention of more advanced enterprise integration patterns, which is an
  improvement of drools pipeline.</para>

  <para></para>

  <para>This integration with Drools allows us to add any of the current Camel
  components. Using the <link
  xlink:href="http://camel.apache.org/components.html">Apache
  Components</link> you can, receive commands from several entry points and
  send the execution result to another entry point. To name a few, JMS
  queue/Atom Feed/Mina connection/a Mail/etc. As you can see, this brings a
  more powerful interoperability mechanism to integrate your application with
  Drools</para>

  <section>
    <title>Architecture</title>

    <para>&lt;insert architecture graphic here&gt;</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction to drools-grid</title>

    <para>Introduction to drools-grid Camel integration is coupled with
    another drools module called: drools-grid. This module allow us to
    interact with Drools sessions independent of the JVM location. At the
    moment we can use two implementations:</para>

    <table>
      <title>drools-grid implementations</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Local</entry>

            <entry>Used when the drools sessions and clients are in the same
            JVM</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Remote</entry>

            <entry>Used when you have drools sessions on a remote JVM.
            Currently, the only implementation is based on Apache Mina.
            HornetQ support will be added in the next release</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para></para>

    <para>Drools Grid is embedded inside the Drools Camel component, so don't
    worry about further implementation information because this is hidden by
    Drools. With this information we can start to configure our Camel
    Context.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</section>
