<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>The Rule IDE (Eclipse)</title>

  <para>The Eclipse based IDE provides developers (and very technical users)
  with an environment to edit and test rules in various formats, and integrate
  it deeply with their applications. In cases where you prefer business rules
  and web tooling, you will want to look at the BRMS (but using the BRMS and
  the IDE together is not uncommon).</para>

  <para>The Drools IDE is delivered as an Eclipse plug-in, which allows you to
  author and manage rules from within Eclipse, as well as integrate rules with
  your application. This is an optional tool, and not all components are
  required to be used, you can use what components are relevant to you. The
  Drools IDE is also a part of the Red Hat Developer Studio (formerly known as
  JBoss IDE).</para>

  <para>This guide will cover some of the features of JBoss Drools, in as far
  as the IDE touches on them (it is assumed that the reader has some
  familiarity with rule engines, and Drools in particular. It is important to
  note that none of the underlying features of the rule engine are dependent
  on Eclipse, and integrators are free to use their tools of choice, as always
  ! Plenty of people use IntelliJ with rules, for instance.</para>

  <note>
    <para>You can get the plug-in either as a zip to download, or from an
    update site. Refer to the chapter on installation.</para>
  </note>

  <figure>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/all.png" format="PNG"
                   scalefit="1" width=""></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section>
    <title>Features Outline</title>

    <para>The rules IDE has the following features</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Textual/graphical rule editor</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>An editor that is aware of DRL syntax, and provides content
            assistance (including an outline view)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>An editor that is aware of DSL (domain specific language)
            extensions, and provides content assistance.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>RuleFlow graphical editor</para>

        <para>You can edit visual graphs which represent a process (a rule
        flow). The RuleFlow can then be applied to your rule package to have
        imperative control.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Wizards for fast creation of</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>a "rules" project</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a rule resource, either as a DRL file or a "guided rule
            editor" file (.brl)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a Domain Specific language</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a decision table</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a ruleflow</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A domain specific language editor</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create and manage mappings from your user's language to the
            rule language</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Rule validation</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>As rules are entered, the rule is "built" in the background
            and errors reported via the problem view where possible</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The above features make use of Eclipse infrastructure and features,
    with all of the power of Eclipse being available.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Drools Runtimes</title>

    <para>A Drools runtime is a collection of jar files that represent one
    specific release of the Drools project jars. To create a runtime, you must
    point the IDE to the release of your choice. If you want to create a new
    runtime based on the latest Drools project jars included in the plugin
    itself, you can also easily do that. You are required to specify a default
    Drools runtime for your Eclipse workspace, but each individual project can
    override the default and select the appropriate runtime for that project
    specifically.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Defining a Drools Runtime</title>

      <para>To define one or more Drools runtimes using the Eclipse
      preferences view you open up your Preferences, by selecting the
      "Preferences" menu item in the menu "Window". A "Preferences" dialog
      should show all your settings. On the left side of this dialog, under
      the Drools category, select "Installed Drools runtimes". The panel on
      the right should then show the currently defined Drools runtimes. If you
      have not yet defined any runtimes, it should look like the figure
      below.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1" width=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>To define a new Drools runtime, click on the add button. A dialog
      such as the one shown below should pop up, asking for the name of your
      runtime and the location on your file system where it can be
      found.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes-add.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>In general, you have two options:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you simply want to use the default jar files as included in
          the Drools Eclipse plugin, you can create a new Drools runtime
          automatically by clicking the "Create a new Drools 5 runtime ..."
          button. A file browser will show up, asking you to select the folder
          on your file system where you want this runtime to be created. The
          plugin will then automatically copy all required dependencies to the
          specified folder. After selecting this folder, the dialog should
          look like the figure shown below.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you want to use one specific release of the Drools project,
          you should create a folder on your file system that contains all the
          necessary Drools libraries and dependencies. Instead of creating a
          new Drools runtime as explained above, give your runtime a name and
          select the location of this folder containing all the required
          jars.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes-add2.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>After clicking the OK button, the runtime should show up in your
      table of installed Drools runtimes, as shown below. Click on checkbox in
      front of the newly created runtime to make it the default Drools
      runtime. The default Drools runtime will be used as the runtime of all
      your Drools project that have not selected a project-specific
      runtime.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes2.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1" width=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can add as many Drools runtimes as you need. For example, the
      screenshot below shows a configuration where two runtimes have been
      defined: a Drools 5.1.1 runtime and a Drools 5.2.0.M2 runtime. The
      Drools 5.1.1 runtime is selected as the default one.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes3.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1" width=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Note that you will need to restart Eclipse if you changed the
      default runtime and you want to make sure that all the projects that are
      using the default runtime update their classpath accordingly.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting a runtime for your Drools project</title>

      <para>Whenever you create a Drools project (using the New Drools Project
      wizard or by converting an existing Java project to a Drools project
      using the action "Convert to Drools Project" that is shown when you are
      in the Drools perspective and you right-click an existing Java project),
      the plugin will automatically add all the required jars to the classpath
      of your project.</para>

      <para>When creating a new Drools project, the plugin will automatically
      use the default Drools runtime for that project, unless you specify a
      project-specific one. You can do this in the final step of the New
      Drools Project wizard, as shown below, by deselecting the "Use default
      Drools runtime" checkbox and selecting the appropriate runtime in the
      drop-down box. If you click the "Configure workspace settings ..." link,
      the workspace preferences showing the currently installed Drools
      runtimes will be opened, so you can add new runtimes there.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes-newproject.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can change the runtime of a Drools project at any time by
      opening the project properties and selecting the Drools category, as
      shown below. Mark the "Enable project specific settings" checkbox and
      select the appropriate runtime from the drop-down box. If you click the
      "Configure workspace settings ..." link, the workspace preferences
      showing the currently installed Drools runtimes will be opened, so you
      can add new runtimes there. If you deselect the "Enable project specific
      settings" checkbox, it will use the default runtime as defined in your
      global preferences.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools-runtimes-project.png"
                     format="PNG" role="" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating a Rule Project</title>

    <para>The aim of the new project wizard is to set up an executable
    scaffold project to start using rules immediately. This will set up a
    basic structure, the classpath, sample rules and a test case to get you
    started.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>New rule project scaffolding</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/new_project1.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When you choose to create a new "rule project" you will get a choice
    to add some default artifacts to it, like rules, decision tables,
    ruleflows, etc. These can serve as a starting point, and will give you
    something executable almost immediately, which you can then modify and
    mould to your needs. The simplest case (a hello world rule) is shown
    below. Feel free to experiment with the plug-in at this point.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>New rule project result</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/new_project2.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The newly created project contains an example rule file (Sample.drl)
    in the src/rules directory and an example Java file (DroolsTest.java) that
    can be used to execute the rules in a Drools engine. You'll find this in
    the folder src/java, in the com.sample package. All the other jars that
    are necessary during execution are also added to the classpath in a custom
    classpath container called Drools Library. Rules do not have to be kept in
    "Java" projects at all, this is just a convenience for people who are
    already using Eclipse as their Java IDE.</para>

    <para>Important note: The Drools plug-in adds a "Drools Builder"
    capability to your Eclipse instance. This means you can enable a builder
    on any project that will build and validate your rules when resources
    change. This happens automatically with the Rule Project Wizard, but you
    can also enable it manually on any project. One downside of this is that
    if you have rule files with a large number of rules (more than 500 rules
    per file), it means that the background builder may be doing a lot of work
    to build the rules on each change. An option here is to turn off the
    builder, or put the large rules into .rule files, where you can still use
    the rule editor, but it won't build them in the background. To fully
    validate the rules you will need to run them in a unit test of
    course.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating a New Rule and Wizards</title>

    <para>You can create a rule simple as an empty text ".drl" file, or use
    the wizard to do so. The wizard menu can be invoked with Control+N, or by
    choosing it from the toolbar, where there is a menu with the JBoss Drools
    icon.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The wizard menu</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/wizards.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The wizard will ask for some basic options for generating a rule
    resource. These are just hints - you can change your mind later. For
    storing rule files you would typically create a directory src/rules and
    create suitably named subdirectories. The package name is mandatory, and
    is similar to a package name in Java; i.e., it establishes a namespace for
    grouping related rules.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>New rule wizard</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/new_rule.jpg"
                     format="JPG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The result of this wizard is a rule skeleton, for you to expand. As
    with all wizards, they are an optional help - you don't have to use them
    if you don't want to.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Textual Rule Editor</title>

    <para>The rule editor is where rule managers and developers will be
    spending most of their time. The rule editor follows the pattern of a
    normal text editor in Eclipse, with all the customary features of a text
    editor. On top of this, the rule editor provides pop-up content
    assistance. You invoke pop-up content assistance the "normal" way by
    pressing Control+Space.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The rule editor in action</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/editor1.jpg"
                     format="JPG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The rule editor works on files that have a .drl (or .rule)
    extension. Usually these contain related rules, but it would also be
    possible to have rules in individual files, grouped by being in the same
    package "namespace", if you so prefer. These DRL files are plain text
    files.</para>

    <para>You can see from the example above that the rule group is using a
    domain specific language. Note the expander keyword, which tells the rule
    compiler to look for a dsl file of that name, to resolve the rule
    language. Even with the domain specific language (DSL) the rules are still
    stored as plain text as you see it onscreen, which allows simpler
    management of rules and versions, e.g., comparing versions of
    rules.</para>

    <para>The editor has an outline view that is kept in sync with the
    structure of the rules; it is updated on save. This provides a quick way
    of navigating around rules by name, even in a file which may have hundreds
    of rules. The items are sorted alphabetically by default.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The rule outline view</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/outline.jpg"
                     format="JPG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Drools Views</title>

    <para>When debugging an application using a Drools engine, these views can
    be used to check the state of the Drools engine itself: the Working Memory
    View, the Agenda View, and the Global Data View. To be able to use these
    views, create breakpoints in your code invoking the working memory. For
    example, the line where you call workingMemory.fireAllRules() is a good
    candidate. If the debugger halts at that joinpoint, you should select the
    working memory variable in the debug variables view. The available views
    can then be used to show the details of the selected working
    memory:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Working Memory View shows all elements of the Drools working
        memory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Agenda View shows all elements on the agenda. For each rule
        on the agenda, the rule name and bound variables are shown.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Global Data View shows all global data currently defined in
        the Drools working memory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The Audit view can be used to display audit logs containing events
    that were logged during the execution of a rules engine, in tree
    form.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Working Memory View</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/workingMemory.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The Working Memory View shows all elements in the working memory
      of the Drools engine.</para>

      <para>An action is added to the right of the view, to customize what is
      shown:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Show Logical Structure toggles showing the logical
          structure of the elements in the working memory, or all their
          details. Logical structures allow for visualizing sets of elements
          in a more obvious way.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Agenda View</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/agenda.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The Agenda View shows all elements on the agenda. For each rule on
      the agenda, the rule name and bound variables are shown.</para>

      <para>An action is added to the right of the view, to customize what is
      shown:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Show Logical Structure toggles showing the logical
          structure of the agenda item, or all their details. Logical
          structures allow for example visualizing sets of elements in a more
          obvious way. The logical structure of AgendaItems shows the rule
          that is represented by the AgendaItem, and the values of all the
          parameters used in the rule.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Global Data View</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/globals.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The Global Data View shows all global data currently defined in
      the Drools engine.</para>

      <para>An action is added to the right of the view, to customize what is
      shown:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Show Logical Structure toggles showing the logical
          structure of the elements in the working memory, or all their
          details. Logical structures allow for example visualizing sets of
          elements in a more obvious way.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Audit View</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/audit.jpg" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>The audit view visualizes an audit log, that is optionally created
      when executing the rules engine. To create an audit log, use the
      following code:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">StatefulSession session = ruleBase.newStatefulSession();
// Create a new Working Memory Logger, that logs to file.
WorkingMemoryFileLogger logger = new WorkingMemoryFileLogger(session);
// An event.log file is created in the subdirectory log dir (which must exist) of the working directory
logger.setFileName("log/event");

        session.insert(...);
        session.fireAllRules();

// stop logging
logger.writeToDisk();</programlisting>

      <para>Open the log by clicking the Open Log action, the first icon in
      the Audit View, and select the file. The Audit View now shows all events
      that where logged during the executing of the rules. There are different
      types of events, each with a different icon:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Object inserted, a green square: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/greensquare.GIF"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Object updated, a yellow square: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/yellowsquare.GIF"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Object removed, a red square: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/redsquare.GIF"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Activation created, a right arrow: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/arrowright.GIF"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Activation cancelled, a left arrow: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/arrowleft.GIF"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Activation executed, a blue diamond: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/bluediamond.GIF"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ruleflow start or end, the "process" icon: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/process.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ruleflow-group activation or deactivation, the "activity"
          icon: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/activity.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rule package addition or removal, the Drools icon:
          <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rule addition or removal, the Drools icon: <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/drools.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>All these events show extra information concerning the event, like
      the id and toString representation of the object in case of working
      memory events (insert, modify and retract), the name of the rule and all
      the variables bound in the activation in case of an activation event
      (created, cancelled or executed). If an event occurs when executing an
      activation, it is shown as a child of the activation's execution event.
      For some events, you can retrieve the "cause":</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The cause of an object modified or retracted event is the last
          object event for that object. This is either the object asserted
          event, or the last object modified event for that object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The cause of an activation cancelled or executed event is the
          corresponding activation created event.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>When selecting an event, the cause of that event is shown in green
      in the audit view (if visible of course). You can also right click the
      action and select the "Show Cause" menu item. This will scroll you to
      the cause of the selected event.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Domain Specific Languages</title>

    <para>Domain Specific Languages (DSL) enable you to create a language that
    allows your rules to look like - rules! Most often the domain specific
    language reads like natural language. Typically you would look at how a
    business analyst would describe the rule, in their own words, and then map
    this to your object model, via rule constructs. A side benefit of this is
    that it can provide an insulation layer between your domain objects and
    the rules themselves (as we know you like to refactor). A domain specific
    language will grow as the rules grow, and works best when there are common
    terms used over an over, with different parameters.</para>

    <para>To aid with this, the rule workbench provides an editor for Domain
    Specific Languages. They are stored in a plain text format, so you can use
    any editor of your choice; this format is simply a slightly enhanced
    version of the "Properties" file format. The editor will be invoked on any
    files with a .dsl extension. There is also a wizard to create a sample
    DSL.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Editing languages</title>

      <figure>
        <title>The Domain Specific Language editor</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/dsl_editor.jpg"
                       format="JPG" width="100%"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The DSL editor provides a tabular view of the mapping of Language
      to Rule Expressions. The Language Expression is what is used in the
      rules. This also feeds the content assistance for the rule editor, so
      that it can suggest Language Expressions from the DSL configuration.
      (The rule editor loads the DSL configuration when the rule resource is
      loaded for editing.) The Rule language mapping defines the "code" for
      the rules into which the language expression will be compiled by the
      rule engine compiler. The form of this Rule language expression depends
      on it being intended for the condition or the action part of a rule.
      (For the RHS it may be a snippet of Java, for instance). The "scope"
      item indicates where the expression belongs, "when" indicating the LHS,
      "then" the RHS, and "*" meaning anywhere. It's also possible to create
      aliases for keywords.</para>

      <para>By selecting a mapping item (a row in the table) you can see the
      expression and mapping in the text fields below the table. Double
      clicking or pressing the edit button will open the edit dialog. Other
      buttons let you remove and add mappings. Don't remove mappings while
      they are still in use.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Language Mapping editor dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/mapping_editor.jpg"
                       format="JPG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Here is a short description of the DSL translation process. The
      parser reads the rule text in a DSL, line by line, and tries to match
      some "Language Expression", depending on the scope. After a match, the
      values that correspond to a placeholder between curly braces (e.g.,
      {age}) are extracted from the rule source. The placeholders in the
      corresponding "Rule Expression" are replaced by their corresponding
      value. In the example above, the natural language expression maps to two
      constraints on a fact of type Person, based on the fields age and
      location, and the {age} and {location} values are extracted from the
      original rule text.</para>

      <para>If you do not wish to use a language mapping for a particular rule
      in a drl, prefix the expression with &gt; and the compiler will not try
      to translate it according to the language definition. Also note that
      Domain Specific Languages are optional. When the rule is compiled, the
      .dsl file will also need to be available.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Rete View</title>

    <para>The Rete Tree View shows you the current Rete Network for your DRL
    file. You display it by clicking on the tab "Rete Tree" at the bottom of
    the DRL Editor window. With the Rete Network visualization being open, you
    can use drag-and-drop on individual nodes to arrange optimal network
    overview. You may also select multiple nodes by dragging a rectangle over
    them; then the entire group can be moved around. The Eclips toolbar icons
    for zooming in and out can be used in the customary manner.</para>

    <para>In the current release there is no export function to creates a gif
    or jpeg file. Meanwhile, please use ctrl + alt + print to create a copy of
    your current Eclipse window, and cut it off.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/thereteview.jpg"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The Rete View is an advanced feature which takes full advantage of
    the Eclipse Graphical Editing Framework (GEF).</para>

    <para>The Rete view works only in Drools Rule Projects, where the Drools
    Builder is set in the project´s properties.</para>

    <para>If you are using Drools in another type of project where you are not
    having a Drools Rule Project with the appropriate Drools Builder, you can
    use a workaround: Set up a little Drools Rule Project next to it, putting
    needed libraries into it, and the DRLs you want to inspect with the Rete
    View. Just click on the right tab below in the DRL Editor, followed by a
    click on "Generate Rete View".</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Large DRL Files</title>

    <para>Depending on the JDK you use, it may be necessary to increase the
    permanent generation max size. Both the SUN and the IBM JDK have a
    permanent generation, whereas BEA JRockit does not.</para>

    <para>To increase the permanent generation, start Eclipse with
    -XX:MaxPermSize=###m</para>

    <para>Example: c:\Eclipse\Eclipse.exe -XX:MaxPermSize=128m</para>

    <para>Rulesets of 4,000 rules or greater should set the permanent
    generation to at least 128Mb.</para>

    <note>
      <para>This may also apply to compiling large numbers of rules in
      general, as there is generally one or more classes per rule.</para>
    </note>

    <para>As an alternative to the above, you may put rules in a file with the
    ".rule" extension, and the background builder will not try to compile them
    with each change, which may provide performance improvements if your IDE
    becomes sluggish with very large numbers of rules.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Debugging Rules</title>

    <figure>
      <title>Debugging</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/debug-overview.png"
                     format="PNG" width="100%"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You can debug rules during the execution of your Drools application.
    You can add breakpoints in the consequences of your rules, and whenever
    such a breakpoint is encountered during the execution of the rules,
    execution is halted. You can then inspect the variables known at that
    point and use any of the default debugging actions to decide what should
    happen next: step over, continue, etc. You can also use the debug views to
    inspect the content of the working memory and the Agenda.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Creating Breakpoints</title>

      <para>You can add and remove rule breakpoints in DRL files in two ways,
      similar to adding breakpoints to Java files:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Double-click the ruler of the DRL editor at the line where you
          want to add a breakpoint. Note that rule breakpoints can only be
          created in the consequence of a rule. Double-clicking on a line
          where no breakpoint is allowed will do nothing. A breakpoint can be
          removed by double-clicking the ruler once more.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you right-click the ruler, a popup menu will show up,
          containing the "Toggle breakpoint" action. Note that rule
          breakpoints can only be created in the consequence of a rule. The
          action is automatically disabled if no rule breakpoint is allowed at
          that line. Clicking the action will add a breakpoint at the selected
          line, or remove it if there was one already.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The Debug Perspective contains a Breakpoints view which can be
      used to see all defined breakpoints, get their properties,
      enable/disable or remove them, etc.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Debugging Rules</title>

      <para>Drools breakpoints are only enabled if you debug your application
      as a Drools Application. You can do this like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Debug as Drools Application</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/debugAsDrools.png"
                       format="PNG" role="" width="100%"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the main class of your application. Right click it and
          select the "Debug As &gt;" sub-menu and select Drools Application.
          Alternatively, you can also select the "Debug ..." menu item to open
          a new dialog for creating, managing and running debug configurations
          (see the screenshot below).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the "Drools Application" item in the left tree and
          click the "New launch configuration" button (leftmost icon in the
          toolbar above the tree). This will create a new configuration with
          some of the properties (like project and main class)already filled
          in, based on the main class you selected in the beginning. All
          properties shown here are the same as for any standard Java
          program.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Change the name of your debug configuration to something
          meaningful. You can just accept the defaults for all other
          properties. For more information about these properties, please
          check the Eclipse JDT documentation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the "Debug" button on the bottom to start debugging your
          application. You only have to define your debug configuration once.
          The next time you run your Drools application, you don't have to
          create a new one but select the previously defined one in the tree
          on the left, as a sub-element of the "Drools Application" tree node,
          and then click the Debug button. The Eclipse toolbar also contains
          shortcut buttons to quickly re-execute one of your previous
          configurations (at least when one of the Java, Java Debug, or Drools
          perspectives has been selected).</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Debug as Drools Application Configuration</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/debug_rules_configuration.png"
                       format="PNG" role="" width="100%"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After clicking the "Debug" button, the application starts
      executing and will halt if any breakpoint is encountered. This can be a
      Drools rule breakpoint, or any other standard Java breakpoint. Whenever
      a Drools rule breakpoint is encountered, the corresponding DRL file is
      opened and the active line is highlighted. The Variables view also
      contains all rule parameters and their value. You can then use the
      default Java debug actions to decide what to do next: resume, terminate,
      step over, etc. The debug view can also be used to inspect the contents
      of the Working Memory and the Agenda at that time as well. You don't
      have to select a Working Memory now, as the current executing working
      memory is automatically shown.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Debugging</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-IDE/debug.png"
                       format="PNG" width="100%"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
