<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Package</title>

  <para>A package is a collection of rules and other related constructs, such
  as imports and globals. The package members are typically related to each
  other - perhaps HR rules, for instance. A package represents a namespace,
  which ideally is kept unique for a given grouping of rules. The package name
  itself is the namespace, and is not related to files or folders in any
  way.</para>

  <para>It is possible to assemble rules from multiple rule sources, and have
  one top level package configuration that all the rules are kept under (when
  the rules are assembled). Although, it is not possible to merge into the
  same package resources declared under different names. A single Rulebase
  may, however, contain multiple packages built on it. A common structure is to
  have all the rules for a package in the same file as the package declaration
  (so that is it entirely self-contained).</para>

  <para>The following railroad diagram shows all the components that may make
  up a package. Note that a package <emphasis>must</emphasis> have a namespace and be declared
  using standard Java conventions for package names; i.e., no spaces, unlike
  rule names which allow spaces. In terms of the order of elements, they can
  appear in any order in the rule file, with the exception of the <kw>package</kw>
  statement, which must be at the top of the file. In all cases, the semicolons are
  optional.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>package</title>

    <mediaobject>

      <imageobject>
	      <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Language/package.png" format="PNG" role="" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Notice that any rule atttribute (as described the section Rule Attributes)
  may also be written at package level, superseding the attribute's default value.
  The modified default may still be replaced by an attribute setting within
  a rule.</para>

  <section>
    <title>import</title>

    <figure>
      <title>import</title>

      <mediaobject>

        <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Language/import.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Import statements work like import statements in Java. You need to
    specify the fully qualified paths and type names for any objects you want
    to use in the rules. Drools automatically imports classes from the
    Java package of the same name, and also from the package
    <code>java.lang</code>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>global</title>

    <figure>
      <title>global</title>

      <mediaobject>

        <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Rule_Language/global.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>With <kw>global</kw> you define global variables. They are used to make
    application objects available to the rules. Typically, they are used
    to provide data or services that the rules use, especially application
    services used in rule consequences, and to return data from the rules,
    like logs or values added in rule consequences, or for the rules to
    interact with the application, doing callbacks. Globals are not 
    inserted into the Working Memory, and therefore a global should never be
    used to establish conditions in rules except when it has a
    constant immutable value. The engine cannot be notified about value
    changes of globals and does not track their changes. Incorrect use
    of globals in constraints may yield surprising results - surprising
    in a bad way.</para>

    <para>If multiple packages declare globals with the same identifier they
    must be of the same type and all of them will reference the same global
    value.</para>

    <para>In order to use globals you must:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Declare your global variable in your rules file and use it in
        rules. Example:</para>

        <programlisting>global java.util.List myGlobalList;

rule "Using a global"
when
    eval( true )
then
    myGlobalList.add( "Hello World" );
end
</programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Set the global value on your working memory. It is a best
        practice to set all global values before asserting any fact to the
        working memory. Example:</para>

        <programlisting>List list = new ArrayList();
WorkingMemory wm = rulebase.newStatefulSession();
wm.setGlobal( "myGlobalList", list );
</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Note that these are just named instances of objects that you pass in
    from your application to the working memory. This means you can pass in
    any object you want: you could pass in a service locator, or perhaps a
    service itself. With the new <kw>from</kw> element it is now common to pass a
    Hibernate session as a global, to allow <kw>from</kw> to pull data from a named
    Hibernate query.</para>

    <para>One example may be an instance of a Email service. In your
    integration code that is calling the rule engine, you obtain your
    emailService object, and then set it in the working memory. In the DRL,
    you declare that you have a global of type EmailService, and give it the
    name "email". Then in your rule consequences, you can use things like
    email.sendSMS(number, message).</para>

    <para>Globals are not designed to share data between rules and they should
    never be used for that purpose. Rules always reason and react to the
    working memory state, so if you want to pass data from rule to rule, assert
    the data as facts into the working memory.</para>

    <para>It is strongly discouraged to set or change a global value from
    inside your rules. We recommend to you always set the value from your
    application using the working memory interface.</para>
  </section>
</section>
