<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
  xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installing the Kie Execution Server</title>
  <para>The BRMS Execution Server is distributed as a web application archive (WAR) file with the
    name of kie-server.war. By default, when you install BRMS, this WAR file is installed and
    deployed in your web container. Consequently this gives you automatic access to this web
    application with the URL of <code>http://SERVER:PORT/CONTEXT/</code>. </para>
  <para>You can of course, copy this WAR file and deploy it in any other web container (Red Hat
    JBoss Web Server or another EAP install, for example) and have this execution server available
    from other web containers. Note that you must deploy the WAR file that is compatible for your
    web container. The BRMS Execution Server bundled with the EAP install is only suitable for
    installation on another EAP install, while the one bundled with the Generic deployment is
    suitable for installation on Red Hat JBoss Web Server only.</para>
  <para>To install the Kie Execution Server and verify it is running, complete the following
    steps:</para>
  <para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Deploy the WAR file into your web container.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a user with the role of <code>kie-server</code> on the web container.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Test that you can access the execution engine by navigating to the endpoint in a
          browser window: <code>http://SERVER:PORT/CONTEXT/services/rest/server/</code> with the web
          container running. For example, if the web container is running on your local machine and
          you are using the default context, you can access it on the following URL:
            <code>http://localhost:8080/kie-server-6.2.0.GA-redhat1/services/rest/server</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>When prompted for username/password, type in the username and password that you
          created in step 2.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Once authenticated, you will see an XML response in the form of engine status, similar
          to this:</para>
        <example>
            <title>sample handshaking server response</title>
            <programlisting>&lt;response type="SUCCESS" msg="Kie Server info" >
  &lt;kie-server-info>  
    &lt;version>6.2.0.GA-redhat-1&lt;/version>
  &lt;/kie-server-info>
&lt;/response>            </programlisting>
          </example>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
</section>
