<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Managing Containers</title>

  <para>Containers within the Execution Server can be started, stopped and updated from within
              KIE Workbench.⁠ </para>
       <section>
              <title>Starting a Container</title>
              <para>Once registered, a Container is in the 'Stopped' mode. It can be started by
                     first selecting it and then clicking the Start button. You can also select
                     multiple Containers and start them all at the same time. </para>
              <para>Once the Container is in the 'Running' mode, a green arrow appears next to it.
                     If there are any errors starting the Container(s), red icons appear next to
                     Containers and the Execution Server that they are deployed on. </para>
              <para>You should check the logs of both the Execution Server and the current Business
                     Central to see what the errors are before redeploying the Containers (and
                     possibly the Execution Server).⁠</para>
       </section>
       <section>
              <title>Stoping and Deleting a Container</title>
              <para>Similar to starting a Container, select the Container(s) that you want to
                     stop (or delete) and click the Stop button (which replaces the Start button for that
                     Container once it has entered the 'Running' mode) or the Delete button.⁠</para>
       </section>
       <section>
              <title>Updating a Container</title>
              <para>You can update deployed <code>KieContainers</code> without restarting the
                     Execution Server. This is useful in cases where the Business Rules change,
                     creating new versions of packages to be provisioned.</para>
              <para>You can have multiple versions of the same package provisioned and deployed,
                     each to a different <code>KieContainer</code>. </para>
              <para>To update deployments in a <code>KieContainer</code> dynamically, click on the
                     icon next to the Container. This will open up the Container Info screen. An
                     example of this screen is shown here:</para>
              <para>
                     <important>
                            <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,64,0"?>INSERT
                                   SCREENSHOT HERE<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                     </important>
              </para>
              <para>The Container Info screen is a useful tool because it not only allows you to see
                     the endpoint for this <code>KieContainer</code>, but it also allows you to
                     either manually or automatically refresh the provision if an update is
                     available. The update can be manual or automatic:</para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Manual Update:</emphasis> To manually update a
                            <code>KieContainer</code>, enter the new Version number in the Version
                     box and click on the <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis> button. You can of
                     course, update the Group Id or the Artifact Id , if these have changed as well.
                     Once updated, the Execution server updates the container and shows you the
                     resolved GAV attributes at the bottom of the screen in the <emphasis
                            role="bold">Resolved Release Id</emphasis> section. </para>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatic Update:</emphasis> If you want a deployed
                     Container to always have the latest version of your deployment without manually
                     editing it, you will need to set the Version property to the value of
                            <code>LATEST</code> and start a <code>Scanner</code>. This will ensure
                     that the deployed provision always contains the latest version. The Scanner can
                     be started just once on demand by clicking the Scan Now button or you can start
                     it in the background with scans happening at a specified interval (in
                     seconds).You can also set this value to <code>LATEST</code> when you are first
                     creating this deployment. The <emphasis role="bold">Resolved Release
                            Id</emphasis> in this case will show you the actual, latest version
                     number.</para>
       </section>
</section>
