<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Process Instance State</title>
 <para>jBPM allows the persistent storage of certain information. This chapter 
  describes these different types of persistence, and how to configure them.
  An example of the information stored is the process runtime state. Storing
  the process runtime state is necessary in order to be able to continue execution 
  of a process instance at any point, if something goes wrong. Also, the process 
  definitions themselves, and the history information (logs of current and previous 
  process states already) can also be persisted. 
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Runtime State</title>

    <para>Whenever a process is started, a process instance is created, which
    represents the execution of the process in that specific context.  For example,
    when executing a process that specifies how to process a sales order, one process
    instance is created for each sales request.  The process instance represents
    the current execution state in that specific context, and contains all the
    information related to that process instance.  Note that it only contains
    the (minimal) runtime state that is needed to continue the execution of that
    process instance at some later time, but it does not include information
    about the history of that process instance if that information is no longer
    needed in the process instance.</para>

    <para>The runtime state of an executing process can be made persistent,
    for example, in a database.  This allows to restore the state of
    execution of all running processes in case of unexpected failure,
    or to temporarily remove running instances from memory and restore
    them at some later time.  jBPM allows you to plug in different
    persistence strategies.  By default, if you do not configure the
    process engine otherwise, process instances are not made persistent.</para>
    
    <para>If you configure the engine to use persistence, it will automatically store
    the runtime state into the database.  You do not have to trigger persistence yourself,
    the engine will take care of this when persistence is enabled.  Whenever you invoke the
    engine, it will make sure that any changes are stored at the end of that invocation, at
    so-called safe points.  Whenever something goes wrong and you restore the engine from
    the database, you also should not reload the process instances and trigger them manually
    to resume execution, as process instances will automatically resume execution if they are
    triggered, like for example by a timer expiring, the completion of a task that was 
    requested by that process instance, or a signal being sent to the process instance.  The
    engine will automatically reload process instances on demand.</para>
    
    <para>The runtime persistence data should in general be considered internal, meaning that you
    probably should not try to access these database tables directly and especially not try
    to modify these directly (as changing the runtime state of process instances without the
    engine knowing might have unexpected side-effects).  In most cases where information about
    the current execution state of process instances is required, the use of a history log
    is mostly recommended (see below).  In some cases, it might still be useful to for example
    query the internal database tables directly, but you should only do this if you know what
    you are doing.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Binary Persistence</title>

    <para>jBPM uses a binary persistence mechanism, otherwise known
    as marshalling, which converts the state of the process instance
    into a binary dataset. When you use persistence with jBPM, this 
    mechanism is used to save or retrieve the process instance state 
    from the database. The same mechanism is also applied to the 
    session state and any work item states.</para> 

    <para>When the process instance state is persisted, two things
    happen: 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>First, the process instance information is transformed 
      into a binary blob. For performance reasons, a custom serialization 
      mechanism is used and not normal Java serialization.</listitem>
      <listitem>This blob is then stored, alongside other metadata about 
      this process instance. This metadata includes, among other things, 
      the process instance id, process id, and the process start date.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>Apart from the process instance state, the session itself can 
    also store some state, such as the state of timer jobs, or the session 
    data that any business rules would be evaluated over.
    This session state is stored separately as a binary blob, along with 
    the id of the session and some metadata. You can always restore session 
    state by reloading the session with the given id.  The session id can 
    be retrieved using <code>ksession.getId()</code>.</para>

    <para>Note that the process instance binary datasets are usually 
    relatively small, as they only contain the minimal execution state 
    of the process instance.  For a simple process instance, this usually 
    contains one or a few node instances, i.e., any node that is currently 
    executing, and any existing variable values.</para>
    
    <para>As a result of jBPM using marshalling, the data model is both 
    simple and small:</para>

    <!-- width && scalefit for PDFs -->
    <ulink url="images/Chapter-Persistence/jbpm_schema.png">
      <figure>
        <title>jBPM data model</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-7-Persistence/jbpm_schema_doc.png" format="PNG"
                       align="center" width="100%" scalefit="1" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </ulink>

    <para>The <code>sessioninfo</code> entity contains the state of the 
    (knowledge) session in which the jBPM process instance is running.</para>

    <table>
      <title>SessionInfo</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Field</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
          <entry>Nullable</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><code>id</code></entry>
          <entry>The primary key.</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>lastmodificationdate</code></entry>
          <entry>The last time that the entity was saved to the database</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>rulesbytearray</code></entry>
          <entry>The binary dataset containing the state of the session</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>startdate</code></entry>
          <entry>The start time of the session</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>optlock</code></entry>
          <entry>The version field that serves as its optimistic lock value</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    
    <para>The <code>processinstanceinfo</code> entity contains the state 
    of the jBPM process instance.</para>

    <table>
      <title>ProcessInstanceInfo</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Field</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
          <entry>Nullable</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><code>instanceid</code></entry>
          <entry>The primary key</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>lastmodificationdate</code></entry>
          <entry>The last time that the entity was saved to the database</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>lastreaddate</code></entry>
          <entry>The last time that the entity was retrieved (read) from the database</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>processid</code></entry>
          <entry>The name (id) of the process</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>processinstancebytearray</code></entry>
          <entry>This is the binary dataset containing the state of the process instance</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>startdate</code></entry>
          <entry>The start time of the process</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>state</code></entry>
          <entry>An integer representing the state of the process instance</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>optlock</code></entry>
          <entry>The version field that serves as its optimistic lock value</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <code>eventtypes</code> entity contains information
    about events that a process instance will undergo or has undergone.</para>

    <table>
      <title>EventTypes</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Field</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
          <entry>Nullable</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><code>instanceid</code></entry>
          <entry>This references the <code>processinstanceinfo</code> primary 
          key and there is a foreign key constraint on this column.</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>eventTypes</code></entry>
          <entry>A text field related to an event that the process has undergone.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <code>workiteminfo</code> entity contains the state of a work item.</para>

    <table>
      <title>WorkItemInfo</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Field</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
          <entry>Nullable</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><code>workitemid</code></entry>
          <entry>The primary key</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>creationDate</code></entry>
          <entry>The name of the work item</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>name</code></entry>
          <entry>The name of the work item</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>processinstanceid</code></entry>
          <entry>The (primary key) id of the process: there is no foreign key constraint 
          on this field.</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>state</code></entry>
          <entry>An integer representing the state of the work item</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>optlock</code></entry>
          <entry>The version field that serves as its optimistic lock value</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry><code>workitembytearay</code></entry>
          <entry>This is the binary dataset containing the state of the work item</entry>
          <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <code>CorrelationKeyInfo</code> entity contains information
      about correlation keys assigned to given process instance - loose relationship as this
      table is considered optional used only when correlation capabilities are required.</para>

    <table>
      <title>CorrelationKeyInfo</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Field</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
            <entry>Nullable</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>keyid</code></entry>
            <entry>The primary key</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>name</code></entry>
            <entry>assigned name of the correlation key</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>processinstanceid</code></entry>
            <entry>The id of the process instance which is assigned to this correlation key</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>optlock</code></entry>
            <entry>The version field that serves as its optimistic lock value</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <code>CorrelationPropertyInfo</code> entity contains information
      about correlation properties for given correlation key that is assigned to given process instance.</para>

    <table>
      <title>CorrelationPropertyInfo</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Field</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
            <entry>Nullable</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>propertyid</code></entry>
            <entry>The primary key</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>name</code></entry>
            <entry>The name of the property</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>value</code></entry>
            <entry>The value of the property</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>optlock</code></entry>
            <entry>The version field that serves as its optimistic lock value</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>correlationKey-keyid</code></entry>
            <entry>Foregin key to map to correlation key</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The <code>ContextMappingInfo</code> entity contains information
      about contextual information mapped to ksession. This is an internal part of RuntimeManager
    and can be considered optional when RuntimeManager is not used.</para>

    <table>
      <title>ContextMappingInfo</title>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Field</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
            <entry>Nullable</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><code>mappingid</code></entry>
            <entry>The primary key</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>context_id</code></entry>
            <entry>Identifier of the context</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>ksession?id</code></entry>
            <entry>Identifier of the ksession mapped to this context</entry>
            <entry>NOT NULL</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><code>optlock</code></entry>
            <entry>The version field that serves as its optimistic lock value</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Safe Points</title>

    <para>The state of a process instance is stored at so-called "safe points"
    during the execution of the process engine.  Whenever a process instance
    is executing (for example when it started or continuing from a previous wait state,
    the engine executes the process instance until no more actions can be performed (meaning
    that the process instance either has completed (or was aborted), or that it has reached a
    wait state in all of its parallel paths). At that point, the engine
    has reached the next safe state, and the state of the process instance
    (and all other process instances that might have been affected) is stored
    persistently.</para>
    </section>    
    </section> 
</section>
