<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xml:id="localSearch" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Local search</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Local search starts from an initial solution and evolves that single solution into a mostly better and better
    solution. It uses a single search path of solutions, not a search tree. At each solution in this path it evaluates a
    number of moves on the solution and applies the most suitable move to take the step to the next solution. It does
    that for a high number of iterations until it's terminated (usually because its time has run out).</para>

    <para>Local search acts a lot like a human planner: it uses a single search path and moves facts around to find a
    good feasible solution. Therefore it's pretty natural to implement.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Local search often needs to start from an initialized solution</emphasis>, therefore
    it's recommended to configure a construction heuristic solver phase before it.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="hillClimbing">
    <title>Hill climbing (simple local search)</title>

    <section>
      <title>Algorithm description</title>

      <para>Hill climbing tries all selected moves and then takes the best move, which is the move which leads to the
      solution with the highest score. That best move is called the step move. From that new solution, it again tries
      all selected moves and takes the best move and continues like that iteratively. If multiple selected moves tie for
      the best move, one of them is randomly chosen as the best move.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/hillClimbingNQueens04.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Notice that one a queen has moved, it can be moved again later. This is a good thing, because in an
      NP-complete problem it's impossible to predict what will be the optimal final value for a planning
      variable.</para>

      <para>Hill climbing can easily get stuck in a local optima:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/hillClimbingGetsStuckInLocalOptimaNQueens04.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Improvements upon hill climbing (such as tabu search and simulated annealing) address the problem of being
      stuck in local optima.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="tabuSearch">
    <title>Tabu search</title>

    <section>
      <title>Algorithm description</title>

      <para>Tabu search works like hill climbing, but it maintains a tabu list to avoid getting stuck in local optima.
      The tabu list holds recently used objects that are <emphasis>taboo</emphasis> to use for now. Moves that involve
      an object in the tabu list, are not accepted. The tabu list objects can be anything related to the move, such as
      the planning entity, planning value, move, solution, ... Here's an example with entity tabu for 4 queens, so the
      queens are put in the tabu list:</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/entityTabuSearch.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>See Tabu Search acceptor below.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="simulatedAnnealing">
    <title>Simulated annealing</title>

    <section>
      <title>Algorithm description</title>

      <para>Simulated annealing evaluates only a few moves per step, so it steps quickly. In the classic implementation,
      the first accepted move is the winning step. A move is accepted if it doesn't decrease the score or - in case it
      does decrease the score - if passes a random check. The chance that a decreasing move passes the random check
      decreases relative to the size of the score decrement and the time the phase has been running (which is
      represented as the temperature).</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/simulatedAnnealing.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>See Simulated Annealing acceptor below.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="lateAcceptance">
    <title>Late acceptance</title>

    <section>
      <title>Algorithm description</title>

      <para>Late acceptance (also known as Late acceptance hill climbing) also evaluates only a few moves per step. A
      move is accepted if it leads to a score that is at least the winning score of a fixed number of steps ago.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/lateAcceptance.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>By default hill climbing behaviour is enabled, which means that moves that lead to a score of at least the
      current solution are also accepted.</para>

      <para>See Late Acceptance acceptor below.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>About neighborhoods, moves and steps</title>

    <section>
      <title>Move generation tips</title>

      <para>At each solution, local search will try all possible moves and pick the best move to change to the next
      solution. It's up to you to generate those moves. Let's take a look at all the possible moves on the starting
      solution of 4 queens:</para>

      <para>It's highly recommended that you verify all solutions are connected by your move set. This means that by
      combining a finite number of moves you can reach any solution from any solution. Otherwise you're already
      excluding solutions at the start. Especially if you're using only big moves, you should check it. Just because big
      moves outperform small moves in a short test run, it doesn't mean that they will outperform them in a long test
      run.</para>

      <para>You can mix different move types. Usually you're better off preferring small (fine-grained) moves over big
      (course-grained) moves because the score delta calculation will pay off more. However, as the traveling tournament
      example proves, if you can remove a hard constraint by using a certain set of big moves, you can win performance
      and scalability. A big moves version could evaluate a lot less unfeasible solutions, which enables it to
      outperform and outscale a small moves version.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A step</title>

      <para>A step is the winning move. The local search solver tries every move on the current solution and picks the
      best accepted move as the step:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Decide the next step at step 0 (4 queens example)</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/decideNextStepNQueens04.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Because the move <emphasis>B0 to B3</emphasis> has the highest score (<literal>-3</literal>), it is picked
      as the next step. Notice that <emphasis>C0 to C3</emphasis> (not shown) could also have been picked because it
      also has the score <literal>-3</literal>. If multiple moves have the same highest score, one is picked randomly,
      in this case <emphasis>B0 to B3</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>The step is made and from that new solution, the local search solver tries all the possible moves again, to
      decide the next step after that. It continually does this in a loop, and we get something like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>All steps (4 queens example)</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/allStepsNQueens04.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Notice that the local search solver doesn't use a search tree, but a search path. The search path is
      highlighted by the green arrows. At each step it tries all possible moves, but unless it's the step, it doesn't
      investigate that solution further. This is one of the reasons why local search is very scalable.</para>

      <para>As you can see, the local search solver solves the 4 queens problem by starting with the starting solution
      and make the following steps sequentially:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>B0 to B3</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>D0 to B2</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>A0 to B1</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If we turn on <literal>debug</literal> logging for the category <literal>org.optaplanner</literal>, then
      those steps are shown into the log:</para>

      <programlisting>INFO  Solving started: time spend (0), score (-6), new best score (-6), random seed (0).
DEBUG     Step index (0), time spend (20), score (-3), new best score (-3), accepted/selected move count (12/12) for picked step (col1@row0 =&gt; row3).
DEBUG     Step index (1), time spend (31), score (-1), new best score (-1), accepted/selected move count (12/12) for picked step (col0@row0 =&gt; row1).
DEBUG     Step index (2), time spend (40), score (0), new best score (0), accepted/selected move count (12/12) for picked step (col3@row0 =&gt; row2).
INFO  Phase (0) localSearch ended: step total (3), time spend (41), best score (0).
INFO  Solving ended: time spend (41), best score (0), average calculate count per second (1780).</programlisting>

      <para>Notice that the logging uses the <literal>toString()</literal> method of our <literal>Move</literal>
      implementation: <literal>col1@row0 =&gt; row3</literal>.</para>

      <para>The local search solver solves the 4 queens problem in 3 steps, by evaluating only 37 possible solutions (3
      steps with 12 moves each + 1 starting solution), which is only fraction of all 256 possible solutions. It solves
      16 queens in 31 steps, by evaluating only 7441 out of 18446744073709551616 possible solutions. Note: with
      construction heuristics it's even a lot more efficient.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting stuck in local optima</title>

      <para>A <emphasis>hill climber</emphasis> always takes improving moves. This may seem like a good thing, but it's
      not. It suffers from a number of problems:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It can get stuck in a local optimum. For example if it reaches a solution X with a score -1 and there is
          no improving move, it is forced to take a next step that leads to a solution Y with score -2, after that
          however, it's very real that it will pick the step back to solution X with score -1. It will then start
          looping between solution X and Y.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>It can start walking in its own footsteps, picking the same next step at every step.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Of course OptaPlanner implements better local searches, such as <emphasis>tabu search</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>simulated annealing</emphasis> which can avoid these problems. We recommend to never use a hill climber,
      unless you're absolutely sure there are no local optima in your planning problem.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deciding the next step</title>

    <para>The local search solver decides the next step with the aid of 3 configurable components:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A <literal>MoveSelector</literal> which selects the possible moves of the current solution. See the
        chapter about Move and neighborhood selection.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An <emphasis>acceptor</emphasis> which filters out unacceptable moves. It can also weigh a move it
        accepts.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A <emphasis>forager</emphasis> which gathers all accepted moves and picks the next step from them.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Decide the next step at step 0 (4 queens example)</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Local_search/decideNextStepNQueens04.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In the above example the selector generated the moves shown with the blue lines, the acceptor accepted all of
    them and the forager picked the move <emphasis>B0 to B3</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>If we turn on <literal>trace</literal> logging for the category <literal>org.optaplanner</literal>, then the
    decision making is shown in the log:</para>

    <programlisting>INFO  Solver started: time spend (0), score (-6), new best score (-6), random seed (0).
TRACE         Move index (0) not doable, ignoring move (col0@row0 =&gt; row0).
TRACE         Move index (1), score (-4), accepted (true) for move (col0@row0 =&gt; row1).
TRACE         Move index (2), score (-4), accepted (true) for move (col0@row0 =&gt; row2).
TRACE         Move index (3), score (-4), accepted (true) for move (col0@row0 =&gt; row3).
...
TRACE         Move index (6), score (-3), accepted (true) for move (col1@row0 =&gt; row3).
...
TRACE         Move index (9), score (-3), accepted (true) for move (col2@row0 =&gt; row3).
...
TRACE         Move index (12), score (-4), accepted (true) for move (col3@row0 =&gt; row3).
DEBUG     Step index (0), time spend (6), score (-3), new best score (-3), accepted/selected move count (12/12) for picked step (col1@row0 =&gt; row3).
...</programlisting>

    <para>Because the last solution can degrade (especially in tabu search and simulated annealing), the
    <literal>Solver</literal> remembers the best solution it has encountered through the entire search path. Each time
    the current solution is better than the last best solution, the current solution is cloned and referenced as the new
    best solution.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Acceptor</title>

      <para>An acceptor is used (together with a forager) to active tabu search, simulated annealing, great deluge, ...
      For each move it checks whether it is accepted or not.</para>

      <para>You can implement your own <literal>Acceptor</literal>, although the build-in acceptors should suffice for
      most needs. You can also combine multiple acceptors.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Tabu search acceptor</title>

        <para>When tabu search takes steps it creates tabu's. It does not accept a move as the next step if that move
        breaks tabu. OptaPlanner implements several tabu types:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Solution tabu</emphasis> makes recently visited solutions tabu. It does not accept a move
            that leads to one of those solutions. If you can spare the memory, don't be cheap on the tabu size.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;solutionTabuSize&gt;1000&lt;/solutionTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Move tabu</emphasis> makes recent steps tabu. It does not accept a move equal to one of
            those steps.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;moveTabuSize&gt;7&lt;/moveTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Undo move tabu </emphasis>makes the undo move of recent steps tabu.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;undoMoveTabuSize&gt;7&lt;/undoMoveTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Planning entity tabu</emphasis> makes the planning entities of recent steps tabu. For
            example, for N queens it makes the recently moved queens tabu.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;entityTabuSize&gt;7&lt;/entityTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Planning value tabu</emphasis> makes the planning values of recent steps tabu. For example,
            for N queens it makes the recently moved to rows tabu.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;valueTabuSize&gt;7&lt;/valueTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>You can even combine tabu types:</para>

        <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
        &lt;solutionTabuSize&gt;1000&lt;/solutionTabuSize&gt;
        &lt;moveTabuSize&gt;7&lt;/moveTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>If you pick a too small tabu size, your solver can still get stuck in a local optimum. On the other hand,
        with the exception of solution tabu, if you pick a too large tabu size, your solver can get stuck by bouncing of
        the walls. Use the benchmarker to fine tweak your configuration. Experiments teach us that it is generally best
        to use a prime number for the move tabu, undo move tabu, entity tabu or value tabu size.</para>

        <para>A tabu search acceptor should be combined with a high subset selection, such as
        <literal>1000</literal>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simulated annealing acceptor</title>

        <para>Simulated annealing does not always pick the move with the highest score, neither does it evaluate many
        moves per step. At least at first. Instead, it gives non improving moves also a chance to be picked, depending
        on its score and the time gradient of the <literal>Termination</literal>. In the end, it gradually turns into a
        hill climber, only accepting improving moves.</para>

        <para>In many use cases, simulated annealing surpasses tabu search. By changing a few lines of configuration,
        you can easily switch from tabu search to simulated annealing and back.</para>

        <para>Start with a <literal>simulatedAnnealingStartingTemperature</literal> set to the maximum score delta a
        single move can cause. Use the <literal>Benchmarker</literal> to tweak the value.</para>

        <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
      &lt;simulatedAnnealingStartingTemperature&gt;2hard/100soft&lt;/simulatedAnnealingStartingTemperature&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;
    &lt;forager&gt;
        &lt;acceptedCountLimit&gt;4&lt;/acceptedCountLimit&gt;
    &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>A simulated annealing acceptor should be combined with a low subset selection. The classic algorithm uses
        a <literal>acceptedCountLimit</literal> of <literal>1</literal>, but usually <literal>4</literal> performs
        better.</para>

        <para>You can even combine it with a tabu acceptor at the same time. Use a lower tabu size than in a pure tabu
        search configuration.</para>

        <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
      &lt;simulatedAnnealingStartingTemperature&gt;10.0&lt;/simulatedAnnealingStartingTemperature&gt;
      &lt;entityTabuSize&gt;5&lt;/entityTabuSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;
    &lt;forager&gt;
        &lt;acceptedCountLimit&gt;4&lt;/acceptedCountLimit&gt;
    &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This differs from phasing, another powerful technique, where first simulated annealing is used, followed
        by tabu search.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Late acceptance acceptor</title>

        <para>Late acceptance accepts any move that has a score which is higher than the best score of a number of steps
        ago. That number of steps is the <literal>lateAcceptanceSize</literal>.</para>

        <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;acceptor&gt;
      &lt;lateAcceptanceSize&gt;500&lt;/lateAcceptanceSize&gt;
    &lt;/acceptor&gt;
    &lt;forager&gt;
        &lt;acceptedCountLimit&gt;1000&lt;/acceptedCountLimit&gt;
    &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Forager</title>

      <para>A forager gathers all accepted moves and picks the move which is the next step. Normally it picks the
      accepted move with the highest score. If several accepted moves have the highest score, one is picked
      randomly.</para>

      <para>You can implement your own <literal>Forager</literal>, although the build-in forager should suffice for most
      needs.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Subset selection</title>

        <para>When there are many possible moves, it becomes inefficient to evaluate all of them at every step. To
        evaluate only a random subset of all the moves, use:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>An <literal>acceptedCountLimit</literal> integer, which specifies how many accepted moves should be
            evaluated during each step. By default, all accepted moves are evaluated at every step.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">  &lt;forager&gt;
    &lt;acceptedCountLimit&gt;1000&lt;/acceptedCountLimit&gt;
  &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Unlike the n queens problem, real world problems require the use of subset selection. Start from an
        <literal>acceptedCountLimit</literal> that takes a step in less then 2 seconds. Turn on INFO logging to see the
        step times. Use the <literal>Benchmarker</literal> to tweak the value.</para>

        <important>
          <para>With a low <literal>acceptedCountLimit</literal> it is recommended to avoid using
          <literal>selectionOrder</literal> SHUFFLED because the shuffling generates a random number for every element
          in the selector, taking up a lot of time, but only a few are actually selected.</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Pick early type</title>

        <para>A forager can pick a move early during a step, ignoring subsequent selected moves. There are 3 pick early
        types:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>NEVER</literal>: A move is never picked early: all accepted moves are evaluated that the
            selection allows. This is the default.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;forager&gt;
        &lt;pickEarlyType&gt;NEVER&lt;/pickEarlyType&gt;
    &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>FIRST_BEST_SCORE_IMPROVING</literal>: Pick the first accepted move that improves the best
            score. If none improve the best score, it behaves exactly like the pickEarlyType NEVER.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;forager&gt;
        &lt;pickEarlyType&gt;FIRST_BEST_SCORE_IMPROVING&lt;/pickEarlyType&gt;
    &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>FIRST_LAST_STEP_SCORE_IMPROVING</literal>: Pick the first accepted move that improves the
            last step score. If none improve the last step score, it behaves exactly like the pickEarlyType
            NEVER.</para>

            <programlisting language="xml">    &lt;forager&gt;
        &lt;pickEarlyType&gt;FIRST_LAST_STEP_SCORE_IMPROVING&lt;/pickEarlyType&gt;
    &lt;/forager&gt;</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using a custom Termination, MoveSelector, EntitySelector, ValueSelector or Acceptor</title>

    <para>You can plug in a custom <literal>Termination</literal>, <literal>MoveSelector</literal>,
    <literal>EntitySelector</literal>, <literal>ValueSelector</literal> or <literal>Acceptor</literal> by extending the
    abstract class and also the related <literal>*Config</literal> class.</para>

    <para>For example, to use a custom <literal>MoveSelector</literal>, extend the
    <literal>AbstractMoveSelector</literal> class, extend the <literal>MoveSelectorConfig</literal> class and configure
    it in the solver configuration.</para>

    <note>
      <para>It's not possible to directly inject a <literal>Termination</literal>, ... instance, instead of also extend
      a <literal>Config</literal> class because:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A <literal>SolverFactory</literal> can build multiple <literal>Solver</literal> instances, which each
          require a distinct <literal>Termination</literal>, ... instance.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A solver configuration needs to be serializable to and from XML. This makes benchmarking with
          <literal>PlannerBenchmark</literal> particularly easy because you can configure different
          <literal>Solver</literal> variants in XML.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <literal>Config</literal> class is often easier and clearer to configure. For example:
          <literal>TerminationConfig</literal> translates <literal>maximumMinutesSpend</literal> and
          <literal>maximumSecondsSpend</literal> into <literal>maximumTimeMillisSpend</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </note>

    <para>If you build a better implementation that's not domain specific, consider contributing it back as a pull
    request on github and we'll optimize it and take it along in future refactors.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
