<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Declaring and Using Entry Points</title>

  <para>Entry points are declared implicitly in Drools by directly making use
  of them in rules. I.e. referencing an entry point in a rule will make the
  engine, at compile time, to identify and create the proper internal
  structures to support that entry point. </para>

  <para>So, for instance, lets imagine a banking application, where
  transactions are fed into the system coming from streams. One of the streams
  contains all the transactions executed in ATM machines. So, if one of the
  rules says: a withdraw is authorized if and only if the account balance is
  over the requested withdraw amount, the rule would look like:</para>

  <example>
      <title>Example of Stream Usage</title>

      <programlisting>rule "authorize withdraw"
when
    WithdrawRequest( $ai : accountId, $am : amount ) from entry-point "ATM Stream"
    CheckingAccount( accountId == $ai, balance &gt; $am )
then
    // authorize withdraw
end
</programlisting>
    </example>
  <para>In the previous example, the engine compiler will identify that
  the pattern is tied to the entry point "ATM Stream" and will both create all
  the necessary structures for the rulebase to support the "ATM Stream" and
  will only match WithdrawRequests coming from the "ATM Stream". In the
  previous example, the rule is also joining the event from the stream with a
  fact from the main working memory (CheckingAccount).</para>

  <para>Now, lets imagine a second rule that states that a fee of $2 must be
  applied to any account for which a withdraw request is placed at a bank
  branch:</para>

  <example>
      <title>Using a different Stream</title>

      <programlisting>rule "apply fee on withdraws on branches"
when
    WithdrawRequest( $ai : accountId, processed == true ) from entry-point "Branch Stream"
    CheckingAccount( accountId == $ai )
then
    // apply a $2 fee on the account
end
</programlisting>
    </example>
  <para>The previous rule will match events of the exact same type as
  the first rule (WithdrawRequest), but from two different streams, so an
  event inserted into "ATM Stream" will never be evaluated against the pattern
  on the second rule, because the rule states that it is only interested in
  patterns coming from the "Branch Stream".</para>

  <para>So, entry points, besides being a proper abstraction for streams, are
  also a way to scope facts in the working memory, and a valuable tool for
  reducing cross products explosions. But that is a subject for another
  time.</para>

  <para>Inserting events into an entry point is equally simple. Instead of
  inserting events directly into the working memory, insert them into the
  entry point as shown in the example below:</para>

  <example>
      <title>Inserting facts into an entry point</title>

      <programlisting language="java">// create your rulebase and your session as usual
StatefulKnowledgeSession session = ...

// get a reference to the entry point
WorkingMemoryEntryPoint atmStream = session.getWorkingMemoryEntryPoint( "ATM Stream" );

// and start inserting your facts into the entry point
atmStream.insert( aWithdrawRequest );
</programlisting>
    </example>

  <para>The previous example shows how to manually insert facts into a given
  entry point. Although, usually, the application will use one of the many
  adapters to plug a stream end point, like a JMS queue, directly into the
  engine entry point, without coding the inserts manually. The Drools pipeline
  API has several adapters and helpers to do that as well as examples on how
  to do it.</para>
</section>
