<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>OSGi</title>
    
      <para>All core jBPM JARs (and core dependencies) are OSGi-enabled.  That means that
      they contain MANIFEST.MF files (in the META-INF directory) that describe their
      dependencies etc.  These manifest files are automatically generated by the build.
      You can plug these JARs directly into an OSGi environment.</para>
      
  <para>OSGi is a dynamic module system for declarative services. So what does
  that mean? Each JAR in OSGi is called a bundle and has its own Classloader.
  Each bundle specifies the packages it exports (makes publicly available) and
  which packages it imports (external dependencies). OSGi will use this
  information to wire the classloaders of different bundles together; the key
  distinction is you don't specify what bundle you depend on, or have a single
  monolithic classpath, instead you specify your package import and version
  and OSGi attempts to satisfy this from available bundles.</para>

  <para>It also supports side by side versioning, so you can have multiple
  versions of a bundle installed and it'll wire up the correct one. Further to
  this Bundles can register services for other bundles to use. These services
  need initialisation, which can cause ordering problems - how do you make
  sure you don't consume a service before its registered? OSGi has a number of
  features to help with service composition and ordering. The two main ones
  are the programmatic ServiceTracker and the XML based Declarative Services.
  There are also other projects that help with this; Spring DM, iPOJO,
  Gravity.</para>

  <para> The following jBPM JARs are OGSi-enabled:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>jbpm-flow</listitem>
        <listitem>jbpm-flow-builder</listitem>
        <listitem>jbpm-bpmn2</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
</section>
