<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xml:id="welcome" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Welcome</title>

  <para>I've always stated that end business users struggle understanding the
  differences between rules and processes, and more recently rules and event
  processing. For them they have this problem in their mind and they just want
  to model it using some software. The traditional way of using two vendor
  offerings forces the business user to work with a process oriented or rules
  oriented approach which just gets in the way, often with great confusion
  over which tool they should be using to model which bit.</para>

  <para>PegaSystems and Microsoft have done a great job of showing that the
  two can be combined and a behavioural modelling approach can be used. This
  allows the business user to work more naturally where the full range of
  approaches is available to them, without the tools getting in the way. From
  being process oriented to rule oriented or shades of grey in the middle -
  whatever suites the problem being modelled at that time.</para>

  <para>Drools 5.0 takes this one step further by not only adding BPMN2 based
  workflow with Drools Flow but also adding event processing with Drools
  Fusion, creating a more holistic approach to software development. Where the
  term holistic is used for emphasizing the importance of the whole and the
  interdependence of its parts.</para>

  <para>Drools 5.0 is now split into 5 modules, each with their own manual -
  Guvnor (BRMS/BPMS), Expert (Rules), Fusion (CEP), Flow (Process/Workflow)
  and Planner. Guvnor is our web based governance system, traditionally
  referred to in the rules world as a BRMS. We decided to move away from the
  BRMS term to a play on governance as it's not rules specific. Expert is the
  traditional rules engine. Fusion is the event processing side, it's a play
  on data/sensor fusion terminology. Flow is our workflow module, Kris
  Verlaenen leads this and has done some amazing work; he's currently moving
  flow to be incorporated into jBPM 5. The fith module called Planner,
  authored by Geoffrey De Smet, solves allocation and scheduling type problem
  and while still in the early stage of development is showing a lot of
  promise. We hope to add Semantics for 2011, based around description logc,
  and that is being work on as part of the next generaion Drools
  designs.</para>

  <para>I've been working in the rules field now for around 7 years and I
  finally feel like I'm getting to grips with things and ideas are starting to
  gel and the real innovation is starting to happen. To me It feels like we
  actually know what we are doing now, compared to the past where there was a
  lot of wild guessing and exploration. I've been working hard on the next
  generation Drools Expert design document with Edson Tirelli and Davide
  Sottara. I invite you to read the document and get involved, <link
  xlink:href="http://community.jboss.org/wiki/DroolsLanguageEnhancements">http://community.jboss.org/wiki/DroolsLanguageEnhancements</link>.
  The document takes things to the next level pushing Drools forward as a
  hybrid engine, not just a capable production rule system, but also melding
  in logic programming (prolog) with functional programming and description
  logic along with a host of other ideas for a more expressive and modern
  feeling language.</para>

  <para>I hope you can feel the passion that my team and I have while working
  on Drools, and that some of it rubs off on you during your
  adventures.</para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Welcome/mark.png"></imagedata>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</chapter>
