<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Number Guess</title>

  <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Number Guess
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.numberguess.NumberGuessExample
<emphasis role="bold">Module:</emphasis> droolsjbpm-integration-examples
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> Java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> NumberGuess.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Demonstrate use of Rule Flow to organise Rules
</programlisting>

  <para>The "Number Guess" example shows the use of Rule Flow, a way of controlling the order in which rules are fired.
  It uses widely understood workflow diagrams for defining the order in which groups of rules will be executed.</para>

  <example>
    <title>Creating the Number Guess RuleBase: NumberGuessExample.main() - part 1</title>

    <programlisting language="java">final KnowledgeBuilder kbuilder = KnowledgeBuilderFactory.newKnowledgeBuilder();
kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "NumberGuess.drl",
                                                    ShoppingExample.class ),
              ResourceType.DRL );
kbuilder.add( ResourceFactory.newClassPathResource( "NumberGuess.rf",
                                                    ShoppingExample.class ),
              ResourceType.DRF );

final KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages() );</programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>The creation of the package and the loading of the rules (using the <code>add()</code> method) is the same as
  the previous examples. There is an additional line to add the Rule Flow (<filename>NumberGuess.rf</filename>), which
  provides the option of specifying different rule flows for the same Knowledge Base. Otherwise, the Knowledge Base is
  created in the same manner as before.</para>

  <example>
    <title>Starting the RuleFlow: NumberGuessExample.main() - part 2</title>

    <programlisting language="java">final StatefulKnowledgeSession ksession = kbase.newStatefulKnowledgeSession();

KnowledgeRuntimeLogger logger =
  KnowledgeRuntimeLoggerFactory.newFileLogger(ksession, "log/numberguess");

ksession.insert( new GameRules( 100, 5 ) );
ksession.insert( new RandomNumber() );
ksession.insert( new Game() );

ksession.startProcess( "Number Guess" );
ksession.fireAllRules();

logger.close();

ksession.dispose();</programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>Once we have a Knowledge Base, we can use it to obtain a Stateful Session. Into our session we insert our facts,
  i.e., standard Java objects. (For simplicity, in this sample, these classes are all contained within our
  <filename>NumberGuessExample.java</filename> file. Class <code>GameRules</code> provides the maximum range and the
  number of guesses allowed. Class <code>RandomNumber</code> automatically generates a number between 0 and 100 and
  makes it available to our rules, by insertion via the <code>getValue()</code> method. Class <code>Game</code> keeps
  track of the guesses we have made before, and their number.</para>

  <para>Note that before we call the standard <code>fireAllRules()</code> method, we also start the process that we
  loaded earlier, via the <code>startProcess()</code> method. We'll learn where to obtain the parameter we pass ("Number
  Guess", i.e., the identifier of the rule flow) when we talk about the rule flow file and the graphical Rule Flow
  Editor below.</para>

  <para>Before we finish the discussion of our Java code, we note that in some real-life application we would examine
  the final state of the objects. (Here, we could retrieve the number of guesses, to add it to a high score table.) For
  this example we are content to ensure that the Working Memory session is cleared by calling the <code>dispose()</code>
  method.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>RuleFlow for the NumberGuess Example</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-ruleflow.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>If you open the <filename>NumberGuess.rf</filename> file in the Drools IDE (provided you have the JBoss Rules
  extensions installed correctly in Eclipse) you should see the above diagram, similar to a standard flowchart. Its
  icons are similar (but not exactly the same) as in the JBoss jBPM workflow product. Should you wish to edit the
  diagram, a menu of available components should be available to the left of the diagram in the IDE, which is called the
  <emphasis>palette</emphasis>. This diagram is saved in XML, an (almost) human readable format, using XStream.</para>

  <para>If it is not already open, ensure that the Properties View is visible in the IDE. It can be opened by clicking
  "Window", then "Show View" and "Other", where you can select the "Properties" view. If you do this
  <emphasis>before</emphasis> you select any item on the rule flow (or click on the blank space in the rule flow) you
  should be presented with the following set of properties.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Properties for the Number Guess Rule Flow</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-ruleflow-properties.png" width="100%"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Keep an eye on the Properties View as we progress through the example's rule flow, as it presents valuable
  information. In this case, it provides us with the identification of the Rule Flow Process that we used in our earlier
  code snippet, when we called <code>session.startProcess()</code>.</para>

  <para>In the "Number Guess" Rule Flow we encounter several node types, many of them identified by an icon.</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Start node (white arrow in a green circle) and the End node (red box) mark beginning and end of the
        rule flow.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Rule Flow Group box (yellow, without an icon) represents a Rule Flow Groups defined in our rules (DRL)
        file that we will look at later. For example, when the flow reaches the Rule Flow Group "Too High", only those
        rules marked with an attribute of <literal>ruleflow-group</literal> <code>"Too High"</code> can potentially
        fire.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Action nodes (yellow, cog-shaped icon) perform standard Java method calls. Most action nodes in this
        example call <code>System.out.println()</code>, indicating the program's progress to the user.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Split and Join Nodes (blue ovals, no icon) such as "Guess Correct?" and "More guesses Join" mark places
        where the flow of control can split, according to various conditions, and rejoin, respectively</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Arrows indicate the flow between the various nodes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>The various nodes in combination with the rules make the Number Guess game work. For example, the "Guess" Rule
  Flow Group allows only the rule "Get user Guess" to fire, because only that rule has a matching attribute of
  <literal>ruleflow-group</literal> <code>"Guess"</code>.</para>

  <example>
    <title>A Rule firing only at a specific point in the Rule Flow: NumberGuess.drl</title>

    <programlisting>rule "Get user Guess"
    ruleflow-group "Guess"
    no-loop
    when
        $r : RandomNumber()
        rules : GameRules( allowed : allowedGuesses )
        game : Game( guessCount &lt; allowed )
        not ( Guess() )
    then
        System.out.println( "You have " + ( rules.allowedGuesses - game.guessCount )
                            + " out of " + rules.allowedGuesses
                            + " guesses left.\nPlease enter your guess from 0 to "
                            + rules.maxRange );
        br = new BufferedReader( new InputStreamReader( System.in ) );
        i = br.readLine();        
        modify ( game ) { guessCount = game.guessCount + 1 }
        insert( new Guess( i ) );
end</programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>The rest of this rule is fairly standard. The LHS section (after <literal>when</literal>) of the rule states
  that it will be activated for each <code>RandomNumber</code> object inserted into the Working Memory where
  <code>guessCount</code> is less than <code>allowedGuesses</code> from the <code>GameRules</code> object and where the
  user has not guessed the correct number.</para>

  <para>The RHS section (or consequence, after <literal>then</literal>) prints a message to the user and then awaits
  user input from <code>System.in</code>. After obtaining this input (the <code>readLine()</code> method call blocks
  until the return key is pressed) it modifies the guess count and inserts the new guess, making both available to the
  Working Memory.</para>

  <para>The rest of the rules file is fairly standard: the package declares the dialect as MVEL, and various Java
  classes are imported. In total, there are five rules in this file:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Get User Guess, the Rule we examined above.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A Rule to record the highest guess.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A Rule to record the lowest guess.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A Rule to inspect the guess and retract it from memory if incorrect.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A Rule that notifies the user that all guesses have been used up.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>One point of integration between the standard Rules and the RuleFlow is via the
  <literal>ruleflow-group</literal> attribute on the rules, as dicussed above. A <emphasis>second point of integration
  between the rules (.drl) file and the Rules Flow .rf files</emphasis> is that the Split Nodes (the blue ovals) can use
  values in the Working Memory (as updated by the rules) to decide which flow of action to take. To see how this works,
  click on the "Guess Correct Node"; then within the Properties View, open the Constraints Editor by clicking the button
  at the right that appears once you click on the "Constraints" property line. You should see something similar to the
  diagram below.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Edit Constraints for the "Guess Correct" Node</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-editconstraints.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Click on the "Edit" button beside "To node Too High" and you'll see a dialog like the one below. The values in
  the "Textual Editor" window follow the standard rule format for the LHS and can refer to objects in Working Memory.
  The consequence (RHS) is that the flow of control follows this node (i.e., "To node Too High") if the LHS expression
  evaluates to true.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Constraint Editor for the "Guess Correct" Node: value too high</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Examples/NumberGuessExample/numberguess-constraint-toohigh.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Since the file <filename>NumberGuess.java</filename> contains a <code>main()</code> method, it can be run as a
  standard Java application, either from the command line or via the IDE. A typical game might result in the interaction
  below. The numbers in bold are typed in by the user.</para>

  <example>
    <title>Example Console output where the Number Guess Example beat the human!</title>

    <programlisting>You have 5 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">50</emphasis>
Your guess was too high
You have 4 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">25</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have 3 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">37</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have 2 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">44</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have 1 out of 5 guesses left.
Please enter your guess from 0 to 100
<emphasis role="bold">47</emphasis>
Your guess was too low
You have no more guesses
The correct guess was 48 

</programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>A summary of what is happening in this sample is:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The <code>main()</code> method of <filename>NumberGuessExample.java</filename> loads a Rule Base, creates a
      Stateful Session and inserts <code>Game</code>, <code>GameRules</code> and <code>RandomNumber</code> (containing
      the target number) objects into it. The method also sets the process flow we are going to use, and fires all
      rules. Control passes to the Rule Flow.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>File <filename>NumberGuess.rf</filename>, the Rule Flow, begins at the "Start" node.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Control passes (via the "More guesses" join node) to the Guess node.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>At the Guess node, the appropriate Rule Flow Group ("Get user Guess") is enabled. In this case the Rule
      "Guess" (in the <filename>NumberGuess.drl</filename> file) is triggered. This rule displays a message to the user,
      takes the response, and puts it into Working Memory. Flow passes to the next Rule Flow Node.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>At the next node, "Guess Correct", constraints inspect the current session and decide which path to
      take.</para>

      <para>If the guess in step 4 was too high or too low, flow proceeds along a path which has an action node with
      normal Java code printing a suitable message and a Rule Flow Group causing a highest guess or lowest guess rule to
      be triggered. Flow passes from these nodes to step 6.</para>

      <para>If the guess in step 4 was right, we proceed along the path towards the end of the Rule Flow. Before we get
      there, an action node with normal Java code prints a statement "you guessed correctly". There is a join node here
      (just before the Rule Flow end) so that our no-more-guesses path (step 7) can also terminate the Rule Flow.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Control passes as per the Rule Flow via a join node, a guess incorrect Rule Flow Group (triggering a rule to
      retract a guess from Working Memory) onto the "More guesses" decision node.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The "More guesses" decision node (on the right hand side of the rule flow) uses constraints, again looking
      at values that the rules have put into the working memory, to decide if we have more guesses and if so, goto step
      3. If not, we proceed to the end of the rule flow, via a Rule Flow Group that triggers a rule stating "you have no
      more guesses".</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The loop over steps 3 to 7 continues until the number is guessed correctly, or we run out of guesses.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
