<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Golfing Example</title>

    <screen><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> Golfing
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.golfing.GolfingExample
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> golf.drl
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Configuration example that finds the solution from a large number of available cross products
</screen>

    <para>The golf example solves a "riddle" style problem that is simple enough to state in sentences, but for which a conventional algorithmic solution is not obvious. It does this by searching for a suitable combination from a "space" of possible solutions.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The riddle</title>

      <para>The problem is written as a riddle:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A foursome of golfers is standing at a tee, in a line from left to right.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Each golfer wears different colored pants; one is wearing red pants.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The golfer to Fred's immediate right is wearing blue pants.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Joe is second in line.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Bob is wearing plaid pants.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Tom isn't in position one or four, and he isn't wearing the hideous orange pants.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The immediate thing about this riddle, is that a solution is not obvious (of course ! it wouldn't be a riddle otherwise !). It also isn't obvious how to write an algorithm to solve it (if it is for you - then you can take a break now, go have a coffee or someting to reward your uber intellect).</para>

      <para>Instead of thinking about how to solve it, we can be lazy and use rules instead. So we don't attempt to solve it, we just state the problem in rules, and let the engine derive the solution.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Launching the example</title>

      <para>The supporting code is in the GolfingExample.java class. There is an inner class "Golfer" which represents a golf player, it has their name, position (1 to 4 meaning left to right), and their pants color, as simple properties.</para>

      <screen>String[] names = new String[] { "Fred", "Joe", "Bob", "Tom" };
String[] colors = new String[] { "red", "blue", "plaid", "orange" };
int[] positions = new int[] { 1, 2, 3, 4 };
        
for ( int n = 0; n &lt; names.length; n++ ) {
    for ( int c = 0; c &lt; colors.length; c++ ) {
        for ( int p = 0; p &lt; positions.length; p++ ) {
            session.insert( new Golfer( names[n], colors[c], positions[p]) );
        }                
    }            
}      </screen>

      <para>The above listing shows the interesting part of the supporting code. Note that we have arrays representing each name, color, and position. We then go through a nested loop inserting instances of Golfer - so in the working memory we will have all combinations of name, color and position. It is then the job of the rules to find the appropriate one.</para>

      <para>Launching the code as a java application should yield the following output:</para>

      <programlisting>Fred 1 orange
Joe 2 blue
Bob 4 plaid
Tom 3 red     </programlisting>

      <para>This shows that the rule(s) have found a suitable solution.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The matching rule</title>

      <para>The solution in rules is quite simple, it is a single rule which expresses the constraints as stated in the riddle. Effectively, we can interpret the riddle as a series of constraints on our object model. Given that we have enough "combinations" in the working memory, all we have to do is express the constraints in a rule and the engine will match it with a solution (we don't really care how it does it, as long as it works !).</para>

      <para>There is one rule in the solution, in golf.drl, called "find solution". The rule is made up of 5 patterns, with constraints that map to items in the riddle.</para>

      <programlisting>$fred : Golfer( name == "Fred" )      </programlisting>

      <para>In the above pattern, we are simply matching a Golfer who is called fred, and binding it to a variable called $fred. All that we know is that there is a golfer called fred.</para>

      <programlisting>$joe : Golfer( name == "Joe",
               position == 2,
               position != $fred.position,
               color != $fred.color )      </programlisting>

      <para>The next pattern says that we have a golfer named Joe, in position 2 ("second in line"). Now, we also know that he must NOT be in the same position as fred (of course !) and have different color pants. So far, nothing that amazing.</para>

      <programlisting>$bob : Golfer( name == "Bob",
               position != $fred.position,
               position != $joe.position,
               color == "plaid",
               color != $fred.color,
               color != $joe.color )      </programlisting>

      <para>Refering to the above, we also know there is a golfer called Bob, who wears plaid pants - once again that all we know about him. but of course, we add in the constraints that he must be in a different position to fred, joe, and also have different colored pants.</para>

      <programlisting>$tom : Golfer( name == "Tom",
               position != 1,
               position != 4,
               position != $fred.position,
               position != $joe.position,
               position != $bob.position,
               color != "orange,               
               color != $fred.color,
               color != $joe.color,
               color != $bob.color )      </programlisting>

      <para>(referring to the above) We also know that there is a guy called Tom, who doesn't wear the Orange pants, AND he is not in position 1, or 4. Of course we also add in the other constraints (he must be in a different position to the others so far, and have a different color).</para>

      <programlisting>Golfer( position == ( $fred.position + 1 ),
        color == "blue",
        this in ( $joe, $bob, $tom ) )      </programlisting>

      <para>Finally, we know that the golfer on the right of Fred (position + 1), is in blue pants. We also add in the constraint that he must be either Joe, Bob or Tom (as Fred can't be beside himself, well he can I guess, but not in the sense we mean here !) - note the use of "this" to refer to the current pattern, we don't really care who "this" is, just who they are not. Maybe if Fred was really really happy they this wouldn't work, but lets assume otherwise for now.</para>

      <para>Thats it ! We have expressed the rule as constraints that map to the ones expressed in the riddle, yet we haven't had to solve the riddle, the engine does that for us.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Conclusion</title>

      <para>This simple example shows how you can express a problem declaratively, and let the engine solve the problem for you, by making use of combinations. This is an often useful technique, as it allows you to express rules as a statement of the problem you are trying to solve.</para>

      <para>Of course, care must be taken. Using combinatorics like this can cause performance problems when there are large numbers of facts (eg in this case, if there were a larger number of golfers, or colors/positions etc - possibilities). When the fact count grows, the combinations the engine has to deal with can explode exponentially, making this not very efficient. However, in cases where the rules are perhaps complex, the problem is hard, but the fact numbers are relatively low, this approach can be very very useful and help you solve problems that would otherwise be very hard.</para>
    </section>

  <section>
    <title>Trouble Ticket</title>

    <para>The trouble ticket example shows how to use the duration attribute for temporal rules, and also includes an alternative version using a dsl.</para>

    <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> TroubleTicket
<emphasis role="bold">Main class:</emphasis> org.drools.examples.TroubleTicketExample, org.drools.examples.TroubleTicketExampleWithDSL
<emphasis role="bold">Type:</emphasis> java application
<emphasis role="bold">Rules file:</emphasis> TroubleTicket.drl, TroubleTicketWithDSL.dslr
<emphasis role="bold">Objective:</emphasis> Show temporal rules in action
</programlisting>

    <para>The trouble ticket example is based around the idea of raising a "ticket" (ie an issue) with a vendor (these are the vendors rules). Each customer has a subscription class assigned to it (eg Gold, Silver etc) and their class determines how the ticket is treated with respect to time, and escalating the issue. The normal drl version will be discussed here, but logically the DSL version is the same (it just uses a DSL defined language instead of the normal DRL).</para>

    <para>We have 2 types of facts, Customer and Ticket. A Ticket belongs to one and only one customer. A Customer has a name and a "subscription" type (Gold, Silver or Platinum). A ticket also has a "status" - which determines (obviously) what state it is in. The state may be set externally, or by the rules engine (eg it starts out "New", and then the system user determines that it is "Done" at some later point). The rules exist to ensure that the tickets are escalated appropriately based on the customer subscription class.</para>

    <para>Customers can choose Silver, Gold, or Platinum (in order of increasing responsiveness). Platinum subscriptions also come with a set of steak knives, and a personal butler to lodge the ticket for you (but obviously it costs more).</para>
  </section>

  </section>
