<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Sliding Length Windows</title>

  <para>Sliding Length Windows work the same way as Time Windows, but consider
  events based on order of their insertion into the session instead of flow of
  time.</para>

  <para>For instance, if the user wants to consider only the last 10 RHT Stock
  Ticks, independent of how old they are, the pattern would look like
  this:</para>

  <programlisting>StockTick( company == "RHT" ) over window:length( 10 )</programlisting>

  <para>As you can see, the pattern is similar to the one presented in the
  previous section, but instead of using window:time to define the sliding
  window, it uses window:length.</para>

  <para>Using a similar example to the one in the previous section, if the
  user wants to sound an alarm in case the average temperature over the last
  100 readings from a sensor is above the threshold value, the rule would look
  like:</para>

  <example>
    <title>aggregating values over length windows</title>

    <programlisting>rule "Sound the alarm in case temperature rises above threshold"
when
    TemperatureThreshold( $max : max )
    Number( doubleValue &gt; $max ) from accumulate(
        SensorReading( $temp : temperature ) over window:length( 100 ),
        average( $temp ) )
then
    // sound the alarm
end</programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>The engine will keep only consider the last 100 readings to calculate
  the average temperature.</para>

  <important>
    <para>Please note that falling off a length based window is not criteria
    for event expiration in the session. The engine disregards events that
    fall off a window when calculating that window, but does not remove the
    event from the session based on that condition alone as there might be
    other rules that depend on that event.</para>
  </important>

  <important>
    <para>Please note that length based windows do not define temporal
    constraints for event expiration from the session, and the engine will not
    consider them. If events have no other rules defining temporal constraints
    and no explicit expiration policy, the engine will keep them in the
    session indefinitively. </para>
  </important>
</section>
