<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Overview</title>
        <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-1-Overview/Overview.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    
    <para>This figure gives an overview of the different components of the jBPM project.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>The core engine is the heart of the project and allows you to
        execute business processes in a flexible manner.  It is a pure Java component that you can
        choose to embed as part of your application or deploy it as a service and connect
        to it through the web-based UI or remote APIs. 
          <itemizedlist>
             <listitem>An optional core service is the human task service that will take care of
             the human task life cycle if human actors participate in the process.</listitem>
             <listitem>Another optional core service is runtime persistence; this will persist the
             state of all your process instances and log audit information about everything that is
             happening at runtime.</listitem>
             <listitem>Applications can connect to the core engine by through it's Java
              API or as a set of CDI services, but also remotely through a REST and JMS API.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>Web-based tools allows you to model, simulate and deploy your processes and other
        related artifacts (like data models, forms, rules, etc.):
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>The process designer allows business users to design and simulate business processes
            in a web-based environment.</listitem>
            <listitem>The data modeler allows non-technical users to view, modify and create data models
            for use in your processes.</listitem>
            <listitem>A web-based form modeler also allows you to create, generate or
            edit forms related to your processes (to start the process or to complete one of the
            user tasks).</listitem>
            <listitem>Rule authoring allows you to specify different types of business rules (decision
            tables, guided rules, etc.) for combination with your processes.</listitem>
            <listitem>All assets are stored and managed on the Guvnor repository (exposed through GIT)
            and can be managed (versioning), built and deployed.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>The web-based management console allows business users to manage
        their runtime (manage business processes like start new processes, inspect running instances, etc.),
        to manage their task list and to perform Business Activity Monitoring (BAM) and see reports.</listitem>
        <listitem>The Eclipse-based developer tools are an extension to the Eclipse IDE, targeted towards developers,
        and allows you to create business processes using drag and drop, test and debug your processes, etc.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>Each of the components are described in more detail below.</para>
</section>