<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>What is jBPM?</title>
    <para>jBPM is a flexible Business Process Management (BPM) Suite.  It is light-weight,
    fully open-source (distributed under Apache license) and written in Java.  It allows
    you to model, execute, and monitor business processes throughout their life cycle.</para>
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" fileref="images/Chapter-1-Overview/Process.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>A business process allows you to model your business goals by describing the steps
    that need to be executed to achieve those goals, and the order of those goals are depicted
    using a flow chart. This process greatly improves the visibility and agility of your business logic.  
    jBPM focuses on executable business processes, which are business processes that contain enough detail
    so they can actually be executed on a BPM engine.  Executable business processes bridge
    the gap between business users and developers as they are higher-level and use 
    domain-specific concepts that are understood by business users but can also be executed
    directly.</para>
    
    <para>Business processes need to be supported throughout their entire life cycle: authoring, deployment,
    process management and task lists, and dashboards and reporting.</para>

    <para>The core of jBPM is a light-weight, extensible workflow engine written
    in pure Java that allows you to execute business processes using the latest
    BPMN 2.0 specification.  It can run in any Java environment, embedded in your
    application or as a service.</para>

    <para>On top of the core engine, a lot of features and tools are offered to 
    support business processes throughout their entire life cycle:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Pluggable human task service based on WS-HumanTask for including 
        tasks that need to be performed by human actors.</listitem>
        <listitem>Pluggable persistence and transactions (based on JPA / JTA).</listitem>
        <listitem>Web-based process designer to support the graphical 
        creation and simulation of your business processes (drag and drop).</listitem>
        <listitem>Web-based data modeler and form modeler to support the creation of data models and process
        and task forms</listitem>
        <listitem>Web-based, customizable dashboards and reporting</listitem>
        <listitem>All combined in one web-based workbench, supporting the complete BPM life cycle:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Modeling and deployment - author your processes, rules, data models, forms and other assets</listitem>
            <listitem>Execution - execute processes, tasks, rules and events on the core runtime engine</listitem>
            <listitem>Runtime Management - work on assigned task, manage process instances, etc</listitem>
            <listitem>Reporting - keep track of the execution using Business Activity Monitoring capabilities</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" fileref="images/Chapter-1-Overview/kie-wb.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>Eclipse-based developer tools to support the modeling, testing and debugging of processes</listitem>
        <listitem>Remote API to process engine as a service (REST, JMS, Remote Java API)</listitem>
        <listitem>Integration with Maven, Spring, OSGi, etc.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>BPM creates the bridge between business analysts, developers and end users 
    by offering process management features and tools in a way that both business 
    users and developers like.  Domain-specific nodes can be plugged into the 
    palette, making the processes more easily understood by business users.</para>

    <para>jBPM supports adaptive and dynamic processes that require flexibility to 
    model complex, real-life situations that cannot easily be described using a rigid 
    process.  We bring control back to the end users by allowing them to control which 
    parts of the process should be executed; this allows dynamic deviation from the process.</para>

    <para>jBPM is not just an isolated process engine.  Complex business logic can
    be modeled as a combination of business processes with business rules and complex
    event processing.  jBPM can be combined with the Drools project to support one unified
    environment that integrates these paradigms where you model your business logic as a 
    combination of processes, rules and events.</para>

</section>
