<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Service Repository</title>
    
  <para>A lot of these domain-specific services are generic, and can be reused by a lot of different
  users.  Think for example about integration with Twitter, doing file system operations or sending
  email.  Once such a domain-specific service has been created, you might want to make it available to
  other users so they can easily import and start using it.</para>
  
  <para>A service repository allows you to import services by browsing the repository looking for
  services you might need and importing these services into your workspace. These will then automatically
  be added to your palette and you can start using them in your processes. You can also import additional
  artefacts like for example an icon, any dependencies you might need, a default handler that will be
  used to execute the service (although you're always free to override the default, for example for
  testing), etc.</para>

  <para>To browse the repository, open the wizard to import services, point it to the right location
  (this could be to a directory in your file system but also a public or private URL) and select the
  services you would like to import.  For example, in Eclipse, right-click your project that contains
  your processes and select "Configure ... -> Import jBPM services ...".  This will open up a
  repository browser.  In the URL field, fill in the URL of your repository (see below for the URL of
  the public jBPM repository that hosts some common service implementations out-of-the-box), or use the
  "..." button to browse to a folder on your file system.  Click the Get button to retrieve the
  contents of that repository.</para>

<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" role="" 
               fileref="images/DomainSpecificProcesses/ImportService.png"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>

  <para>Select the service you would like to import and then click the Import button.  Note that
  the Eclipse wizard allows you to define whether you would like to automatically configure the
  service (so it shows up in the palette of your processes), whether you would also like to download
  any dependencies that might be needed for executing the service and/or whether you would like to
  automatically register the default handler, so make sure to mark the right checkboxes before importing
  your service (if you are unsure what to do, leaving all check boxes marked is probably best).</para>

  <para>After importing your service, (re)open your process diagram and the new service should show
  up in your palette and you can start using it in your process.  Note that most services also include
  documentation on how to use them (e.g. what the different input and output parameters are) when
  you select them browsing the service repository.</para>
  
  <para>Click on the image below to see a screencast where we import the twitter service in a new jBPM
  project and create a simple process with it that sends an actual tweet.  Note that you need the 
  necessary twitter keys and secrets to be able to programatically send tweets to your twitter account.
  How to create these is explained <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/jbpm/v6.0/repository/Twitter/">here</ulink>,
  but once you have these, you can just drop them in your project using a simple configuration file.</para>

    <ulink url="http://people.redhat.com/kverlaen/twitter-repository.swf">
      <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/DomainSpecificProcesses/Twitter.png" format="PNG" role="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </ulink>
    
<section>
  <title>Public jBPM service repository</title>
  
  <para>We are building a public service repository that contains predefined services that people 
  can use out-of-the-box if they want to:</para>

  <para><ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/jbpm/v6.0/repository/">http://docs.jboss.org/jbpm/v6.0/repository/</ulink></para>

  <para>This repository contains some integrations for common services like Twitter integration or
  file system operations that you can import.  Simply point the import wizard to this URL to start
  browsing the repository.</para>
  
  <para>If you have an implementation of a common service that you would like to contribute to the
  community, do not hesitate to contact someone from the development team.  We are always looking for
  contributions to extend our repository.</para>

</section>

<section>
  <title>Setting up your own service repository</title>
  
  <para>You can set up your own service repository and add your own services by creating a
  configuration file that contains the necessary information (this is an extended version of the
  normal work definition configuration file as described earlier in this chapter) and putting
  the necessary files (like an icon, dependencies, documentation, etc.) in the right folders.</para>
  
  <para>The extended configuration file contains the normal properties (like name, parameters,
  results and icon), with some additional ones.  For example, the following extended configuration file
  describes the Twitter integration service (as shown in the screencast above):</para>

<programlisting>
import org.drools.core.process.core.datatype.impl.type.StringDataType;
[
  [
    "name" : "Twitter",
    "description" : "Send a twitter message",
    "parameters" : [
      "Message" : new StringDataType()
    ],
    "displayName" : "Twitter",
    "eclipse:customEditor" : "org.drools.eclipse.flow.common.editor.editpart.work.SampleCustomEditor",
    "icon" : "twitter.gif",
    "category" : "Communication",
    "defaultHandler" : "org.jbpm.process.workitem.twitter.TwitterHandler",
    "documentation" : "index.html",
    "dependencies" : [
      "file:./lib/jbpm-twitter.jar",
      "file:./lib/twitter4j-core-2.2.2.jar"
    ]
  ]
]</programlisting>

<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>The icon property should refer to a file with the given file name in the same folder as
    the extended configuration file (so it can be downloaded by the import wizard and used in the process
    diagrams).  Icons should be 16x16 GIF files.</listitem>
    <listitem>The category property defines the category this service should be placed under when
    browsing the repository.</listitem>
    <listitem>The defaultHandler property defines the default handler implementation (i.e. the Java
    class that implements the <code>WorkItemHandler</code> interface and can be used to execute the
    service).  This can automatically be registered as the handler for that service
    when importing the service from the repository.</listitem>
    <listitem>The documentation property defines a documentation file that describes what the service
    does and how it works.  This property should refer to a HTML file with the given name in the same
    folder as the extended configuration file (so it can be shown by the import wizard when browsing
    the repository).</listitem>
    <listitem>The dependencies property defines additional dependencies that are necessary to execute
    this service.  This usually includes the handler implementation JAR, but could also include
    additional external dependencies.  These dependencies should also be located on the repository
    on the given location (relative to the folder where the extended configuration file is located),
    so they can be downloaded by the import wizard when importing the service.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

  <para>The root of your repository should also contain an <filename>index.conf</filename> file that
  references all the folders that should be processed when searching for services on the repository.
  Each of those folders should then contain:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>An extended configuration file with the same name as the folder (e.g.
    <filename>Twitter.conf</filename>)</listitem> that defines the service task
    <listitem>The icon as references in the configuration file</listitem>
    <listitem>The documentation as references in the configuration file</listitem>
    <listitem>The dependencies as references in the configuration file (for example in a lib folder)</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  You can create your own hierarchical structure, because if one of those folders also contains an
  <filename>index.conf</filename> file, that will be used to scan additional sub-folders.  Note that the
  hierarchical structure of the repository is not shown when browsing the repository using the import
  wizard, as the category property in the configuration file is used for that.</para>

</section>

</section>
