<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:base="./../../" xml:id="KIEModuleIntroductionBuildingIntroductionSection"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>6.0 introduces a new configuration and convention approach to building knowledge bases,
    instead of the using the programmatic builder approach in 5.x. The builder is still
    available to fall back on, as it's used for the tooling integration.</para>
  <para>Building now uses Maven, and aligns with Maven practices. A KIE project or module is simply
    a Maven Java project or module; with an additional metadata file META-INF/kmodule.xml. The
    kmodule.xml file is the descriptor that selects resources to knowledge bases and configures
    those knowledge bases and sessions. There is also alternative XML support via Spring and OSGi
    BluePrints.</para>
  <para>While standard Maven can build and package KIE resources, it will not provide validation at
    build time. There is a Maven plugin which is recommended to use to get build time validation. The
    plugin also pre-generates many classes, making the runtime loading faster too.</para>
  <para>The example project layout and Maven POM descriptor is illustrated in the screenshot</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Example project layout and Maven POM</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/kie/BuildDeployUtilizeAndRun/defaultkiesession.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>KIE uses defaults to minimise the amount of configuration. With an empty kmodule.xml being
    the simplest configuration. There must always be a kmodule.xml file, even if empty, as it's used
    for discovery of the JAR and its contents.</para>
  <para>Maven can either 'mvn install' to deploy a KieModule to the local machine, where all other
    applications on the local machine use it. Or it can 'mvn deploy' to push the KieModule to a
    remote Maven repository. Building the Application wil pull in the KieModule and populating the
    local Maven repository in the process.</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Example project layout and Maven POM</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/kie/BuildDeployUtilizeAndRun/maven.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <para>JARs can be deployed in one of two ways. Either added to the classpath, like any other JAR
    in a Maven dependency listing, or they can be dynamically loaded at runtime. KIE will scan the
    classpath to find all the JARs with a kmodule.xml in it. Each found JAR is represented by the
    KieModule interface. The terms classpath KieModule and dynamic KieModule are used to refer to the
    two loading approaches. While dynamic modules supports side by side versioning, classpath
    modules do not. Further once a module is on the classpath, no other version may be loaded
    dynamically.</para>
  <para>Detailed references for the API are included in the next sections, the impatient can jump
    straight to the examples section, which is fairly self-explanatory on the different use cases.</para>
</section>
