<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installing and using</title>

  <para>Drools provides an Eclipse-based IDE (which is optional), but at its
  core only Java 1.5 (Java SE) is required.</para>

  <para>A simple way to get started is to download and install the Eclipse
  plug-in - this will also require the Eclipse GEF framework to be installed
  (see below, if you don't have it installed already). This will provide you
  with all the dependencies you need to get going: you can simply create a new
  rule project and everything will be done for you. Refer to the chapter on
  the Rule Workbench and IDE for detailed instructions on this. Installing the
  Eclipse plug-in is generally as simple as unzipping a file into your Eclipse
  plug-in directory.</para>

  <para>Use of the Eclipse plug-in is not required. Rule files are just
  textual input (or spreadsheets as the case may be) and the IDE (also known
  as the Rule Workbench) is just a convenience. People have integrated the
  rule engine in many ways, there is no "one size fits all".</para>

  <para>Alternatively, you can download the binary distribution, and include
  the relevant jars in your projects classpath.</para>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Dependencies and jars</title>

    <para>Drools is broken down into a few modules, some are required during
    rule development/compiling, and some are required at runtime. In many
    cases, people will simply want to include all the dependencies at runtime,
    and this is fine. It allows you to have the most flexibility. However,
    some may prefer to have their "runtime" stripped down to the bare minimum,
    as they will be deploying rules in binary form - this is also possible.
    The core runtime engine can be quite compact, and only require a few 100
    kilobytes across 2 jar files.</para>

    <para>The following is a description of the important libraries that make
    up JBoss Rules</para>

    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
        <para>drools-api.jar - this provides the interfaces 
	and factories. Drools-api also helps clearly show what is intended 
	as a user api and what is just an engine api.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>drools-core.jar - this is the core engine, runtime component.
        Contains both the RETE engine and the LEAPS engine. This is the only
        runtime dependency if you are pre-compiling rules (and deploying via
        Package or RuleBase objects).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drools-compiler.jar - this contains the compiler/builder
        components to take rule source, and build executable rule bases. This
        is often a runtime dependency of your application, but it need not be
        if you are pre-compiling your rules. This depends on
        drools-core</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drools-jsr94.jar - this is the JSR-94 compliant implementation,
        this is essentially a layer over the drools-compiler component. Note
        that due to the nature of the JSR-94 specification, not all features
        are easily exposed via this interface. In some cases, it will be
        easier to go direct to the Drools API, but in some environments the
        JSR-94 is mandated.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>drools-decisiontables.jar - this is the decision tables
        'compiler' component, which uses the drools-compiler component. This
        supports both excel and CSV input formats.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>There are quite a few other dependencies which the above components
    require, most of which are for the drools-compiler, drools-jsr94 or
    drools-decisiontables module. Some key ones to
    note are "POI" which provides the
    spreadsheet parsing ability, and "antlr" which provides the parsing for
    the rule language itself.</para>

    <para>NOTE: if you are using Drools in J2EE or servlet containers and you
    come across classpath issues with "JDT", then you can switch to the janino
    compiler. Set the system property "drools.compiler": For example:
    -Ddrools.compiler=JANINO.</para>

    <para>For up to date info on dependencies in a release, consult the
    README_DEPENDENCIES.txt file, which can be found in the lib directory of
    the download bundle, or in the root of the project directory.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Runtime</title>

    <para>The "runtime" requirements mentioned here are if you are deploying
    rules as their binary form (either as KnowledgePackage objects, or KnowledgeBase objects
    etc). This is an optional feature that allows you to keep your runtime
    very light. You may use drools-compiler to produce rule packages "out of
    process", and then deploy them to a runtime system. This runtime system
    only requires drools-core.jar and drools-api for execution. This is an optional
    deployment pattern, and many people do not need to "trim" their
    application this much, but it is an ideal option for certain
    environments.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing IDE (Rule Workbench)</title>

    <para>The rule workbench (for Eclipse) requires that you have Eclipse 3.4
    or greater, as well as Eclipse GEF 3.4 or greater. You can install it
    either by downloading the plug-in or, or using the update site.</para>

    <para>Another option is to use the JBoss IDE, which comes with all the
    plug-in requirements pre packaged, as well as a choice of other tools
    separate to rules. You can choose just to install rules from the "bundle"
    that JBoss IDE ships with.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing GEF (a required dependency)</title>

      <para>GEF is the Eclipse Graphical Editing Framework, which is used for
      graph viewing components in the plug-in.</para>

      <para>If you don't have GEF installed, you can install it using the
      built in update mechanism (or downloading GEF from the Eclipse.org
      website not recommended). JBoss IDE has GEF already, as do many other "distributions" of
      Eclipse, so this step may be redundant for some people.</para>

      <para>Open the Help-&gt;Software updates...-&gt;Available Software-&gt;Add Site...
      from the help menu. Location is:</para>

	  <programlisting>http://download.eclipse.org/tools/gef/updates/releases/</programlisting>
	
      <para>Next you choose the GEF plug-in:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/install_gef.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Press next, and agree to install the plug-in (an Eclipse restart
      may be required). Once this is completed, then you can continue on
      installing the rules plug-in.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing GEF from zip file</title>

      <para>To install from the zip file, download and unzip the file. Inside
      the zip you will see a plug-in directory, and the plug-in jar itself. You
      place the plug-in jar into your Eclipse applications plug-in directory,
      and restart Eclipse.</para>
 
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing Drools plug-in from zip file</title>

    <para>Download the Drools Eclipse
    IDE plugin from the link below. Unzip the downloaded file in your main eclipse folder
    (do not just copy the file there, extract it so that the feature and plugin jars end
    up in the features and plugin directory of eclipse) and (re)start Eclipse.</para>
    
    <para><ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/drools/downloads.html">http://www.jboss.org/drools/downloads.html</ulink></para>

    <para>To check that the installation was successful, try opening the Drools perspective:
    Click the 'Open Perspective' button in the top right corner of your Eclipse window,
    select 'Other...' and pick the Drools perspective.  If you cannot find the Drools perspective
    as one of the possible perspectives, the installation probably was unsuccessful. Check
    whether you executed each of the required steps correctly: Do you have the right version
    of Eclipse (3.4.x)?  Do you have Eclipse GEF installed (check whether the org.eclipse.gef_3.4.*.jar
    exists in the plugins directory in your eclipse root folder)? Did you extract the Drools Eclipse
    plugin correctly (check whether the org.drools.eclipse_*.jar exists in the plugins directory in
    your eclipse root folder)?  If you cannot find the problem, try contacting us (e.g. on irc or on
    the user mailing list), more info can be found no our homepage here:</para>
    <para><ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/drools/">http://www.jboss.org/drools/</ulink></para> 
    </section>  
    <section>
		<title>Drools Runtimes</title>
  <para>A Drools runtime is a collection of jars on your file system that represent
    one specific release of the Drools project jars. To create a runtime, you must 
    point the IDE to the release of your choice.  If you want to create a new runtime
    based on the latest Drools project jars included in the plugin itself, you can also
    easily do that.  You are required to specify a default Drools runtime for your
    Eclipse workspace, but each individual project can override the default and select
    the appropriate runtime for that project specifically.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Defining a Drools runtime</title>

      <para>You are required to define one or more Drools runtimes using the Eclipse preferences
      view.  To open up your preferences, in the menu Window select the Preferences
      menu item.  A new preferences dialog should show all your preferences.  On the
      left side of this dialog, under the Drools category, select "Installed Drools
      runtimes".  The panel on the right should then show the currently defined Drools
      runtimes.  If you have not yet defined any runtimes, it should like something like
      the figure below.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>To define a new Drools runtime, click on the add button.  A dialog as shown
      below should pop up, requiring the name for your runtime and the location on your
      file system where it can be found.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes-add.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>In general, you have two options:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>If you simply want to use the default jars as included in the Drools
        Eclipse plugin, you can create a new Drools runtime automatically by clicking the
        "Create a new Drools 5 runtime ..." button.  A file browser will show up, asking
        you to select the folder on your file system where you want this runtime to be
        created.  The plugin will then automatically copy all required dependencies to
        the specified folder.  After selecting this folder, the dialog should look like
        the figure shown below.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>If you want to use one specific release of the Drools project, you should
        create a folder on your file system that contains all the necessary Drools libraries
        and dependencies.  Instead of creating a new Drools runtime as explained above, give
        your runtime a name and select the location of this folder containing all the required
        jars.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes-add2.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>After clicking the OK button, the runtime should show up in your table of installed
      Drools runtimes, as shown below.  Click on checkbox in front of the newly created runtime 
      to make it the default Drools runtime.  The default Drools runtime will be used as the
      runtime of all your Drools project that have not selected a project-specific runtime.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes2.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can add as many Drools runtimes as you need.  For example, the screenshot below
      shows a configuration where three runtimes have been defined: a Drools 4.0.7 runtime, a
      Drools 5.0.0 runtime and a Drools 5.0.0.SNAPSHOT runtime.  The Drools 5.0.0 runtime is
      selected as the default one.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes3.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Note that you will need to restart Eclipse if you changed the default runtime and
      you want to make sure that all the projects that are using the default runtime update
      their classpath accordingly.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Selecting a runtime for your Drools project</title>

      <para>Whenever you create a Drools project (using the New Drools Project wizard or by
      converting an existing Java project to a Drools project using the "Convert to Drools
      Project" action that is shown when you are in the Drools perspective and you right-click
      an existing Java project), the plugin will automatically add all the required jars to
      the classpath of your project.</para>

      <para>When creating a new Drools project, the plugin will automatically use the default
      Drools runtime for that project, unless you specify a project-specific one.  You can do
      this in the final step of the New Drools Project wizard, as shown below, by deselecting
      the "Use default Drools runtime" checkbox and selecting the appropriate runtime in the
      drop-down box.  If you click the "Configure workspace settings ..." link, the workspace
      preferences showing the currently installed Drools runtimes will be opened, so you can
      add new runtimes there.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes-newproject.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>You can change the runtime of a Drools project at any time by opening the project
      properties (right-click the project and select Properties) and selecting the Drools
      category, as shown below.  Check the "Enable project specific settings" checkbox and select
      the appropriate runtime from the drop-down box.  If you click the "Configure workspace
      settings ..." link, the workspace preferences showing the currently installed Drools
      runtimes will be opened, so you can add new runtimes there.  If you deselect the "Enable
      project specific settings" checkbox, it will use the default runtime as defined in your
      global preferences.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Chapter-Install/drools-runtimes-project.png" format="PNG" role="" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

    </section> 
	</section>
</section>
<!--
    <section>
      <title>Installing from the update site</title>

      <para>Using the update site is a handy way to install the plug-in, and
      keep it up to date (the Eclipse platform will check for updates as
      needed). It gives you a good chance of staying up to date with
      improvements, fixes etc.</para>

      <para>Some firewalls may cause trouble with using update sites in
      Eclipse, if you have issues, then install it manually from the plug-in.
      Also, if you have previously installed the plug-in manually, you will
      need to manually remove it from your plug-in directory.</para>

      <para>Step 1. Use the Eclipse help menu to find the feature installer.
      <screenshot>
          <info>Access the software updates menu</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/help_menu.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 2: Choose the option for installing a new feature (obviously
      in future, if you want to check for updates, you use the other option
      !). <screenshot>
          <info>Search for new features</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/search_new_features.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 3: This screen will show what update sites are already
      configured for your Eclipse instance. <screenshot>
          <info>Update sites</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/update_sites_existing.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 4: This screen is where you enter in the remote site details.
      You give it a name eg "JBoss Drools" and the url. <programlisting> Check the Drools IDE Update Site section of the Drools Downloads webpage: 
				http://labs.jboss.com/drools/downloads.html</programlisting>
      <screenshot>
          <info>New remote site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/new_remote_site.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 5: Select the new update site you just added. Eclipse will
      remember this for when it checks for updates automatically in the
      future. <screenshot>
          <info>Choose the newly added update site</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/update_sites.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 6: You should see the available features (Drools IDE)
      retrieved from the update site. <screenshot>
          <info>Available features</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/search_results.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 7: The license agreement. Choose the option to accept the
      license agreement. Once this happens, the workbench will start
      downloading. Might be an opportune time to go have a coffee. <screenshot>
          <info>License</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/licence.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 8: Confirm that this is the feature you want. <screenshot>
          <info>Confirmation</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/confirm.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 9: Press Accept to accept the fact that the feature is not
      digitally signed. No one signs their features, its a silly default
      screen in Eclipse. <screenshot>
          <info>Verify</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/digital_sign.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Step 10: The workbench will need to restart now for the feature to
      take effect. <screenshot>
          <info>Restart the workbench</info>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-Install/restart.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot></para>

      <para>Now go have another coffee, and then take a look at the chapter on
      the Rule Workbench for what you can do with it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
-->
</section>
