<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Deploying</title>

  <section>
    <title>KnowledgePackage and Knowledge Definitions</title>

    <para>A Knowledge Package is a collection of Knowledge Definitions, such
    as rules and processes. It is created by the Knowledge Builder, as
    described in the chapter "Building". Knowledge Packages are self-contained and
    serializable, and they currently form the basic deployment unit.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>KnowledgePackage</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Chapter-User_Guide/KnowledgePackage.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Knowledge Packages are added to the Knowledge Base. However, a
    Knowledge Package instance cannot be reused once it's added to the
    Knowledge Base. If you need to add it to another Knowledge Base, try
    serializing it first and using the "cloned" result. We hope to fix this
    limitation in future versions of Drools.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>KnowledgeBase</title>

    <para>The Knowledge Base is a repository of all the application's knowledge
    definitions. It may contain rules, processes, functions, and type models.
    The Knowledge Base itself does not contain instance data, known as facts;
    instead, sessions are created from the Knowledge Base into which data can be
    inserted and where process instances may be started. Creating the
    Knowledge Base can be
    heavy, whereas session creation is very light, so it is recommended that
    Knowledge Bases be cached where possible to allow for repeated session
    creation.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>KnowledgeBase</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-User_Guide/KnowledgeBase.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A <code>KnowledgeBase</code> object is also serializable, and some people
    may prefer to build and then store a <code>KnowledgeBase</code>, treating it also 
    as a unit of deployment, instead of the Knowledge Packages.</para>

    <para>The KnowledgeBase is created using the KnowledgeBaseFactory.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>KnowledgeBaseFactory</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-User_Guide/KnowledgeBaseFactory.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A KnowledgeBase can be created using the default
    configuration.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Creating a new KnowledgeBase</title>

      <programlisting language="java">KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>If a custom class loader was used with the <code>KnowledgeBuilder</code> to
    resolve types not in the default class loader, then that must also be set
    on the <code>KnowledgeBase</code>. The technique for this is the same as with the
    <code>KnowledgeBuilder</code>.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Creating a new KnowledgeBase with a custom ClassLoader</title>

      <programlisting language="java">KnowledgeBaseConfiguration kbaseConf =
    KnowledgeBaseFactory.createKnowledgeBaseConfiguration( null, cl );
KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase( kbaseConf );</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>In-Process Building and Deployment</title>

    <para>This is the simplest form of deployment. It compiles the
    knowledge definitions and adds them to the Knowledge Base in the same JVM.
    This approach requires drools-core.jar and drools-compiler.jar to be on
    the classpath.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Add KnowledgePackages to a KnowledgeBase</title>

      <programlisting language="java">Collection&lt;KnowledgePackage&gt; kpkgs = kbuilder.getKnowledgePackages();

KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kpkgs );</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Note that the <code>addKnowledgePackages(kpkgs)</code> method can be called
    iteratively to add additional knowledge.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Building and Deployment in Separate Processes</title>

    <para>Both the <code>KnowledgeBase</code> and the <code>KnowledgePackage</code>
    are units of
    deployment and serializable. This means you can have one machine do any
    necessary building, requiring <filename>drools-compiler.jar</filename>, and
    have another machine deploy and execute everything, needing only
    <filename>drools-core.jar</filename>.</para>

    <para>Although serialization is standard Java, we present an example of
    how one  machine might write out the deployment unit and how another 
    machine might read in and use that deployment unit.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Writing the KnowledgePackage to an OutputStream</title>

      <programlisting language="java">ObjectOutputStream out = new ObjectOutputStream( new FileOutputStream( fileName ) );
out.writeObject( kpkgs );
out.close();
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Reading the KnowledgePackage from an InputStream</title>

      <programlisting language="java">ObjectInputStream in = new ObjectInputStream( new FileInputStream( fileName ) );
// The input stream might contain an individual
// package or a collection.
@SuppressWarnings( "unchecked" )
Collection&lt;KnowledgePackage&gt; kpkgs =
    ()in.readObject( Collection&lt;KnowledgePackage&gt; );
in.close();

KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();
kbase.addKnowledgePackages( kpkgs );
</programlisting>
    </example>

      <para>The <code>KnowledgeBase</code> is also serializable and some people may prefer
      to build and then store the <code>KnowledgeBase</code> itself, instead of the
      Knowledge Packages.</para>

      <para>Drools Guvnor, our server side management system, uses this
      deployment approach. After Guvnor has compiled and published serialized
      Knowledge Packages on a URL, Drools can use the URL resource type
      to load them.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>StatefulknowledgeSessions and KnowledgeBase Modifications</title>

    <para>Stateful Knowledge Sessions will be discussed in more detail in
    section "Running". The <code>KnowledgeBase</code> creates and returns
    <code>StatefulKnowledgeSession</code> objects, and it may optionally
    keep references to those.
    When <code>KnowledgeBase</code> modifications occur those modifications are applied
    against the data in the sessions. This reference is a weak reference and it
    is also optional, which is controlled by a boolean flag.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>KnowledgeAgent</title>

    <para>The <code>KnowlegeAgent</code> provides automatic loading, caching and
    re-loading of resources and is configured from a properties files. The
    Knowledge Agent can update or rebuild this Knowlege Base as the
    resources it uses are changed. The strategy for this is determined by the configuration
    given to the factory, but it is typically pull-based using regular
    polling. We hope to add push-based updates and rebuilds in future
    versions. The Knowledge Agent will continuously scan all the added
    resources, using a default polling interval of 60 seconds. If their 
    date of the last modification is updated it will rebuild the cached
    Knowledge Base using the new resources.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>KnowledgeAgent</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-User_Guide/KnowledgeAgent.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The <code>KnowlegeBuilder</code> is created using a
    <code>KnowledgeBuilderFactory</code> object.
    The agent must specify a name, which is used in the log files to associate
    a log entry with the corresponding agent.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Creating the KnowledgeAgent</title>

      <programlisting language="java">KnowledgeAgent kagent = KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgent( "MyAgent" );
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <figure>
      <title>KnowledgeAgentFactory</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="100%"
                     fileref="images/Chapter-User_Guide/KnowledgeAgentFactory.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The following example constructs an agent that will build a new
    KnowledgeBase from the specified ChangeSet. (See section "Building" for
    more details on the ChangeSet format.) Note that the method can be called
    iteratively to add new resources over time. 
    The Knowledge Agent polls the resources added from the ChangeSet 
    every 60 seconds, the default interval, to see if they are updated.
    Whenever changes are found it will construct a new Knowledge Base or apply
    the modifications to the existing Knowledge Base according to its
    configuration.
    If the change set specifies a resource that
    is a directory its contents will be scanned for changes, too.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Writing the KnowledgePackage to an OutputStream</title>

      <programlisting language="java">KnowledgeAgent kagent = KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgent( "MyAgent" );
kagent.applyChangeSet( ResourceFactory.newUrlResource( url ) );
KnowledgeBase kbase = kagent.getKnowledgeBase();
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Resource scanning is not on by default, it's a service and must be
    started, and the same is true for notification. Both can be done via the
    ResourceFactory.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Starting the Scanning and Notification Services</title>

      <programlisting language="java">ResourceFactory.getResourceChangeNotifierService().start();
ResourceFactory.getResourceChangeScannerService().start();
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>The default resource scanning period may be changed via the
    <code>ResourceChangeScannerService</code>. A suitably updated 
    <code>ResourceChangeScannerConfiguration</code> object is passed to the service's
    <code>configure()</code> method, which allows for the service to be reconfigured on
    demand.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Changing the Scanning Intervals</title>

      <programlisting language="java">ResourceChangeScannerConfiguration sconf =
    ResourceFactory.getResourceChangeScannerService().newResourceChangeScannerConfiguration();
// Set the disk scanning interval to 30s, default is 60s.
sconf.setProperty( "drools.resource.scanner.interval", "30" ); 
ResourceFactory.getResourceChangeScannerService().configure( sconf );
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Knowledge Agents can take an empty Knowledge Base or a populated one.
    If a populated Knowledge Base is provided, the Knowledge Agent will
    run an iterator from Knowledge Base and subscribe to the resources that
    it finds. While it is
    possible for the Knowledge Builder to build all resources found in a
    directory, that information is lost by the Knowledge Builder so that those
    directories will not be continuously scanned. Only directories specified
    as part of the <code>applyChangeSet(Resource)</code> method are monitored.</para>

    <para>One of the advantages of providing <code>KnowledgeBase</code> as the starting
    point is that you can provide it with a <code>KnowledgeBaseConfiguration</code>. When
    resource changes are detected and a new <code>KnowledgeBase</code> object is
    instantiated, it will use the <code>KnowledgeBaseConfiguration</code> of the previous
    <code>KnowledgeBase</code> object.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Using an existing KnowledgeBase</title>

      <programlisting language="java">KnowledgeBaseConfiguration kbaseConf =
    KnowledgeBaseFactory.createKnowledgeBaseConfiguration( null, cl );
KnowledgeBase kbase KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase( kbaseConf );
// Populate kbase with resources here.

KnowledgeAgent kagent =
    KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgent( "MyAgent", kbase );
KnowledgeBase kbase = kagent.getKnowledgeBase();
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>In the above example <code>getKnowledgeBase()</code> will return the same
    provided kbase instance until resource changes are detected and a new
    Knowledge Base is built. When the new Knowledge Base is built, it will be
    done with the <code>KnowledgeBaseConfiguration</code> that was provided to 
    the previous <code>KnowledgeBase</code>.</para>

    <para>As mentioned previously, a ChangeSet XML can specify a directory and
    all of its contents will be added. If this ChangeSet XML is used with the
    <code>applyChangeSet()</code> method it will also add any directories to the scanning
    process. When the directory scan detects an additional file, it will be 
    added to the Knowledge Base; any removed file is removed from the
    Knowledge Base, and modified files will be removed from the Knowledge Base.
    </para>

    <example>
      <title>ChangeSet XML which adds a directories contents</title>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;change-set xmlns='http://drools.org/drools-5.0/change-set'
            xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
            xs:schemaLocation='http://drools.org/drools-5.0/change-set.xsd' &gt;
   &lt;add&gt;
      &lt;resource source='file:/projects/myproject/myrules' type='PKG' /&gt;
   &lt;/add&gt;
&lt;/change-set&gt;
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Note that for the resource type PKG the drools-compiler dependency is
    not needed as the Knowledge Agent is able to handle those with just
    drools-core.</para>

    <para>The <code>KnowledgeAgentConfiguration</code> can be used to modify a
    Knowledge Agent's default behavior. You could use this to load
    the resources from a directory, while inhibiting the continuous scan
    for changes of that directory.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Change the Scanning Behavior</title>

      <programlisting language="java">KnowledgeBase kbase = KnowledgeBaseFactory.newKnowledgeBase();

KnowledgeAgentConfiguration kaconf =
    KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgentConfiguation();
// Do not scan directories, just files.
kaconf.setProperty( "drools.agent.scanDirectories", "false" );
KnowledgeAgent kagent =
    KnowledgeAgentFactory.newKnowledgeAgent( "test agent", kaconf );
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Previously we mentioned Drools Guvnor and how it can build and
    publish serialized Knowledge Packages on a URL, and that the
    ChangeSet XML can handle URLs and Packages. Taken together, this forms
    an importanty deployment scenario for the Knowledge Agent.</para>
  </section>
</section>
